<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>3:AM Magazine</title>
	<atom:link href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am</link>
	<description>Whatever it is, we&#039;re against it</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 08:00:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.4.1</generator>
		<item>
		<title>The game of (not) life</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-game-of-not-life/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-game-of-not-life/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2013 08:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amy Marrs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[art]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lynton Wells]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Halley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Coover]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56620</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Bang-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="Bang" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56628" /></p>

After running simulations for many millions of generations, <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em> evolved the ability to create miniature games of life. And that is precisely what institutional art does – it cowers behind the protocols of the marketplace and institution, and like a virus mindlessly replicates itself and its practitioners. Too much more of this and the art world will calcify into another beaux-arts academy, or worse yet, for those of us who still believe in the radical potential of the image, art may become fixed, becoming something akin to Kabuki theatre and not budge from its forms and function for centuries.

By <strong>James McGirk</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/conwaygameoflife.jpg" alt="" title="conwaygameoflife" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56625" /></p>
<p>[Image: <a href="http://www.math.cornell.edu/~lipa/mec/lesson6.html">Cornell Math Explorer's Club</a>]</p>
<p>By James McGirk.</p>
<p>There is no better analogy for contemporary art than <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em>. This is not the same thing as <em>The Game of Life</em>, which is played on a board and simulates the education and subsequent useful employment of a human being. <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em> is a math game, an evolution simulator simple enough to be played on a checkerboard, but most often encountered on a computer. In the game, three rules govern whether or not an individual “cell” lives, dies or reproduces. The operator places pixels on a grid. Each turn the pixels either disappear or reproduce, gradually linking up and evolving into complicated patterns. After hundreds of generations these patterns begin to exhibit remarkable behaviour — some oscillate like machines or glide around the board depositing seeds, but no matter how many generations pass, no matter how infinite the number ofpermutations possible, <em>Conway’s</em> creatures are a constrained infinity; their patterns will never rupture the protocols that created them, for example they will never tip over into another dimension the way Jackson Pollock did when he tipped his canvas over and began dribbling paint on it from above. The problem with contemporary art today is that like the writhing patterns of <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em> it is snarled, hopelessly snarled, in the protocols of a larger, more insidious system.</p>
<p>Art feeds off of disposable income. Money may be delivered directly to an artist or as is more often the case in the professional art world, the money will be mediated through galleries or fellowships or institutional support. The collapse of Lehman Brothers and subsequent implosion of the economy in 2008 evaporated a great deal of disposable income. Yet according &#8216;How to Make it in the Art World,&#8217; an article published in <em>New York</em> magazine, the art world is thriving, albeit in a “weird moment of equipoise, as the Art Death Star and the Rebel Forces [battle] to the quick.” <em>New York</em>’s art critic Jerry Saltz and his fellow <em>New York</em> writers trace a “billion-dollar unregulated market” with “case studies” that include Sarah Sze, whose massive billowing bricolage mobiles suggest networks and systems; Kehinde Wiley’s sumptuous portraits of marginal others in luxurious garb that are so in demand by wealthy collectors, the artist has partially outsourced his production to China and Senegal, and myriad other collectors and gallerists and artists who, according to Saltz and his crew, hew to “impish contradictions” with “everyone act[ing] like they’re overthrowing the system by thriving in it.”</p>
<p>To Saltz the art world has fractured into thousands of interdependent cliques that are evolving in little clusters, dribbling currency and cross-pollinating one another. He is giddy about the carnivalesque atmosphere, and after a meltdown at Art Basel now sees “art fairs as cultural-biomasses: survival mechanisms where galleries act like great schools of fish, banding together in like groups that allow more to thrive, confusing and eluding predators.” But if you squint at the dozens of artists producing what would charitably be referred to as exploded Cornell boxes of artfully arranged garbage, the discombobulated videogames, and all the howling neons and punky scrawls that pervade contemporary art they will all seem suspiciously similar. If there were a single thread connecting all of these disparate forms it is the ability to snag an intriguing lead from a lazy writer/blogger and extract strands of quivering quasi-academic snot from the agar of the artwork. </p>
<div align="center">*</div>
<p>Art takes time and effort to produce. To paraphrase Walter Benjamin’s <em>The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction</em> this meant art was once a ritual activity, a sort of sacrifice of productive labour on behalf of a deity or a monarch, and for millennia this relationship meant that images had an inherent sacredness built into to them (doubly so because images themselves were so rare). This aura gradually eroded as images became more common, first through the patronage of the merchant class, and later at an exponentially faster rate through the advent of technologies like the printing press and photography. To repel the onslaught of all these cheap imitations, the work of art had to dig a niche for itself, which meant recognising itself in the context of all the art that had come before it. Art was authentic, more than a mere product, an intellectual achievement, a delicate soufflé of the eons of history that had come before it. Each work of art became a piece of intellectual property, like a master tape, no different than a scribble of expertly produced code. Authenticity lodged a fungible, wordy void within art that connected it to the rest of art history. Discourse about a piece of work and artist’s statements became as important as the work itself. How else do you justify a painted plank of wood or canvas being worth more than its materials and labour?</p>
<p>This squib of text within, however, like an undefended wireless Internet connection, left the work of art vulnerable to hijack by sinister forces, and that is precisely what happened. As context became increasingly important to the discourse about art, to the point where it began to influence the artists creating it, the emphasis of the work began to shift away from appearance and form to the work of art’s position within a network of interdependent intellectual and historical constituencies, and the work of art became something you read rather than looked at.</p>
<p>This was not a good thing. Vision is a far stranger and more complicated process than language. What we see is extremely subjective. The light absorbed by our rods and conesis just one feed of information in an assemblage that more closely resembles The Terminator’s LED augmented vision than the output of a video camera. Imagine a uniform white surface suddenly descending on your field of vision. It would be intensely threatening if it were unexpected, yet perhaps less so if the signal were received in a Bed Bath and Beyond than while walking over an icy crevasse, yet depending on factors such as knowing that you are at risk of a stroke or an accompanying reek of chloroform, one might still be compelled to shriek for help.</p>
<p>Viewers project layers of meaning onto what they see, and like language, some of this is coded and contextual, and consists of logic and syntax that can be learned and manipulated with language. (A famous demonstration of the sort of subterranean optic education we receive as technologically adept Westerners occurred in Africa in the 1950s when anthropologists working with tribesmen discovered that a viewer had to understand that film was a two-dimensional representation before being able to interpret footage of their surroundings.) But there are also countless numbers of unconscious and semi-conscious subroutines at play. By allowing language to hijack interpretation, the work of art pushes code into the foreground and ignores the dank, potentially gorgeous mysteries of vision. The work of art is then no different really than the glider guns sputtering across the board of <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em>.</p>
<div align="center">*</div>
<p>Visual art that relies on historical context and academic discourse retards itself. That said, in the heyday of poststructuralism, between the 1970s and early 1990s, there was a lot great work produced that explored and exposed the relationship between language and image. Cindy Sherman staged scenes, creating phony film stills that recalled just enough of the iconography of cinema, itself a fusion between language and vision, to almost but not quite, invoke narrative. Her work unpeeled provocative insights into how much of narrative is unconsciously transmitted, and how pigheaded and strange those unconscious chunks of narrative could be. But once you made that connection, once you read Cindy Sherman’s beautiful work as another way to <em>épater le bourgeois</em>, it seemed thinner. The way that walking home from someplace new will always seem less exciting (and shorter) than it did on the way out there.</p>
<p>Sherman’s contemporary Peter Halley refined the rupture between language and reality with a near mathematical precision. He used the protocols of both post-structural criticism and geometric abstraction to reveal the relationship between code and visual representation. He fore-grounded his paintings with syntax, using a severely restrictedpalette of forms, usually just two, cells and conduits, skinny blocks of colour representing conduits and fatter ones representing cells, to create paintings that look like circuit boards. He paired these schematic-like images with an intensely precise and absolutelycrucial title. <em>Revolver</em> (2009), for example, is a triptych, with each of its three panesshowing a series of nested rectangles (four of them, then five, then only three) that convey the chemical and mechanical innards, the heft and the firing mechanism of a revolver. The colours, a combination of black with metallic tones and textures, the series of shapes (the symmetry of four ruptured into five and then left with only three) all refer back to the title; without the word “revolver” these shapes and colors would be meaningless, yet the colours and textures reveal how arbitrary and categorical the word “revolver” really is when compared with the vitality of the thing itself. That is if you reassure yourself that the painting is about handguns exclusively and not, say for example, The Beatles album bearing the same name. And yet for all this sophisticated interplay the work is bloodless and academic. This may well be intentional, a rebuke to the increasingly clotted and academic art world, but because of his reliance on language, when placed beside a painting that brings the full resources of the artist to bear on his medium, Halley’s work is wanting.</p>
<p>Mark Rothko worked at a similar (i.e. gargantuan scale) to Peter Halley, yet by choosing to dwell within the darker, unknowable realms of vision, Rothko’s work achieved an effect far more transcendent than Halley. Simon Schama describes the moment he first encountered a Rothko in BBC’s <em>Power of Art</em>, taking a wrong turn in the Tate Museum and walking into a dimly lit room: “Something in there was throbbing steadily, pulsing like the inside of a body part, all crimson and purple. I felt I was being pulled through those black lines to some mysterious place in the universe.” Rothko used light, size, colour and a larger-than-life scale to swallow his viewers and put them through a spin cycle of optical effects. He didn’t need academic discourse to achieve his ends. Where Halley methodically combined post-structuralism and the techniques of geometric abstraction, Rothko used the more ambiguous but powerful vocabulary of his medium to communicate. And that is where the power of art resides. A work of art that relies on its affiliations or an artist’s statement to ground its viewer hobbles itself.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Bang.jpg" alt="" title="Bang" width="590" height="557" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56628" /><br />
[Image: 'Bang Goes Theory', <a href="http://www.waddingtoncustot.com/exhibition/halley2013/">Waddington Custot Galleries</a>]</p>
<div align="center">*</div>
<p>Grounding is also known as quilting, suggesting that one is stitched into a patchwork of associations. Or, to recall <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em>, placed onto a checkerboard and subject to three evolutionary rules. Both “grounding” and “quilting” are an elaborate way of saying: “to prime.” How a viewer is primed to approach a work of art is crucial to its interpretation. A work of art is a bit like an electrical circuit. Without a viewer to complete the circuit, a work of art can do nothing. Not only does this make the experience of interpreting a work of art an inherently subjective one, it also tips the balance of power away from the artist. If this seems hyperbolic, on a micro scale it is. An individual work of art can always snag someone’s attention and obliterate whatever flimsy strands of context the viewer is screening the work through. But consider for a moment how artwork is actually distributed to a viewer’s optic nerve.</p>
<p>The relationship with the viewer has flipped. As a glance at <a href="http://www.deviantart.com/">deviantART</a> or a ramble through any open studio night anywhere will prove, there is now a practically unlimited supply of artwork to look at. An artist must seek out his or her viewer. And there now exists a bureaucracy mediating who gets to see what art where and when. To extend the circuit analogy, when people talk about the art world they mean something akin to an electric grid, a system which connects works of art to a scarce supply of viewers. Like the utilities, which mandate certain conditions in exchange for a steady supply of electricity (namely that you pay your bills on time and that your appliances do not feed electricity back into the grid), the art world is dominated by an oligopoly of a few powerful tastemakers who, like the utility companies, will only supply viewers to those who conform to their standards. Which is why the secondary economies of galleries and museums, and tertiary economy of tastemakers and critics are so important: viewers need somebody sift through all of that art and tell them what is worth looking at.</p>
<p>This is not a conspiracy. While most of the people involved in the business of distributing viewers to works of art, particularly those who work in the non-profit sector, likely consider themselves to be working in the service of art, even the most noble among them are dealing with a different set of agendas than the artists are. Artists no longer define what art is, institutions and auctioneers do. Art has allowed itself to become restrained by the marketplace and the academy. These are both systems which ultimately shunt artwork beneath the protocols of something else. They both attempt to quantify and restrain artwork through systems of logic.</p>
<p>An artist’s labour only provides a sliver of value to their work in the marketplace. The rest comes from exchange. “The relationship of money to any individual piece of art is very simple,” writes critic and former art dealer Dave Hickey in <em>Air Guitar: Essays on Art and Democracy</em>. “There is none. Since relative economic value can only be assigned to sets of things (to works of one artist, one period, one style, et cetera), and since even one-of-a-kind objects are valued within the set of “one-of-a-kind objects” (Catherine the Great’s dildo as compared to Louis the XIV’s bedpan), any work of art is both worthless and priceless because it <em>is</em> unique… Everything you pay over [a culturally ascribed minimum value of approximately three hundred to one thousand dollars] is the consequence of previous external investments taken at risk.”</p>
<p>In a perfect marketplace, where all consumers and suppliers have the same information, which is to say all suppliers are capable of delivering the same product to all consumers, and all consumers are capable of buying the same piece of work at the same time, a work of art might do well to preserve its autonomy and stand out from its peers. But the art world is anything but fair. There is no equivalent of the Securities and Exchange Commission. Certain galleries and collectors have far better access to work than others do, which leaves the marketplace for art deeply crooked. Unscrupulous galleries often collude with collectors to inflate prices. Considering how easy it is to anonymously purchase art worth millions of dollars and transfer it from person to person, it is an open secret that many use the art world to evade taxes and launder money. This corruption actually affects the way that the work of art is made. The marketplace assigns a qualitative value to sets of art, and by extension ascribes value to certain techniques or images or styles within art, and by establishing a hierarchy of forms encourages others to adopt the same stance, creating pastiches of art, near-art more approachable to salesmen and collectors than real art, which in turn crowds out the potentially unique and presumably better real stuff.</p>
<p>Institutions and not-for-profits are more insidious still, at least galleries and collectors have a lot of autonomy in their decision making, which although it may privilege certain forms and inflate the value of some awfully crappy artwork, at least allows for a fair amount of creative destruction. This is not the case within the academy. “In institutional cultures there is neither failure nor success, only the largesse or spite of one’s superiors,” writes Hickey. “We continue to presume honest virtue in those art functionaries who receive salaries, ideally from public sources… Through the exquisite logic of Protestant economic determinism, virtue is ascribed to those who can afford to live nice, regular middle-class lives as a consequence of their submission to whatever authority dispenses their salary.”</p>
<p>For art to pass muster it must be vetted through multiple layers of professional bureaucrats (some in the guise of grant-holding artists and professors) and what the industry refers to as stakeholders, constituencies either real or imagined within the institution that are thought to care about the decision. These range from donors who must be appeased, to boards of directors to the press, to the public, to peer institutions, to other decision makers and to more abstracted stakes like the institution’s mission or the director’s boneheaded attempts at social engineering. Few people enmeshed in a gigantic, conservative institution will gamble on an extreme piece of artwork, and more often than not will attempt to mitigate risk and facilitate their decision-making by looking forsignifiers of success such as affiliations, other shows, pedigree or a familiar socioeconomic background. </p>
<p>Remember those impish contradictions, those effortless juxtapositions of high and low that Jerry Saltz and his team applauded? The young artists “breaking barriers between genres,” the cheeky suggestion that to succeed one must: “Join the establishment. Cling to your street cred… Pretend you’re an outsider even when you’re at the center of everything… Get born into it.” Jamming between discourses (“radical egalitarianism”) is characteristic of today’s “new elite,” writes Prof. Shamus Khan in <em>Privilege: The Making of an Adolescent Elite at St. Paul’s School</em>. “Privilege is not an attempt to construct boundaries around knowledge and protect such knowledge as a resource. Ironically, exclusivity marks the losers in the hierarchical, open society. From this perspective, inequality is explained not by the practices of the elite but instead by the character of the disadvantaged. Their limited (exclusive) knowledge, tastes, and dispositions mean they have not seized upon the fruits of our newly open system.” </p>
<p>After running simulations for many millions of generations, <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em> evolved the ability to create miniature games of life. And that is precisely what institutional art does – it cowers behind the protocols of the marketplace and institution, and like a virus mindlessly replicates itself and its practitioners. Too much more of this and the art world will calcify into another beaux-arts academy, or worse yet, for those of us who still believe in the radical potential of the image, art may become fixed, becoming something akin to Kabuki theatre and not budge from its forms and function for centuries.</p>
<div align="center">*</div>
<p>Contemporary art has become a heat sink of associations and affiliations, so much so that barely any representation can resist being drawn into a preexisting framework of interpretation. Yet there are pockets of resistance.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.lyntonwells.info/">Lynton Wells</a> has developed a visual language that is toxic to logic but so technicallyprecise and exquisitely rendered it forces his viewer to rely on other senses. He paints realistic, yet anthropomorphic, frogs and fishes and other icons of western myth (such as nude faeries and trees) and places them into colourful, complex backgrounds that faintly recall Gerhard Richter. <a href="http://www.lyntonwells.info/paintingtrial.html"><em>Fish, James</em></a> (2010-2011), for example, features an arched rainbow trout clutching a fishing line that curls into a swirling filigree of plant-life and an abstract churning pattern against a background as strange and ominous as a prairie sky before a storm.</p>
<p>Dan Flavin and Mark Rothko dimmed the lights to defamilarise their viewers. Lynton Wells defamiliarises his by using imagery so saccharine it resists interpretation — even as kitsch. There are no cues to pop-culture for even the most generous viewer to ground him or herself onto. These aren’t Disney characters or even cartoons, but something more primeval. If anything, the trout in <em>Fish, James</em> recalls an illustration in a high-end children’s book from another era, perhaps Edwardian, but then there is the hallucinogenic background to contend with. Attempting to contextualise the fish draws the viewer’s eye away from the creature and into the tendrils of the plants and churning surfaces within the painting. The work is also so well crafted it demands attention to detail. Wells uses layers of raw pigment he works directly into his medium for an effect as lustrous as a Dutch master. <em>Fish, James</em> is beautiful and hard to look away from, bewitchingly compelling despite the pulses of anti-intellectual energy emanating from the fishing fish. And then it dawns on you that you have been indulging in Wells’ strange loops and stacked surfaces and colors and optical effects both subtle and glaringly obvious that you have been forced to spend seconds swimming in the piece. The net effect is arguably as sublime as anything Mark Rothko or Dan Flavin ever produced.</p>
<p>There is an intellectual component swirling among Wells’ myriad layers as well, one that hints at a new philosophical approach, one straddling the multiple channels nested within sight, but difficult to explain with words. The closest analogue might be Robert Coover’s writing. Coover takes the opposite approach to Peter Halley. Instead of forcing colour through the protocols of geometry and logic, Coover takes myths and narratives and fleshes them out as far as language will allow him to do so. Multiple timelines, entire books devoted to genres, even the CAVE, an experimental chamber that allows storytelling in multiple of dimensions simultaneously. Somehow Coover’s work always seems to accept its limitations and feel at risk of slipping past the protocols of language into nothingness. Wells seems to be plumbing the same raw substance of human thought but coming at it through a far more robust medium than Coover. Instead of surrendering to it, Wells is just beginning to burrow in.</p>
<div align="center">*</div>
<p>Early in his career, Lynton Wells was a successful artist, but at the peak of his fame he abandoned it all to make work the way he wanted to. To return to <em>Conway’s Game of Life</em> Wells is the pattern that used its flippers to pull itself onto the beach and start breathing air. But there is plenty of art that has never been connected to the grid. Beyond the nexus of professional art and artists there is another realm, a larger one encompassing everything from doodles and children’s scrawls and fairground portrait artists to people like the late Thomas Kinkade and the legions of sculptors and painters who ply the tourist trade on the coasts. There is absolute freedom out there, but it comes at a terrible price. By losing the attachment to history and academia, a work of art surrenders any claim of being different from any other product and has no protection from the whims of the marketplace. Art in this realm no longer has a culturally ascribed minimum value.</p>
<p>Oil paintings go for as little at fifty dollars in the convention halls at the airport Hyatt, scruffy Salvation Army rescues go for single digits in flea markets – to compete in this environment with art that takes as much labour, time and emotional pain to produce as anything on the grid is madness, yet one artist, after becoming disgusted with her two dealers and the hypocrisy and greed run amok in the art world decided to slough all of her affiliations before gaining any critical traction whatsoever. Not only is she concealing the prestigious institutions she attended, erasing her exhibition record and has severed her personal connections to the professional art world, she actually adopted a sobriquet, effectively erasing herself from the grid. In December, Amy Marrs will set up a stall in an artisan flea market and sell her work, in three or four sizes, priced the way any other product is – as a small fraction over what it cost her to produce it in materials and time. Her work is geometric and abstract, patterns and optic effects distilled from subculture so as to reveal its connection to the original ethos of modernism – as a grasp toward a new form of spirituality in a mad, violent and unfair world, of new forms that are so clean, crisp, cold and honest next to the hideous indulgence of elite art that she hopes to blow it to pieces.</p>
<p>Perhaps, if there is a lesson to be taken away from all of this, it is that art should not be relegated to a simulation, that art is not a game of life at all, but a component of life that deserves to be exposed to the world beyond its bindings, no matter how fragile it might seem.</p>
<p><em><a href="http://www.waddingtoncustot.com/exhibition/halley2013/">Peter Halley: Paintings 2012-2013</a>, 11 April-3 May, Waddington Custot Galleries, Cork Street, London.</em></p>
<div align="centre"><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/james.gif" alt="james" title="james" width="140" height="164" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-47176" /></div>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://jamesmcgirk.com/">James McGirk</a> has a BA and an MFA from Columbia University. He writes a monthly column for <em><a href="http://www.3quarksdaily.com/">3QuarksDaily</a></em> and his bylines have appeared in <em>TIME</em>, <em>Foreign Policy</em>, <em>More Intelligent Life</em>, and other publications. His short stories has been published by <em>Fence</em> and <em>The Drum</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-game-of-not-life/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Playing infinite chess</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/playing-infinite-chess/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/playing-infinite-chess/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 08:49:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Richard Marshall</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The End Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[End Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joel David Hamkins]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=55602</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/JDH2-420x179.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56615" /></p>

I was fascinated early on by the incompleteness theorems and the independence phenomenon, by the idea that one could prove things about the nature of proof itself. We can prove that our fundamental mathematical theories are simply unable in principle to validate themselves, to prove their own consistency, like the fantastic pronouncements of a strange gentleman whom we are unsure is a con man or a sage. For every such theory, furthermore, there will be true statements that we are unable to prove in them, and so ultimately none of our fundamental theories can have the whole story. The idea that we can prove such things about the nature of truth and provability was incredible to me, and I sought to get to the bottom of it. 

Continuing the <em>End Times</em> series, <strong>Richard Marshall</strong> interviews <strong>Joel David Hamkins</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/JoelDavidHamkins.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56613" /></p>
<p><a href="http:/jdh.hamkins.org/">Joel David Hamkins</a> interviewed by Richard Marshall.</p>
<p>Joel David Hamkins is a maths/logic hipster, melting the logic/maths hive mind with ideas that stalk the same wild territory as Frege, Tarski, Godel, Turing and Cantor. He thinks we all can go there and that we all should. He gives tips about the Moebius strip to six year olds and plays around with his sons homework. He has discovered all sorts of wonders involving supertasks, infinite-time Turing machines, black-hole computations, the mathematics of the uncountable, the lost melody phenomenon of infinitary computability (which really should be the name of a band), set theory and multiverses, infinite utilitarianism, and infinite chess. He&#8217;s also thinking about whether we really have an absolute notion of the finite and doubts if any of this is brain melting, which is just a testimony to his modesty. He also thinks that although maths is open to all he thinks mathematicians could use more metaphors  and silly terminology to get their ideas across better than they do. All in all, this is the grooviest of the hard core maths/logic groovsters. Bodacious!     </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You work in the philosophy of maths and logic. Did you think you’d become a philosopher early on, or was it maths that first took your fancy? Or is your career a surprise?</p>
<p><strong>Joel David Hamkins:</strong> Logicians have always been hard to categorise. Even Frege complained that the philosophers took him as a mathematician and the mathematicians as a philosopher, and Tarski sought in Berkeley to forge a unity between mathematical and philosophical logic. For my part, I would be happy in the company of Frege and Tarski, whatever category that may be. Meanwhile, my original training as a logician was in pure mathematics. As a freshman at Caltech, in the midst of my first genuine logic course and pondering registration for the next semester, a friend came running up to me with the news that there were many further courses in logic. There was evidently an entire field of study called “logic,” and I was in rapture; this was to be my future. I was fascinated early on by the incompleteness theorems and the independence phenomenon, by the idea that one could prove things about the nature of proof itself. We can prove that our fundamental mathematical theories are simply unable in principle to validate themselves, to prove their own consistency, like the fantastic pronouncements of a strange gentleman whom we are unsure is a con man or a sage. For every such theory, furthermore, there will be true statements that we are unable to prove in them, and so ultimately none of our fundamental theories can have the whole story. The idea that we can prove such things about the nature of truth and provability was incredible to me, and I sought to get to the bottom of it. </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Many people find logic and maths very very hard. Philosophy of maths and logic is kind of taking hard to another level! So perhaps you could begin by explaining why you think some people get maths and others don’t. Do you understand people having these feelings? Is it maths that’s the problem, or just the way its been taught or are there just some minds that are better suited to it than others? Have you ever been stumped in a way that is common to most folk?</p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> I’m not sure that I agree with the premise of the question — that many people simply can’t appreciate mathematical ideas — and I believe instead that a fascinating world of mathematical ideas awaits anyone who is open to discovering it. This morning I went into my daughter’s first-grade classroom, full of inquisitive six-year-old girls, and we all made Möbius bands by cutting out paper strips and taping the ends together, after a twist. The children proved that a Möbius band has only one side by colouring it all the way around, whereas with a simple untwisted band they could colour the outside one colour and the inside another colour. We explored what happens with two twists, or more, and what happens when you cut a Möbius band down the centre, all the way around. <a href="http:/jdh.hamkins.org/math-for-six-year-olds">Give it a try!</a> Try cutting a Möbius band one-third in from the edge, all the way around, but make your prediction for the outcome before finishing the cut. Mathematics is full of such playful ideas; there is no reason for someone to feel that they just cannot “get” it. These ideas lead, for those who take ideas seriously, to deeper and more abstract mathematical ideas, which can illuminate a greater mathematical truth, while remaining playful for those with the right attitude. The curious properties of the Möbius band lead to further examples of non-orientability, such as the <a href="http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klein_bottle">Klein</a> bottle, and ultimately one lands in the main ideas of algebraic topology. Many sophisticated mathematical ideas similarly have their origin in an intriguing puzzle; we begin with a curiosity or paradox and in resolving it gain genuine mathematical insight. But to answer the last part of your question, of course every mathematician and philosopher finds themselves stumped with the problems that vex them. We persevere, and often enough overcome the initial confusions and find ourselves a way through the tangle. What a great feeling it is when one solves a long-troubling question. It is surely one of life’s great enjoyments. I’d prefer that we get away from the idea that a person may not be a “math person” or may just not “get” math. Such a person is unlikely to assert in the same sweeping manner that they just don’t get literature or humour or art, or that they are not an “idea person”. Meanwhile, I guarantee that there are some fascinating mathematical ideas, at just exactly the right level, waiting for them to ponder. Anyone, even a child, can learn to count into Cantor’s <a href="http:/freevideolectures.com/Course/3153/Real-Analysis/26">transfinite ordinals</a>, and there are fun elementary problems in graph colouring or game theory. Some beautiful classical arguments, such as the proof that the square root of 2 is irrational or the proof that there are infinitely many prime numbers, stand as pinnacles of human achievement, known for two thousand years, yet are accessible enough for any intelligent person to grasp.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MakeyourownMobiusband.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="784" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56612" /></p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> There are some really cool philosophical problems that you’ve been engaged with that I think anyone will appreciate. So can you say something about supertasks and the infinite time Turing machines? In a paper you ask what would we and what could we do with an infinitely fast computer. This sounds like science fiction but its what people are working on. So firstly, what’s a supertask and what could such a computer do? And are we going to be building one anytime soon?</p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> A supertask is a process involving infinitely many steps, and it is interesting to imagine performing the steps faster and faster in such a way that all are completed in finite total time. That may seem perplexing, but Zeno long ago pointed out that in walking from here to there, we accomplish the supertask of first traversing half the distance, and then half the remaining distance, and then again half the remaining distance and so on ad infinitum. After only finitely many such traversals, we are not quite there, are we, and the full supertask is completed at the instant of our arrival. Similarly, if one performs the first of infinitely many steps in a process in half a minute, and the next in a quarter minute and then an eighth and so on, then the whole infinite process will be completed in one minute, in an instance of the geometric series (1/2)+(1/4)+(1/8)+ … = 1. In the Zeno example, this corresponds simply to walking from here to there at constant speed. Suppose now that we successively add two marbles to a giant bag and then take one out, repeating this action over and over, faster and faster, infinitely many times. What is in the bag when we have completed all these actions? On the one hand, since we seem to be steadily increasing the number of marbles in the bag, it would seem natural to expect that the bag has infinitely many marbles at the end. But suppose that the marbles are numbered 1, 2, 3 and so on, and that at each step we always remove the smallest-numbered marble currently in the bag, never using that marble again. With this procedure, the bag will actually be empty at the end. If there were any marbles in it at the end, then among those marbles, there would have to be one with the smallest number. This marble, if you think about it, would have to have been the smallest-numbered marble at an earlier stage in the process, when all the even-smaller-numbered marbles had been dealt with, and therefore it would have been removed at that earlier stage. But this would have prevented it from being in the bag at the end, and so indeed the bag must be empty then. I find this kind of supertask to show that certain intuitions that we have about the nature of finitary processes are no longer valid for infinitary processes, and so we must be very careful when reasoning about supertask procedures.</p>
<p><a href="http:/people.math.uni-bonn.de/koepke/Preprints/Ordinal_computations.pdf">Jeff Kidder</a> and <a href="http:/books.google.co.uk/books?id=nkBa0sMVzYEC&amp;pg=PA225&amp;lpg=PA225&amp;dq=jeff+kidder+turing&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=lE3HokSRwh&amp;sig=35ram_Q2O1tZE0adIlWl5Z2PgUY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=4qogUb_vDYiDhQf-zIDoCg&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=jeff%20kidder%20turing&amp;f=false">Andy Lewis</a> and I developed the theory of <a href="http:/jdh.hamkins.org/ittms/">infinite-time Turing machines</a> to provide a theoretical tool for analysing the nature of infinitary computation. What does it mean exactly to carry out a computational procedure with infinitely many steps? The infinite time Turing machine model provides an answer, a theoretical answer, which helps us to understand the resulting class of infinite-time computable functions and infinite-time decidable sets, in the same way that the standard Turing machine model underlies our conception of what it means to be computable in finite time. We don’t actually build these machines, of course, in either the finitary or infinitary realm. Rather, the machines are used in what amounts to thought experiments, guiding our understanding of the resulting concepts of computability and decidability. It turns out that the infinite time Turing machines describe a rich level of complexity that was not yet captured by the other notions of complexity in descriptive set theory, and it is in this context that one should think of the subject. Nevertheless, there are several groups of researchers working on the fantastical idea that it might be consistent with the laws of physics to have a physical realisation of a supertask computational device. This line of thinking can be seen as an attack on the widely-held Church-Turing thesis, which asserts that the Turing machine model of computability correctly captures what it means for a function to be computable in principle or for a set to be decidable in principle by effective means. Turing had argued and indeed even derived his Turing machine model by thinking carefully about what it was that a human did when carrying out a rote computational procedure with paper and pencil, thereby arriving at his original formulation of the thesis. The new objections, however, are aimed at refuting a stronger thesis, for which the notion of computability allows the human computer not only to compute with paper and pencil, but also to take advantage of whatever strange and wonderful computational powers might be possible in a physical universe, using whatever bizarre quantum-mechanical or relativistic effect might be useful for computation. For example, some of the infinitary computational procedures work by exploiting relativistic time contraction (as in the <a href="http:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sa81lP9MR0I">twin paradox</a>), so as to carry out an infinite procedure in finite time for one observer. Similarly, in <a href="http:/www.newscientist.com/article/dn8836-black-holes-the-ultimate-quantum-computers.html">black-hole computation</a>, a computational device achieves super-Turing capability by falling into a black hole, finding inside another physical universe, while observing whether a certain signal follows or not sent from a component of the device that remains outside the black-hole.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You presented some of your thoughts about this at a conference about effective mathematics of the uncountable</a>. In your paper you liken the uncountability to being able to recognise a tune but not being able to hum it. Is that a picture of what maths of the uncountable is about? Can you say something about this kind of maths that sounds really cool?</p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> The <a href="http:/arxiv.org/pdf/math/0602483.pdf">lost-melody</a> phenomenon for infinitary computability expresses one of the unusual features of it that Andy Lewis and I discovered, hinging on the distinction between the ability to produce a particular complex object and the ability to recognise the object when it is presented to you. What we realised is that there can be a mathematical object <em>m</em>, a certain infinite string of binary digits, such that the infinitary computers cannot produce <em>m</em> on their own, but they are capable of recognising in a computable manner whether a given object is <em>m</em> or not. The idea is that <em>m</em> is extremely complicated, too complicated to produce by any computable procedure, but at the same time it exhibits certain pertinent internal consistencies, which are sufficient to characterise <em>m</em> uniquely, thereby allowing an infinitary computer to verify whether it is dealing with the real <em>m</em> or not. So the object <em>m</em> is computably recognisable, but not computable. It is a lost melody — perhaps from some classical symphony — a tune that you are not able to sing on your own, but nevertheless you can recognise correctly yes-or-no when someone else sings it. This lost-melody phenomenon has now been established for many of the various models of infinitary computability, and one of the necessary features when it occurs is that the computational devices, unlike classical Turing machines, should not be able to undertake a computable exhaustive search of their entire input space.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Another big idea that you’re thinking about at the moment is the dispute in set theory between a universe and multiverse. Can you say what this dispute is about? I guess one of the things that interests me is the idea that the multiverse approach challenges the notion that every set-theoretic assertion has a final definitive truth value. Does this then touch on issues outside of maths, such as vagueness? And does the idea intersect with ideas in physics about the nature of reality?</p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> Set theory can be and often is taken as an ontological foundation for the rest of mathematics in the sense that abstract mathematical objects can be construed fundamentally as sets, and being precise in mathematics often amounts to specifying one’s context in set-theoretic terms. We identify a function, for example, with its graph, a set of ordered pairs, and essentially all mathematical objects can be construed as sets in a similar way. The existence of a common foundation like this for the whole of mathematics has been extremely important for the unity of the subject, for mathematicians often borrow a result from one area for use in another, applying a result of complex analysis, for example, in algebra; this would become incoherent if each sub-area had its own separate foundation. A dominant perspective within set theory itself, what I have called the universe view, holds that there is an absolute background concept of set, giving rise to the unique cumulative universe of all sets, in which every set-theoretic assertion — and hence also every mathematical assertion — has a definite truth value. On this view, statements such as the continuum hypothesis and others have definite final answers, and the goal of set theory is to find these fundamental truths. The widespread independence phenomenon, where such statements turn out to be neither provable nor refutable in our best and strongest theories, is seen on this view as a distraction, telling us about the weaknesses of our theories rather than about what it really true.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, there is tension between the universe view and what is surely the principal set-theoretic discovery of the twentieth century, namely, the unexpected but pervasive phenomenon of diverse set-theoretic possibility. It turns out that almost every nontrivial statement of infinite combinatorics, for example, including the continuum hypothesis and hundreds of other similar assertions, is independent of the axioms of set theory, even when they are strengthened by any of the various large cardinal axioms. What set theory is about is exploring the full range of this set-theoretic possibility. The most powerful tools in set theory, such as forcing, ultrapowers and inner models, are most naturally understood as methods for building alternative set-theoretic universes, realising different mathematical truths. We have discovered an entire cosmos of alternative mathematical universes, related to each other as forcing extensions or through large cardinal embeddings in complex commutative diagrams, like the lines of a constellation in a dark night sky. The competing multiverse position takes these alternative universes to be fully as real as the cumulative universe on the universe view, and the debate on pluralism sets these two perspectives against each other. We may fruitfully consider the analogy with geometry, which for centuries was taken to be about the absolute concepts of point, line and space. The discovery of non-Euclidean geometry in the late nineteenth century was shocking, and the formerly crystalline concepts of geometry splintered into a multitude of non-Euclidean geometries, including spherical geometries, hyperbolic geometries and so on, with different geometrical truths and properties. Nevertheless, geometers today regard these alternative geometrical worlds to be fully as real and geometrically legitimate as classical Euclidean space, and one may find <a href="http:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=MKwAS5omW_w">mathematical</a> videos <a href="http:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=MN7_FZH3neU">showing</a> what it is like to wander around in certain hyperbolic spaces. Similarly, the multiverse position in set theory takes those alternative set-theoretical universes as fully real and set-theoretically legitimate. </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/JDH2.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="288" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56615" /></p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> I noticed you’ve done some work on the theory of infinite utilitarianism. Can you give us some idea about that? </p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> A simple extension of the theory of utilitarianism from finite worlds to the infinite might direct one to compare two worlds simply by computing the total sum of utility in each world, even if this should be infinite; but such an approach leads to some counterintuitive conclusions. For example, compare a first world with infinitely many people, each having happiness level 1, with a second world, in which we’ve improved each of their lives, so they now have happiness 2 each. The overall sum is the same infinity, but it seems that we might want strictly to prefer the second world over the first. The theory of infinite utilitarianism is about the various principles that we might appeal to in order to do so, and various researchers have proposed and defended a number of very specific principles. In joint work, <a href="http:/www.youtube.com/watch?v=7XDwT9tDGpk">Barbara Gail Montero</a> and I have argued that a number of these proposals founder on a similar extension to the infinite of a cardinality principle that holds for finite sets but fails for infinite sets. For example, consider a strong version of the <a href="http:/video.about.com/management/Pareto-s-Principle.htm">Pareto</a> principle, asserting that if we are comparing two worlds with the same people, and everyone in the first world is at least as well off in the second, with at least one person becoming strictly better off, then the second world is strictly better than the first overall. This sounds good at first, but some examples may loosen that intuition. Suppose we have a soccer team with infinitely many players, some very good and some terrible, with their spectrum of abilities given by the integers: ⋯ -2 -1 0 1 2 ⋯ . Now suppose that they go through spring training, and each player improves by one unit. Has the team strictly improved? According to the strong Pareto principle, yes, but if one considers the overall spectrum of ability, it appears to be exactly the same as it was before, ⋯ -2 -1 0 1 2 ⋯, with the only difference being that each player has moved one place to the right, a difference that doesn’t seem to matter in term of the team’s ability. Montero and I argue that the intuition we have for the strong version of the Pareto principle is essentially similar to and ultimately as flawed as the naïve intuition that adding an element to a set always produces a set strictly larger in cardinality. This principle is true for finite sets, but false for infinite sets. A slightly weaker Pareto principle, which we believe is the correct principle, asserts that if every individual in one world is made at least as well off in another (with the same individuals), then the second world is at least as good overall as the first. The topic has numerous papers on these and similar questions, with some of the proposed collections of principles turning out to be subtly inconsistent, as well as dozens of fascinating thought experiments, which test our intuitions about the comparative value of worlds.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> And a very groovy paper you’ve just produced is about <a href="http:/www.sms.cam.ac.uk/media/1231297">infinite chess</a>. What is infinite chess? Have you proved that there can or can’t be check mate in such a game? </p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> Last year when I was visiting at NYU, I put up on my office door in the philosophy department a poster of one of my infinite chess positions, a little puzzle, on which there gradually appeared scribbled comments and post-it notes from the graduate students and post-docs who proposed solutions. Infinite chess is chess played on an infinite chess board, a boundless plane tiled with alternating black and  white squares on which the familiar chess pieces— kings, queens, rooks, bishops, knights and pawns — move about according to their usual movement rules, striving to place the opposing king in checkmate. Checkmate, when it occurs, does so after only finitely many moves, and infinitely long play counts as a draw. There is no standard starting position, but rather one considers the game beginning from a specified initial position, not necessarily finite. Although unfortunately we cannot sit down in a café for a game of infinite chess, it remains a game of the mind, and there are interesting game-theoretic questions about it remaining open. For example, it is not known whether there can be, even in principle, a computable procedure giving optimal play from any finite position of infinite chess. In ordinary finite 8 x 8 chess, in contrast, like any finite game, there is in principle a computable procedure for optimal play, simply because the entire game tree — the tree of all possible legal moves — although vast, is finite, and one may compute optimal play by recursion backwards from the finitely many positions where the game has been already won or drawn. So as our computers gain power, it is inevitable that they will be able to implement this procedure and when they do, computers will achieve absolutely perfect play in chess. Already computers can beat any human player essentially by searching huge parts of this game tree, which amounts to an approximation of this ideal algorithm.</p>
<p>In infinite chess, however, this game tree argument breaks down, because the tree is infinite and cannot be searched in finite time. And not only is the game tree infinite, but it is also can be infinitely branching, because queens, bishops and rooks may have the choice of infinitely many legal moves from a given position. Thus, we cannot hope even to search the game tree to finite depth. This observation had strongly suggested that the mate-in-n problem for finite positions in infinite chess the problem of determining whether a designated player can force checkmate from a given position in at most n moves — might not be computably decidable. Meanwhile, Brumleve, Schlicht and I proved that the mate-in-n problem of infinite chess actually is decidable. Our algorithm does not search the game tree, which as we’ve said is impossible, but rather it interprets the mate-in-n problem as an assertion in what we call the structure of chess, whose theory we proved is a regular language in the sense of finite automata theory and therefore decidable. The fact that checkmates, when they occur, do so after only finitely many moves makes infinite chess technically what is known as an open game and therefore subject to the theory of transfinite ordinal game values, a powerful theory that applies to any open game. In this theory, the transfinite ordinal value of a position is a kind of abstract measure of the distance of a position from a win for a designated player. A position has finite value <em>n</em>, for example, when the player can force checkmate in at most <em>n</em> moves. The position has value <em>ω</em>, for example, when any move by black leads to a mate-in-n position winning for white, but black may choose <em>n</em> as large as desired. Such transfinite values and higher occur in infinite chess, but it is totally open how large they may become. The omega one of chess is the supremum of the game values that arise.  In our recent paper, Evans and Woodin and I prove that the following infinite position has value omega squared times four, with black to move, and we have other positions with value omega cubed and higher. We conjecture that the game values will go considerably higher. We had an idea for establishing this, but unfortunately, it didn’t quite fit into the two dimensions of ordinary infinite chess. But the idea does work, if you can believe it, in infinite 3D chess! The history of 3D chess, you may be surprised to learn, spans several centuries, going back at least to Kieseritzky’s Kubikschack in 1851, including Maack’s raumschach chess clubs in Hamburg from 1919, and running well into the twenty-third century, in light of the games played by Spock and Kirk on several Star Trek episodes. We may be the first, however, to have established nontrivial facts about the infinite version of 3D chess. What we proved is that every countable ordinal arises as a game value of an infinite position in infinite 3D chess, and thus the omega one of infinite 3D chess is true omega one, as large as it could possibly be.  </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> So can you introduce the lay folk to some of the really interesting ideas that you’re brooding about in the philosophy of maths? What are the cutting edge thoughts around and why are they significant? And are there some way out, weird calculations that would melt our brains?</p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> One idea I am brooding on — I’m not sure it will melt anyone’s brain — is the question of whether we really do have an absolute notion of the finite, as many seem to say we do, for example, when describing the natural numbers as the set containing, 0, 1, 2, and so on. My question is whether that “and so on” is really as meaningful as some people take it to be. Mathematicians, of course, give some substance to the idea by proving that the natural numbers are categorical, in that there is one and only one structure satisfying the second-order <a href="http:/www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/447921/Peano-axioms">Peano axioms</a>, and this is the structure of the natural numbers. My objection to this explanation is that this second-order proof in effect establishes the uniqueness of the concept of finiteness by relying on the presumed absoluteness of our concept of set of natural numbers, which is surely a murkier realm in comparison. So how can people think this approach succeeds? Ultimately, I find myself increasingly led to the idea that there may be an undiscovered plurality of finiteness concepts, going along with the plurality of set concepts, that different mathematical universes may have incomparable concepts of the finite, each of them improved by a stronger concept of the finite. Indeed, I speculate that this kind of plurality is ultimately what underlies the pervasive logical independence we find in our theories as well as the pervasive phenomenon of computable undecidability. I await technological developments in set theory that will provide an arithmetic analogue to forcing, allowing us to modify the arithmetic of a model of set theory in a controlled way that does not seem to give preference to the legitimacy of one model over the other, just as forcing does in the higher-order realm. </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> One thing that strikes me is that maths is dead important but the higher end of maths is largely inaccessible to ordinary folk like myself. However, it is this higher stuff where a lot of maths becomes both significant and really weird and exciting. I noticed that your intro to your paper ‘<a href="http:/jdh.hamkins.org/set-theoreticgeology/">Set-Theoretic Geology</a>’ had a very neat picture that helped guide a reader someway into what you were analysing, so do you think perhaps pictures are underused in making higher maths comprehensible to the folk? So is there any way that I could become maths literate without being able to do the calculations? Could there be a use for maths teaching for the non-specialist so the sorts of issues you are examining become more widely known about, in the way that science literacy might be promulgated? </p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> Mathematics is a very tall subject, in that new knowledge often builds on earlier knowledge, and it can be difficult to understand or appreciate the new knowledge without mastering the old. Euclid famously told Ptolemy that “there is no royal road in geometry,” no shortcut for kings. Nevertheless, I also believe that mathematicians can often do a much better job of explaining their ideas, in particular, by making more room for metaphor and soft explanations, which help to explain the idea behind an argument. Such explanations are useful not only for beginners, but also help experts to organise their thoughts about a topic in a more enlightening and higher-level manner, allowing them to apply those ideas elsewhere. How frustrating it is to read an incomprehensible mathematical argument, which contains numerous details while omitting the most important part, a high-level description of the argument. I try in my own writing to explain my ideas on many levels, using pictures, metaphors or whatever I think might be helpful. I’ve realised in retrospect, however, that this has often caused me to introduce odd or even silly terminology, such as the lost-melody theorem, the hypnagogic digraph, and buttons and switches in the modal logic of forcing, to name a few. I am trying in each case to convey a particular idea as best I can, but does the silly terminology make me absurd? Probably, but if it helps people understand the idea, then so be it.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> I’ve noticed that you are the top-rated user on MathOverflow, the new online forum for mathematics questions and answers. What can you tell us about that? </p>
<p><strong>JDH:</strong> <a href="http:/mathoverflow.net/">MathOverflow</a> is a new online forum for asking and answering research-level questions in mathematics, with dozens of new posts every day on diverse topics, including many on logic and foundations, including the philosophy of mathematics. The forum provides a vastly more focused manner for mathematicians to interact than was previously possible, connecting researchers who are interested in or knowledgeable about a particular topic, drawing from a large pool of users ranging from graduate students and post-docs up to senior faculty, including a surprising number of extremely prominent mathematicians. Faced with a puzzling mathematical issue, you can tap into this collective expertise simply by posting a question. In very short order, you will find that someone, somewhere in the world, who has thought deeply about that very issue, will post an expert reply. Indeed, you may receive several answers giving perspectives on your topic that hadn’t occurred to you. Young researchers can experiment with the ideas they are learning, by posting questions right at the boundary of what they understand. I have used MathOverflow not only in this ordinary way to learn a topic I was curious about, but also to confirm, for questions arising in my own work that I suspected were difficult, that they did not admit of an elementary solution I had missed. People now say that a problem is “MathOverflow-hard” — a pun on the terminology such as NP-hard from complexity theory — to mean that a problem was asked on MathOverflow, but not answered there, a rare occurrence indicating that a question is difficult. Part of the success of MathOverflow, in addition to efforts to maintain a high-level of discourse, is attributed simply to its manner of social design, using principles or even tricks of social engineering to motivate people to participate, and the software model, built by <a href="http://stackexchange.com/">Stackexchange</a>, seems to have hit upon some successful ideas. The result, though, is a slightly game-like nature for the forum, since contributors earn “reputation” points when other users vote up their contributions. This may sound silly, and some may find it off-putting, even if it does stimulate the competitive instincts of others, but the voting and particularly the sorting of answers by votes does seem effectively to communicate the community’s perspective on a post, because quality answers generally rise to the top, while junk answers inevitably sink to the bottom. So people are motivated to provide explanations that other users find valuable. Personally, I am engaged on MathOverflow because I find the mathematics there to be compelling. I was surprised to find such a strong interest in mathematical foundations among non-logicians there, with numerous questions about set theory and the philosophy of set theory coming from other parts of mathematics, and of course I was pleased to find that my explanations were appreciated. So, yes, I am the top-rated user there, and I can joke with my colleagues that at least in this sense I can claim to be the most “reputable” mathematician in the world. In any case, I’ve learned an enormous amount of mathematics there.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, there is also the companion site, <a href="http:/math.stackexchange.com">Math.Stackexchange</a>, which is open to lower level material. You can check out a question I asked there about the large numbers in what I call the <a href="http:/math.stackexchange.com/questions/72646/help-me-put-these-enormous-numbers-in-order">googol-plex-bang-stack hierarchy</a> and another concerning a <a href="http:/math.stackexchange.com/questions/65967/can-you-answer-my-sons-fourth-grade-homework-question">homework assignment</a> my fourth-grade son brought home from school. There are also an astounding number of fantastic mathematics blogs, at every level of expertise, many of them written by enthusiastic youngsters who take pains to explain an idea very well; search <a href="http://mathblogging.org">MathBlogging</a> to find one to your taste. And please climb into <a href="http:/cantorsattic.info">Cantor’s Attic</a>, a site I founded with Victoria Gitman, a Wikipedia-style compendium of information on all notions of infinity, large and small.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/richardmarshallnewnew.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-55265" /></p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE INTERVIEWER</strong><br />
<a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?s=%22richard+marshall%22"><strong>Richard Marshall</strong></a> is still biding his time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/playing-infinite-chess/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Two Million &amp; Three</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/two-million-three/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/two-million-three/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 10:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Andrew Stevens</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56577</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/iraq2-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="iraq2" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56586" /></p>

Dereen describes how the city used to be surrounded by palm trees, whose shade and shelter held back the creeping desert. Basra sits squarely within the band of desert encircling North Africa and the Middle East, the Syrian desert to the west and the Sahara beyond that. It is one of the hottest cities in the world. But within the desert there is an oasis: the world’s largest Palm grove, including orchard after orchard of hardy date Palms. Lodged in the basin of the Shatt al-Arab river, which carries the waters of the Euphrates and the Tigris into the Persian Gulf, this was Iraq’s most fertile agricultural region. But war and neoliberal policies forced many farmers off the land. Basra’s orchards, with their dense tree cover and crucial position on the Iraq-Iran border, have been a battle ground three times in the last thirty years. If famers weren’t deterred by violence and unexploded mines, they had to contend with the destruction of the city’s water and electricity infrastructure during the bombing of March 2003. Then the new government cut subsidies and dropped protectionist measures. The result is acres of farm land uprooted, dredged and sold off for urban sprawl.

By <strong>Alistair Cartwright</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/iraq1.jpg" alt="" title="iraq1" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56583" /></p>
<p>By Alistair Cartwright.</p>
<p>The Ten Years On conference that took place on February 9th was a milestone. It was the biggest anti-war conference this country has seen in five years. Anyone who knows Friends House will know that it&#8217;s a hard place to fill. The main space &#8211; with its tiers of old wooden pews fanning out in blocks of a hundred, like felled trees in a shallow crater, and its three galleries, which deceptively hold half as many people again &#8211; is more like an amphitheatre than a hall. It&#8217;s big without being grand or cavernous. But it has none of the power to channel and concentrate that your average town hall or lecture theatre does. It&#8217;s classic Quaker in this sense, designed for listening not to a preacher but to the person sitting next to you. But that Saturday Friends House was packed. By the time of the closing speeches the only seat I could get was by a side door, perched on the edge of a step. Not ideal, because you couldn&#8217;t see a thing of the top table. You could hear fine though, which is what mattered, most of the time. And even when you couldn&#8217;t there was enough goodwill to compensate for the direst acoustics. </p>
<p>		In the opening session one mic wasn&#8217;t quite enough to pick up Tony Benn. At 87 years old his words are still powerful but his voice has gotten fainter. So the five speakers pushed their five mics together &#8212; a gesture of solidarity I imagine him smiling at. And Noam Chomsky had to call in his technical assistant &#8212; his niece &#8212; to coax a glitching Skype connection back to life.  </p>
<p>So I sat there with several others, ears trained on the stage and eyes pointing the wrong way. </p>
<p>		Have you ever looked at something without seeing it? That&#8217;s exactly what I did for about six hours (in.c breaks, running between workshops, queuing for coffee, helping with ushering, talking in corridors). What I didn&#8217;t see was the thing we were inside of. </p>
<p>		At about 5pm, when energy levels not assisted by caffeine or rabble rousing begin their natural tail-off, I saw this thing for the first time. US campaigner Phyllis Bennis was describing how the demonstrations of February 2003 followed the arc of the sun, starting in the Middle East, rippling through South East Asia, welling up in South Korea and Australia, sailing the Pacific to the US West coast, jumping from one city to another, before crossing the Atlantic to the UK, sweeping up through Scandinavia, and down through mainland Europe and North Africa. The same slogan in 150 languages. What became known as &#8216;the uncommitted six&#8217; was a phenomenon left in the wake of this wave of protest: six dependents of US foreign policy, who this time bucked the trend and voted against &#8212; Mexico, Chile, Guinea, Cameroon, Angola and Pakistan. It meant the defeat of the second UN resolution that the US and the UK sought as a legal go-ahead for the war. </p>
<p>		Somewhere in the middle of all this, between the far sides of the Pacific and the Atlantic, I started looking at the faces in the audience.    </p>
<p>		Scanning the crowd I saw faces black and white; heads grey, red, mohawked and crew-cut; and among them what must have been the youngest delegates of the day: a boy about 13 years old squeezing sideways down a row of seats, right in the middle of the hall. </p>
<p>		When he reached his seat I saw he was with two others, a girl and a boy the same age. Out in the corridor I managed to catch the whole family. The parents peeled away and let the kids do the talking. They were a sister and a brother, Sheween and Dereen, and their cousin Daroon. </p>
<p>		Only Daroon was on the February 15th demonstration, which is not surprising when I learn that his father is Iraqi dissident and antiwar campaigner, Sami Ramadani. At the time Daroon was four years old. He remembers only a few things: a home made placard, a whistle bought from a demo-hawker, and above all the noise. The noise drowns out the other details. It&#8217;s clearly a strong memory for him but nearly impossible to describe. An event, an object, a person or a place would be easy, but how do you describe an <em>intensity</em>? </p>
<p>						* * *</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/basra.jpg" alt="" title="basra" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56585" /></p>
<p>The three young people I spoke to represent a generation that has grown up with war. The war on terror has brought death and destruction to Afghanistan and Iraq. Under the cover of humanitarian intervention it has been extended to Libya and Syria. Now in Mali and Somalia the old term is openly reprised. But this war has also stoked racism and hollowed out democracy at home. Born and raised in Britain, with family in Iraq, Sheween, Dereen and Daroon have in some ways seen the worst of both worlds. </p>
<p>		They came out of the conference a mixture of intense interest, some sadness, plenty of excitement, and hope. Daroon was all smiles and the words came tumbling out of him. Articulating ideas, shaping and colouring them with speech, and reciting, speedily and somewhat breathlessly, the flow of events, seem to spurr him on. As if talking kept his smile going. His cousins are more quiet but far from listless and not exactly shy. When I ask if they plan to be on the next protest, Sheween is the first to interject: a declamatory &#8216;yes!&#8217;. Her brightness comes in bursts, clarifying and reaffirming, or jolting the conversation onto the next stage. </p>
<p>		Dereen, who I spotted in the audience, is in many ways more unassuming. What sticks in the mind are his selections: of examples, instances, events, objects and tales. He speaks slower than his cousin and less definitively than his sister, but everything he alights on is in some way bigger than its immediate contents. Every selection opens up a vista. </p>
<p>		Like when I ask him for his highlght of the day and he tells me about a leaflet outlining the case of Omar Khadr, a Canadian and the youngest person to have been held at Guantanamo Bay. Khadr was 15 when he was arrested in Afghanistan, allegedly following a firefight that killed a US soldier. He should have been treated as a child soldier, in other words released and rehabilitated. Instead he was tortured and held without charge for three years. Last autumn he finally returned to Canada where he remains in prison awaiting parole. He is 26 years old, the same age as me. </p>
<p>		Khadr&#8217;s story reminded Dereen of the dangers of him and his sister&#8217;s visit to Iraq in 2007. Sectarian violence was then at its height. The role of the US divide-and-rule strategy in engineering this situation is well known. In 2004 Sunni and Shia militias fought alongside each other in the resistance. They drove back US troops in Fallujah and had the British vitrually confined to Barracks in Basra. Sectarian co-option was the strategy devised to try and turn this situation around. It half succeeded, although success is not the word: the resistance was immobilised by drowning it and half the country in blood. In the process Bush and Blair lost their cherished dream of Iraq as a stable base of operations in the Middle East. Elections and the creation of a new government were a farce; the oil law that would give the multinationals a constitutional guarantee fell through time after time; finally Maliki kicked out his own patrons, with a polite &#8216;no&#8217; to Obama&#8217;s request to extend Bush&#8217;s Status of Forces agreement. Of course the neoliberals didn&#8217;t do so badly. Halliburton cleaned up in a botch-job reconstruction. BP and ExxonMobil are also in there, pumping millions of dollars out of the country, but they sit less comfortably than they would have liked alongside French, Russian and Chinese competitors. The set up is far from stable. It is basically cowboy territory; hegemony fast and loose. </p>
<p>		Sheween and Dereen&#8217;s family are from Kurdistan. The two of them are well aware of the tensions and frailities existing between that region &#8212; where amid the chaos, the Barzani government has pushed for autonomy and cut advance deals with the oil companies &#8212; and the rest of the country. They wish next time they will be able to vist Baghdad, and that Iraq will be a unified Iraq. </p>
<p>		At the same time they talk about the beauty of the country. About Sulaymaniyah, known as the cultural capital of Kurdistan, and how they were amazed to find it surrounded by mountains on all sides, like a bowl &#8212; a three dimensional experience I imagine no picture postcard can replicate. </p>
<p>		Dereen mentions Basra which they also visited. He remembers a soldier coming to speak to their class in school. The soldier described Basra as a desert. But Dereen knew the city was once regarded as the Venice of the Middle East: when Sheikh Zayed built Abu Dhabi, Basra was his model. </p>
<p>		Dereen describes how the city used to be surrounded by palm trees, whose shade and shelter held back the creeping desert. Basra sits squarely within the band of desert encircling North Africa and the Middle East, the Syrian desert to the west and the Sahara beyond that. It is one of the hottest cities in the world. But within the desert there is an oasis: the world&#8217;s largest Palm grove, including orchard after orchard of hardy date Palms. Lodged in the basin of the Shatt al-Arab river, which carries the waters of the Euphrates and the Tigris into the Persian Gulf, this was Iraq&#8217;s most fertile agricultural region. But war and neoliberal policies forced many farmers off the land. Basra&#8217;s orchards, with their dense tree cover and crucial position on the Iraq-Iran border, have been a battle ground three times in the last thirty years. If famers weren&#8217;t deterred by violence and unexploded mines, they had to contend with the destruction of the city&#8217;s water and electricity infrastructure during the bombing of March 2003. Then the new government cut subsidies and dropped protectionist measures. The result is acres of farm land uprooted, dredged and sold off for urban sprawl.   </p>
<p>						* * *</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/iraq2.jpg" alt="" title="iraq2" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56586" /></p>
<p>From earlier in the day I remember two phrases, a statement and a question. Something said by John Rees, an officer of Stop the War Coalition, and something asked by Tariq Ali. The statement, that if this movement didn&#8217;t exist we would have to invent it. The question, what happened to the two million people who marched in 2003? </p>
<p>		Being rhetorical, it was natural that the questioner should answer his own question: the fact is that many who demonstrated in 2003 wholeheartedly and without a shadow a doubt expected the demonstration to succeed &#8212; then and there, in its immediate goal, before the war had even started. If it had done it would have been unprecedented. Movements of opposition have constrained, hampered and derailed existing wars. None so far has prevented a war from happening in the first place. It was necessary then for everyone on the 2003 demonstration to learn a lesson about political struggle. We had to learn that every gain worth holding onto, whether the right of women to vote or the end of Apartheid, is hard won; that major social transformation, even when it happens suddenly, all at once and on a seismic scale, doesn&#8217;t come overnight; that every movement has a prehistory, and if it doesn&#8217;t, if it explodes onto the scene as something new and at least partly unforseen, then it needs to create and live through this prehistory. </p>
<p>		Being rhetorical, it was also a question asked in the plural. &#8216;What happened to all those people?&#8217; was a question for this room full of people to take up and ask itself. </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s what happened to three of them.         </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/alistaircartwright.jpg" alt="" title="alistaircartwright" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56582" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR<br />
Alistair Cartwright</strong> has writing published and forthcoming in the poetry magazines <em>The Delinquent</em> and <em>Department</em>, in the London Consortium journal <em>Static</em>, and in the &#8216;nocturnal&#8217; <em>Nyx</em>. He writes reviews and features for Counterfire.org and is an editor of DifferentSkies.net, a new online publication for experimental prose and creative non-fiction.    </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/two-million-three/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Argument against Brevity &amp; other poems</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/argument-against-brevity-other-poems/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/argument-against-brevity-other-poems/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 19:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>steven fowler</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Poetry]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=54470</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/562689_847059628952_1757069263_n-420x179.jpeg" alt="" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-54472" />

If the condition of our relations
is less gratifying, know the temporary 
reserves abound. This unusual
agitation. We have attempted no
propagandism, acknowledged no
revolution. Our struggle has been,
of course, ours. Nevertheless,
complaint, even if it were just,
would certainly be unwise.
The proposition has been made,
especially to XXXXX XXXXXXX.
It has been kindly received, yet
they fail to penetrate
and soften even the heart.

By <strong>Dustin Luke Nelson</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Dustin Luke Nelson.</p>
<p><strong>Draft Toward a Syllogism for a Roommate Who Won’t Let Me Get a Cat</strong><br />
		<em>for LM</em></p>
<p>The facts with which I shall deal this evening are mainly old and familiar. If there shall be any novelty, it will be in the mode of presenting facts. There is a question. What is the question which those fathers understood just as well, and even better than we do now? It is this. What is your proof? You say you are inexcusable while we are destructive, or something of the sort. Is this not adherence to the old and tired, against the new and untried? I full indorse this, and I adopt it as a text for this discourse. </p>
<p><strong>Thoughts on A</strong><br />
		<em>for MO</em></p>
<p>If the condition of our relations<br />
is less gratifying, know the temporary<br />
reserves abound. This unusual<br />
agitation. We have attempted no<br />
propagandism, acknowledged no<br />
revolution. Our struggle has been,<br />
of course, ours. Nevertheless,<br />
complaint, even if it were just,<br />
would certainly be unwise.<br />
The proposition has been made,<br />
especially to XXXXX XXXXXXX.<br />
It has been kindly received, yet<br />
they fail to penetrate<br />
and soften even the heart.</p>
<p><strong>Argument Against Brevity</strong><br />
		<em>for KR</em></p>
<p>How then shall we perform it?<br />
Accounts of outrages committed<br />
by mobs. Are there no divisions?<br />
Mr. Speaker, it is said, did steal, take, and carry away ten boars,<br />
ten sows, ten shoats, and ten pigs. Therefore, I recommend a day<br />
of public humiliation. A day.</p>
<p>But you are, perhaps, ready to ask,<br />
“What has this to do with<br />
the perpetuation of our Throne of Grace?”<br />
Well, by golly, that is the most equally divided gang of hogs I ever<br />
did hear of.</p>
<p>And furthermore, I answer, it has much to do with it. </p>
<p><strong>No Regrets For Our Beards</strong><br />
		<em>for JW</em></p>
<p>A blockade could not be established,<br />
and vigorously enforced, without committing<br />
occasional mistakes, and inflicting<br />
unintentional injuries. I deem it duty<br />
to recommend, to view, to see, some from<br />
interested motives, others upon patriotic<br />
considerations, and still others influenced<br />
by philanthropic sentiments. There are<br />
there. Others have been added. Others of so extraordinary<br />
a nature, dealing with us in anger<br />
for our sins. I feel, more, how weak<br />
and fruitless must be any word of mine.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/562689_847059628952_1757069263_n-225x300.jpeg" alt="" width="225" height="300" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-54472" /></p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
Dustin Luke Nelson is a founding editor of InDigest and the host of the InDigest Reading Series. He is a 2012 National Poetry Series finalist and has recently had work published in the Greying Ghost Pamphlet Series, Opium, METRO Twin Cities, Scud, and elsewhere. He has been a writer and producer on Radio Happy Hour and Geocachers. He lives in Astoria and at <a href="http://blogsareaboutego.blogspot.com.">blogsareaboutego.blogspot.com</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/argument-against-brevity-other-poems/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cloudy Sake</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/cloudy-sake/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/cloudy-sake/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 08:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Fiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56487</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/DavidMoscovich-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="DavidMoscovich" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56490" /></p>

Your phone buzzes again, this time it’s Azuka, she’s writing to you from work, <em>Pick me up some bananas on the way home</em>, says the text message, there’s something insidious about the tone, something unspoken, you’re reminded of the last fortune cookie you read, <em>develop your intuition</em>, that was the fortune cookie, only now do you understand the significance of that masterful ribbon of wisdom, she knows, there’s something in the tone of her text, she knows, she knows you’re meeting another girl, probably even knows her name.

By <strong>David Moscovich</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By David Moscovich.</p>
<p><strong>CLOUDY SAKE</strong></p>
<p>It’s really annoying how much time you’re spending writing this novel, don’t you have any self-control, any sense, your working gig is in the afternoon so you are in the habit of writing all morning, and this is one such morning when Kimiko sends you a freak text message, <em>Meet takoyaki today lunch?</em> Kimiko, it’s freakish because most Japanese do not spontaneously meet for lunch, not because of some inherent trait, but because most people plan weeks even months in advance, something stirs in the basest part of you, and you write back with excited fingertips, <em>I love takoyaki. What train station?</em></p>
<p>You go back to writing your “novel” while waiting for her response: </p>
<blockquote><p>On this brisk autumn day, he arranged the mannequins so that Olivia and Persephone were on the couch in front of the tea table, and Gerda was in the recliner, palm extended to make a point. He pressed play on the tape recorder, and Gerda spoke first in British upper crust falsetto: I do not believe there is inherent racism in modern Japanese society, but rather a persistent prejudice which has its roots in Japanese imperialism itself. What, objected Olivia, Japanese imperialism? Ha! responded Gerda. My dear, dear Olivia. Have you not heard of the islands of Okinawa?</p></blockquote>
<p>Your phone buzzes, and you break off, thankfully, from the pretentious tripe, and read, <em>Higashi Machi station. Meet 12 clock? Are you ok? Yes, I&#8217;m ok</em>, you write, <em>Are you ok?</em> to which she responds, <em>Ok Ok</em>, do you ask too many questions? to be safe, this time you are twenty minutes early arriving at the station, you take the escalator to street level and watch the ubiquitous compact Nissan taxis mingle in with city busses along the main thoroughfare, there seem to be no used cars in Nagasaki, you haven’t seen even a door scratched in the entire city, not that you walk around looking at car doors, but most of them seem to undergo the kind of waxing one associates with a Rolls Royce, what is this mysterious, prosperous, ordered land of no litter and cosmetically perfect automobiles? you ask yourself, and then your phone buzzes again, this time it’s Azuka, she’s writing to you from work, <em>Pick me up some bananas on the way home</em>, says the text message, there’s something insidious about the tone, something unspoken, you’re reminded of the last fortune cookie you read, <em>develop your intuition</em>, that was the fortune cookie, only now do you understand the significance of that masterful ribbon of wisdom, she knows, there’s something in the tone of her text, she knows, she knows you’re meeting another girl, probably even knows her name, abandon ship, abandon ship, you sink into a despair, knowing she will be waiting for you at the point of rendezvous, you call Kimiko to cancel the meeting, something came up, you’ll see her another time, you’re lying, there will be no other time, you’re a coward, you’ve backed down, you’ll never text another girl again, it’s all over, it’s all over now, it’s done.</p>
<p><br/><br />
<strong>AZUKA</strong></p>
<p>You conclude the 1st grade class with a singalong, <em>Hello Happy Day, How Are You</em>, you’re anxious to rip down a whiskey, in the lobby you notice there is the glass display of miniature workers pouring concrete into barrels, you pick one up to see if there is a whistle hole in its behind, there isn’t, the Assistant Principal sees you with your lips on the bronze buttocks, the janitor and Principal follow you outside to see you off, once you leave the school you tilt your golden flask at the back of the bus, the flask engraved with the initials J.T., your great grandfather who lost everything in the stock market crash of 1928, you’re texting Azuka with dinner plans, you have no heart, of course she’s already had a few beers when she calls you, you set the flask on the seat, she wants you to pick up cabbage, pork, enoki mushrooms and <em>kimchee</em> to make a spicy <em>nabe</em> tonight, you agree, Wakatta, Azu-chan, wakatta, you tell her you’ll do it and hang up the phone, you get off the bus on the ultra-wide street, all the major streets are wide in Nagasaki, a long stretch of textured yellow strips on every sidewalk, there to guide the blind, a sad reminder that even the blind have a better chance if they’re Japanese, you step into the grocery store, the beer fridge sports eight different labels with the same tasteless beer inside, you pick four tallboys to get you through dinner, intuiting some cultural blow-up and misunderstanding is about to happen with Azuka, you get stares in the checkout line, stares from the crone with the pocked face, stares from the young couple wearing berets, the clerk, though, is unable to look at you, you swipe your card, you say nothing and leave, loitering for a moment you enjoy scandalizing the façade of the grocery outside and crack open a beer, you lift the beer to your lips and take one step onto the street as a motorcycle rips through your best shirt, a black button down with thin gold stripes, the handlebars of the bike twist you onto the unforgiving ground of the sidewalk.</p>
<p><br/><br />
<strong>GAUZE</strong></p>
<p>Now a small crowd is standing above you, <em>Is he okay?</em> they ask each other, <em>I don’t know, what should we do, he can’t speak Japanese</em>, nobody bothers to actually ask you, they notice bits of blood on your foreign face, they‘re making phone calls, you brush the pendants of dirt off your pants, your sleeves are torn and the top button is missing, the groceries miraculously have landed unaffected, propped against the wall of “Californya Café” (a misspelled sulking ground behind the station), you prop yourself up and start walking, unacceptable by Japanese standards, you should reassure those around you, instead you say nothing, you’re feeling particularly misanthropic and your arm feels like one giant bee-sting, you leave them in a group discussing what to do, they could do it for hours, the motorcycle rider pedals next to you, apologizing, bowing, pedaling, begging you to stop, apologizing, bowing deeply, pleading, pedaling, bowing three times fast, sincerely apologizing, really apologizing, he’s incredibly sorry, bowing again, you’re not saying anything, your elbow is whistling bloodover your pants, you don’t care, you just want the day to be done and to nuzzle into the confusing set of cultural signifiers awaiting you at Azuka’s, she is frighteningly devoted to you, a commitment you never thought possible, it’s what drives you away, you knock and she’s there, jumping at the door, almost wagging her tail, clasping her hands, it’s surreal, is she faking it, you wonder, you callous soul-wrecker, you don’t deserve her, why would you question such a thing, of course she’s sincere, it’s you who are not sincere, she sees you’ve been hurt, the jumping stops, the argument grows even uglier when she wraps purple gauze around your arm, the gauze has Disney characters printed on it, you blame each other for what the city does to you, she kicks the bathroom door leaving a slipper print on the new white paint, you will break her heart for sure this time. </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/DavidMoscovich.jpg" alt="" title="DavidMoscovich" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56490" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://davidmoscovich.com/">David Moscovich</a> writes flash fiction and performs his texts both live and on the radio, fragmenting, ricocheting, and refurnishing language until it meets its own devolution. He lives in New York City.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/cloudy-sake/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Before the Storm</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/before-the-storm/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/before-the-storm/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 08:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Flash Fiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56481</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/AlexSheal-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="AlexSheal" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56482" /></p>

I met her in a cocktail bar, but she wasn’t working as a waitress. She was getting drunk like me at the counter, blabbing away to strangers, some of whom were queuing to order. We swooned this way and that, as if on the deck of a storm-swept ship; then she yelled in my ear. She stank of perfume and gin; and later, in her room, I wondered whether she’d splashed on the latter and drunk the former.

By <strong>Alex Sheal</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Alex Sheal.</p>
<p>I met her in a cocktail bar, but she wasn’t working as a waitress. She was getting drunk like me at the counter, blabbing away to strangers, some of whom were queuing to order. We swooned this way and that, as if on the deck of a storm-swept ship; then she yelled in my ear. She stank of perfume and gin; and later, in her room, I wondered whether she’d splashed on the latter and drunk the former.  </p>
<p>Before that, we had a conversation going something like:<br />
- You?<br />
- Yeah, hold on a minute.<br />
- I know that it’s ____ ____.  No, it’s OK.<br />
- Wait wait wait&#8230;</p>
<p>So we hit it off. I can’t remember where we were standing then, just the words and the sharp stink of gin and the other one of perfume. A number of people loitered around, some with their backs to us, like an open-mic audience whose attention has wandered. Shouting or chanting occurred at a certain point as an individual climbed onto the bar before crashing off again.</p>
<p>When we burst out the doors, it surprised me to see the hurricane had passed; moreso that not a drop of water lay in the street full of taxi drivers. Then I remembered it was November and a storm hadn’t rampaged through this city in months, years since a proper one. Which explained the lack of overturned cars and gale-ripped rooves in the vicinity, the passersby dressed neatly and looking like they had plans: not dishevelled and haunted like drunks or hurricane survivors.</p>
<p>But the storm swirled up again later, hurling our half-naked bodies from one end of her bedroom to the other. A shelf cracked my skull and she stubbed an ankle; there were weeps and yells, I recriminated and pushed a wall back with my palm. That room made no sense as a storm refuge, numberless rogue objects lying around and not enough duct tape on the windows. Her housemates panicked up and down the stairs, thumping on the walls, for dawn had turned to day and still the storm roared.</p>
<p>Somewhere in the midst of that I wondered about the perfume and the gin. I may even have muttered to her: Did you put on the gin and drink the perfume? And she probably said: Yes. She said that a lot, darting her eyes directly at mine.</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>She had the kind of figure flustered artists try to paint twenty times before throwing down their brush. Full of secrets; bright with life. All lines and turns, squiggles and swerves. I stayed in motion, thought of nothing, gripped tight with toes and fingers to happenstance wall corners and benighted bed posts.</p>
<p>Then we slept, our storm-scattered raft adrift in the afternoon sun, mouths parched, detritus trailing us across the lifeless ocean. Or did fish school beneath us, flashing like bonfire sparks in a bottomless night?</p>
<p>The weird thing – and I only remembered this later, soon after we’d parted – was the way she clamped up as the winds rose, forearms before my face, knees to her neck, head pressed groundwards, and how, damp with sweat, I had to prise her apart, one limb after the other, coaxing in the stairway.</p>
<p>I heard the following year that she died in a motorbike crash, drunk, during a season that made the papers for such pointless catastrophes.</p>
<p><em>October __, 20__</em></p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/AlexSheal.jpg" alt="" title="AlexSheal" width="590" height="332" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56482" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.facebook.com/alex.sheal">Alex Sheal</a>’s fiction has previously featured in <em>Litro</em>, <em>Untitled Books</em> and <em>The New Writer</em>, and he has been the recipient of the New Writer Novella Prize and David Higham Award. He lives in Hanoi, Vietnam, and is the co-founder of photography tour company <a href="http://www.vietnaminfocus.com">Vietnam in Focus</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/before-the-storm/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>century of dislocation</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/century-of-dislocation/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/century-of-dislocation/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 15:42:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>David Winters</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Criticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56520</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/speedboat.jpg" alt="speedboat.jpg" width="420" height="179" />

The collective anxiety of Manhattan life portrayed in <i>Speedboat</i>, along with the more personal anxiety and paranoia experienced by Kate Ennis in <i>Pitch Dark</i>, are ones that are still resoundingly relatable to our lives today. Substitute Xanax for the Valium and Percodan scattered throughout <i>Speedboat</i> and <i>Pitch Dark</i>, and one has our world, a world in which external realities affect our inner states of mind, a world we inhabit with others whose differences in some way become part of our own story: “As much as this is the age of crime, after all, this is the century of dislocation. Not just for journalists or refugees: for everyone.”

<b>K. Thomas Kahn</b> reviews <b>Renata Adler's</b>'s newly reissued novels <i>Speedboat</i> and <i>Pitch Dark</i>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By K. Thomas Kahn.</p>
<p><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56534" src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/speedboat.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="357" /></p>
<p><strong><a href="http://www.nybooks.com/books/imprints/classics/speedboat/"><em>Speedboat</em> </a></strong>and <strong><a href="http://www.nybooks.com/books/imprints/classics/pitch-dark/"><em>Pitch Dark</em></a> </strong>by <strong><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renata_Adler">Renata Adler</a></strong>, reissued by <strong><a href="http://www.nybooks.com/books/">NYRB Classics</a></strong>, 2013</p>
<blockquote><p>Do I need to stylize it, then, or can I tell it as it was?&#8230; Is that where it begins? I don’t know. I don’t know where it begins. It is where I am.</p></blockquote>
<p>These lines, from the opening pages of Renata Adler’s second novel, <em>Pitch Dark</em> (1983), should rightly be read as a self-reflexive rumination on the fragmented and nonlinear prose style in her two fictional works, an endeavor to centralize the act of storytelling (and, with it, the conflicts between objectivity and subjectivity) begun by Adler when <em>Speedboat</em> was published in 1976. The impact of <em>Speedboat</em> upon writers as diverse as David Foster Wallace, Elizabeth Hardwick, and David Shields proves its status as a <em>sui generis</em> text. As Guy Trebay notes:</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Speedboat</em> &#8230; stamp[s] contemporary consciousness with its singular mark. Because the book prefigured by decades certain telegraphic forms of communication we now take for granted, it is easy to miss the point that Speedboat got there well before e-mails or Facebook or Twitter.</p></blockquote>
<p>Because <em>Speedboat</em> in effect reinvented the novel with its unique mix of vignettes, kaleidoscopic and panoramic reportage, and a presciently liberal social commentary, Adler’s prefiguration of how contemporary life is ingested in—and therefore best understood by—fragments represents a stylistic shift in narration. As such, <em>Speedboat</em> is a seminal text in the history of the literary novel’s evolution. Now that it and its companion novel <em>Pitch Dark</em> have been reissued by the New York Review of Books after being out of print for some twenty-five years, one can read these texts anew, posit their importance to experimental fiction written in the wake of <em>Speedboat</em>, and also admire Adler’s gift for incisive social and personal insights that are still relevant and resonant to this day.</p>
<p>Both <em>Speedboat</em>’s and <em>Pitch Dark</em>’s narrators are reporters. In the former novel, Jen Fain shifts back and forth in time as she relates experiences at boarding school, graduate school, cocktail parties with academics, interviews conducted with people of different classes and races in her capacity as reporter, and the political conflicts that affect a liberal, bohemian social clique whose globetrotting always brings them back to Manhattan as if the city were a magnet. (These experiences are also Kate Ennis’s in <em>Pitch Dark</em>, but the later novel focuses more on Ennis’s psychological conflict than on the more external factors with which <em>Speedboat</em> is concerned.) As Adler eschews plot almost entirely, the vignettes Jen Fain offers form a whole only as one reads. Muriel Spark observes how, when reading Adler’s prose, “[y]ou have to piece it together as you would if you had picked up a stranger’s private journal.”</p>
<p>Although <em>Speedboat</em> is more of a public chronicle than a private document like <em>Pitch Dark</em>, it is still very much a subjective view of city life and how this affects an individual’s consciousness. Fain observes: “I find that many city people give their most minute attention to the ethics of found objects, small.” In many ways, this is one of the pressing issues in <em>Speedboat</em>: how the mundane encounters in our lives—the bureaucratic idiocies at the institution where Fain serves as an adjunct; telephone calls from PBS soliciting donations; international phone calls with bad connections, effectively rendering them party-lines (as Matthew Specktor has also termed Adler’s prose style in his <a href="http://www.believermag.com/issues/201302/?read=article_specktor">piece</a> in <em>The Believer</em>); the political and intimate disconnect one has with one’s lovers—are like pieces in a puzzle which can never be placed together into a concrete whole, and yet, if we are to make sense of our individuality, must somehow be mapped on to our subjectivities, even if our attempts fail: “Something lost in translation there, perhaps. Everywhere.”</p>
<p>And while “[p]eople seem to be unhappy in so many different ways,” Fain must incorporate the fragments of other people’s experiences in order to fathom her own. In this way, “the inevitable is being interrupted by strangers all the time,” thus affecting the narrative we attempt to construct for ourselves:</p>
<blockquote><p>The plot of things separating, not so common, disintegration, breaking up. The plot of one thing following in the track of another, as in thrillers, chases. The plot of things parallel. Suspense, which has time as an obstacle to a resolution in the future. Nostalgia, which has time as an obstacle to a resolution in the past. Maybe there are stories, even, like solitaire or canasta: they are shuffled and dealt, then they do or do not come out.</p></blockquote>
<p>Also affecting our narratives are, as Trebay believes Adler presages, our modes of communication and travel, which combine to further displace us from other people despite how necessary they are to the task of trying to understand our identities in relation to the world in which we live: “The jet, the telephone, the boat, the train, the television. Dislocations.”</p>
<p><em>Pitch Dark</em> takes dislocation as its main theme. Like Jen Fain, <em>Pitch Dark</em>’s Kate Ennis is a reporter, and, to some extent, the social, cultural, and political background with which <em>Speedboat</em> deals is one the reader must keep in mind when reading <em>Pitch Dark</em>. Due to this, the two novels read as companion pieces, with the first-person narrators blending into each other, complete with shared experiences and a common worldview. (Indeed, in the second section of <em>Pitch Dark</em>, the narrator even becomes Adler herself, causing Spark to wonder: “Does Miss Adler mean to suggest that she herself is Kate Ennis?”)</p>
<p>Ennis’s main conflict in Adler’s second novel is whether to leave a married man with whom she has been having an affair for eight years. More poetic in both style and depth than <em>Speedboat</em>, <em>Pitch Dark</em> uses repetition to convey the circuitous meanderings of its narrator as she ponders whether or not to leave Jake (a conflict and character name that allude to Penelope Mortimer’s<a href="http://www.nybooks.com/books/imprints/classics/the-pumpkin-eater/"><em> The Pumpkin Eater</em></a>). Two oft-repeated refrains that get to the heart of Ennis’s mental state throughout the course of <em>Pitch Dark</em> are as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p>You are, you know, you were the nearest thing to a real story to happen in my life. Did I throw the most important thing perhaps, by accident, away?</p></blockquote>
<p>And while Ennis muses on her past with Jake, her present is sullied by the fact that her identity—and<em> Pitch Dark</em> is very much Ennis’s quest for autonomy—is subsumed beneath Jake’s as well as the other events in her life. In her attempt to excavate herself, Kate’s internal journey is mirrored by an external one that moves from Manhattan to New York State, from Orcas Island to the Irish countryside.</p>
<p>Increasingly, Ennis’s travels give rise to feelings of paranoia and both cultural and self-dislocation: “I still have the sense, how to put this, that the land, even the sleeping country towns, know of me.” The titular section of <em>Pitch Dark</em> is the most plot-driven, but it is still very much interior in focus as Ennis deals with an ever-mounting sense of panic after a slight fender bender in a tiny Irish town, an incident that becomes a Kafkaesque nightmare involving a lorry driver as a bizarre “teamster” in a middle-of-the-night motorway ride to Dublin in a rented vehicle Ennis feels sure is under police scrutiny and which has hardly any gas in the tank. Spark is spot-on when she remarks of this section: “This is a superb piece of nightmare writing.”</p>
<p>Like Jen Fain in <em>Speedboat</em>, Kate Ennis discovers that to think of the self as unaffected by one’s environment is a flawed endeavor; to this end, both narrators realize that the act of storytelling in which the “I” is front and center risks missing material or else running against the problem of how to incorporate it: “Because it would be part of what I know, part of what I have to tell, that I understand something, not everything, but something&#8230;” In this way, the quote with which I began this piece comes to suggest that a fragmented, solipsistic style is the best way to unearth one’s identity from the events that shape (and sometimes destroy) it. Describing a diary she kept in her twenties, Ennis observes:</p>
<blockquote><p>The penmanship was fine, still those clear, regular capitals. But the record was of moods. There were no events, few names, no facts, no indication of what happened&#8230; What few names there were appeared uncharacterized, and not part of any incident or sentence; and the moods were described only to the extent of being up or down, like a chart of the stock market or of an illness&#8230; The events simply were not there, and, more surprisingly, I could not reconstruct them.</p></blockquote>
<p>The collective anxiety of Manhattan life portrayed in <em>Speedboat</em>, along with the more personal anxiety and paranoia experienced by Kate Ennis in <em>Pitch Dark</em>, are ones that are still resoundingly relatable to our lives today. As Specktor writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>[Adler’s] work hasn’t dated: its depth of engagement on every level—with private life and the life of state—its comedy and perspective, its shrewd observation of everything from literature to politics to manners and back again, these qualities mark Adler’s work as fathomless, as damn near inexhaustible.</p></blockquote>
<p>Adler’s work is an analysis of the individual in ”an age of crime,” as she phrases it in <em>Pitch Dark</em>, one in which “[v]ery few of us, it seems fair to say, are morally at ease.” As Jen Fain remarks in <em>Speedboat</em>, as she attempts to quell mass hysteria on a tiny charter plane “start[ing] down the runway of the Fishers Island airport”: “For flights I have these pills. &#8230; I counted and found I had enough painkilling pills for everyone.” Substitute Xanax for the Valium and Percodan scattered throughout <em>Speedboat</em> and <em>Pitch Dark</em>, and one has our world today, a world in which external realities affect our inner states of mind, a world we inhabit with others whose differences in some way become part of our own story: “As much as this is the age of crime, after all, this is the century of dislocation. Not just for journalists or refugees: for everyone.”</p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR </strong><br />
<strong>K. Thomas Kahn</strong> is a writer based in New York City whose criticism has appeared in the <em>Los Angeles Review of Books</em>, <em>The Quarterly Conversation</em>, <em>Bookslut</em>, <em>Music and Literature Magazine</em>, <em>The Millions</em>, and other venues. He is the curator of <a href="http://twitter.com/proustitute">@proustitute</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/century-of-dislocation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Metaphysical foundations for science</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/metaphysical-foundations-for-science/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/metaphysical-foundations-for-science/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 08:00:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Richard Marshall</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The End Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=54307</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/ejlowe-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="ejlowe" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56465" /></p>

Philosophical debate should be open to anyone, but one can only take part in such a debate if one recognises, as every rational person should, that there is such a thing as a philosophical debate, which differs in important ways from purely factual debates.  Unfortunately, this very simple and, on reflection, very obvious fact seems to elude a number of well-known scientists who, in the course of publishing best-selling works of popular science, have taken the opportunity to pour scorn on philosophy. They should follow the lead of their wiser and greater forebears, including Newton and Einstein, who were far from being unphilosophical in their thinking, and whose philosophical cast of mind contributed in a major way to the originality and importance of their theories.

Continuing the <em>End Times</em> series, <strong>Richard Marshall</strong> interviews <strong>E.J. Lowe</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/ejlowe.jpg" alt="" title="ejlowe" width="590" height="384" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56465" /><br />
[Photo: <a href="http://www.ttahko.net/">Tuomas E. Tahko</a>]</p>
<p><a href="http:/www.dur.ac.uk/philosophy/staff/?username=dfl0ejl">E.J. Lowe</a> interviewed by Richard Marshall.</p>
<p>E.J. Lowe is a frost-cool deep fry who goes to the heavy core of the metaphysical lodestone and thinks about kinds of being all the time by  building a system in the old style in order to get a grip on the very nature of reality itself. He thinks metaphysics is a slow business but we shouldn&#8217;t be fooled into thinking slowness is stasis, doesn&#8217;t think that common sense is riddled with confusions but there are some inconsistencies in it, thinks ontologies are expensive and in-car/out-car ones are too cheap, thinks there&#8217;s a four category ontology, thinks Aristotle the king of the metaphysicians but prefers his own version of the ontological square, thinks hard about the nature of the laws of nature, thinks about universals and particulars, about powers and categories, can count tables but not red things, thinks empty sets can&#8217;t be empty sets, thinks he has hands, thinks freewill can&#8217;t be disproved by any empirical evidence, and thinks scientists should be more philosophical when entering important philosophical debates than they have tended to be recently. Which makes him hard-core.     </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> What made you become a philosopher? Were you always having these <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Survey-Metaphysics-Lowe/9780198752530/?a_aid=3ammagazine">metaphysical</a> thoughts even when young? Or did they just emerge?</p>
<p><strong>EJ Lowe:</strong> As a schoolboy, I was extremely interested in science and mathematics, but especially in astronomy and cosmology. I had my own telescope – a 6-inch Newtonian reflector – of which I was inordinately proud and fond, although light pollution in my home town was so bad as to make it pretty useless for observing the stars. Cosmology was in an exciting state of turbulence in those days, with the rivalry between the now accepted ‘Big Bang’ theory and Fred Hoyle’s elegant theory of the continuous creation of matter and energy, according to which the universe, even as it continuously expands, remains spatiotemporally homogeneous on the large scale. I might even go so far as to say that Hoyle was my scientific ‘hero’ at that time. I went up to Cambridge University in 1968 – where Hoyle was Professor of Astronomy – to read Natural Sciences, with the hope of eventually getting into cosmology. But I found the first-year course dull and tedious, especially the experimental side of it, and also began to realise that I probably didn’t possess the necessary mathematical aptitude to be really successful as a theoretical physicist. So, after one year, I changed to History, and took a BA in that subject two years later (1971). I’d always been interested in history anyway, and soon discovered that I could concentrate a good deal on the history of political thought, which especially attracted me. This introduced me to early modern political philosophy, including the works of Locke, which soon led me on to early modern metaphysics and epistemology. However, this wasn’t what first acquainted me with philosophy. My eldest brother, who is 11 years older than me, took a degree in physics at Oxford and then went on to do the BPhil in philosophy, eventually becoming a lecturer in that subject in London for a while, so even as a young teenager I had a pretty good idea of what philosophy is. As a teenager, I started to try to work out a metaphysical system of my own, partly drawing on my (admittedly rather limited) understanding of developments in modern physics, especially the idea of symmetry and equivalence principles of the sort that lie at the heart of Einstein’s theories of relativity – which I tried my best to understand. </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/9780198752530.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-54317" /></p>
<p>My idea was that one might hope to frame some very general equivalence principle which enabled one to see that all the great metaphysical systems are ultimately just different ways of formulating the same basic facts about the ultimate structure of reality, one implication of this being that no empirical test could possibly choose between them. This, I thought, fitted in well with Karl Popper’s idea that what distinguishes science from metaphysics is that scientific theories are empirically falsifiable whereas metaphysical theories are not – although this doesn’t mean that metaphysical theories are meaningless or worthless, indeed, quite the contrary, since they provide indispensable ‘framework’ principles for scientific theorising. Actually, I still believe something like this to be the case. Anyway, in time I began to realise that my early interest in cosmology was really an interest in fundamental metaphysics and ontology, and this is what eventually took me away from history and political philosophy to pure philosophy. After completing my BA degree, I wanted to switch to do a PhD in philosophy, but Cambridge wouldn’t let me do that, so I departed to Oxford to do the BPhil in philosophy and subsequently a DPhil. At that time, I concentrated in metaphysics and the philosophy of science, having Rom Harré as my BPhil dissertation supervisor and <a href="http:/www.3ammagazine.com/3am/whisperer-of-doubt/">Simon Blackburn</a> as my DPhil supervisor, with a thesis entitled ‘Induction and Causal Inference’ (1975). In that thesis, I criticised Hume’s account of induction and causation (while recognising that he espoused what later came to be known as a ‘sceptical realist’ view of causation and causal powers) and developed a theory of ampliative reasoning which appeals to our knowledge of causal powers, linking the notion of such powers with a ‘dispositional’ account of natural laws according to which such laws primarily concern natural kinds and only derivatively their particular instances (a view which resembles the Armstrong-Dretske-Tooley view of laws as involving universals rather than regularities amongst particulars, but also differs importantly from that view with regard to the type of universals involved). These ideas eventually developed into the view that I defended in my first book, <em>Kinds of Being</em> The foregoing is, in as short as space as possible, a summary of my philosophical development and education.<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> Armstrong, van Inwagen and Lewis (and Lewis in particular I guess) kind of give the general options for contemporary metaphysics. Are you cutting free from these and setting out a new option? You think Lewis’s approach tends to be engaged in an exciting battle between revisionary and merely descriptive metaphysics, which is a thrill but may not help us understand better the nature of the world don’t you? Is serious metaphysics dull?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> I have always thought that metaphysics needs to be tackled systematically, rather than piecemeal. I liken the task to that of putting together the pieces of a gigantic jigsaw puzzle: it’s no use just trying to perfect many small but disconnected parts of the puzzle in the hope that these will eventually fit together, since it’s likely there are several different ways in which any small number of pieces will fit together, no more than one of which will be <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Truth-Truth-making-Lowe/9781844651450/?a_aid=3ammagazine">correct</a>. Rather, you need to work simultaneously on the ‘big picture’ and on its many parts. </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/9781844651450.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-54318" /></p>
<p>I don’t altogether accept P. F. Strawson’s distinction between ‘revisionary’ and ‘descriptive’ metaphysics, much though I admire his book <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Individuals-PF-Strawson/9780415051859/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Individuals</a></em>, which was in fact one of the first serious books in metaphysics that I read, long before I became a student of philosophy. I do, however, follow Aristotle and Locke in taking it that ‘common sense’ is a reasonable – indeed, the only reasonable – starting point for philosophical thinking. But it is only a starting point, and some common sense ideas will inevitably have to be abandoned by the philosopher, since some of them, when pursued to their logical conclusions, give rise to puzzles and paradoxes, which it is the task of the philosopher to try to resolve – an idea, of course, that goes back at least as far as Socrates. The revisionary/descriptive distinction is best seen as marking the poles of a spectrum of positions, with the most sensible and defensible positions lying somewhere in the middle. Common sense cannot intelligibly be abandoned completely, but neither can it be defended from every charge of incoherence. The task of the philosopher is to strike the right balance between its rejection and its revision. Russell once said that common sense leads to science, and science shows common sense to be false. But that is too stark a judgement. Certainly, many common sense notions – for instance, those of so-called ‘folk physics’ – are shown to be false by modern science. But a physics which is so disconnected with common sense as to be nothing more than an abstract mathematical formalism can at best be of only instrumental value: it cannot help us to understand the fundamental nature of reality, which is the aspiration of metaphysics. In pursuing its task, metaphysics must take notice of developments in theoretical science, but should not be in servitude to them. It will need to deploy distinctive formal methods and tools of its own, but these too should not simply be carried over slavishly from logic and mathematics – for instance, in the shape of formal logic, set theory, and classical mereology – as though metaphysics were some kind of applied logic or mathematics. In my view, metaphysics, with ontology at its heart, is an autonomous and fundamental mode of inquiry, beholden neither to the empirical sciences nor to the a priori sciences of logic and mathematics. It really is, as Aristotle said, ‘first philosophy’, and as such an implicit pre-requisite for any more specific form of intellectual inquiry whatever. In that sense, I am not a ‘naturalistic’ metaphysician. But my kind of metaphysics is far from being ‘dull’, I would venture to say. It seeks to articulate a coherent system of ontological categories and a consistent account of the fundamental formal relations obtaining between entities belonging to these categories, in terms of which we may hope to understand the fundamental structure of reality as a whole. That is just about the most ambitious intellectual task that anyone could hope to undertake. And because it is so difficult, we should not be surprised that progress in it is slow – much slower than in theoretical physics or mathematics, for instance. We should not mistake its slowness for complete stasis. Genuine progress can be and has been made in metaphysics.   <br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> You say that common sense ontology is riddled with confusions – are these errors? If so, how come we manage to survive? Survival suggests either that they can’t be all that confused, or that common sense ontology isn’t that important. Both alternatives seem to be threats to the whole business of metaphysical examination of ontologies, especially revisionary metaphysics. What’s your push-back?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> I’ve already implicitly answered this question. I don’t think that common sense ontology is ‘riddled’ with confusions, only that it harbours some inconsistencies which emerge in the form of various puzzles and paradoxes. These inconsistencies only manifest themselves when common sense notions are pushed to their limits, and that’s why common sense thinking serves us well enough for everyday purposes, or is ‘adaptive’, to use the jargon of evolutionary psychology. One task of philosophy in general and of metaphysics in particular is to tease out these hidden inconsistencies and consider how best to deal with them – either by replacing common sense notions with significantly different ones, or by revising common sense notions in certain ways. It is this process that eventually leads to the development of a comprehensive system of ontology, such as the one that I currently favour, the ‘four-category ontology’, as I call it, which has its historical roots in Aristotle’s early work, the <em>Categories</em>. A good example of the sort of puzzle or paradox that I have in mind is the ancient problem of the Ship of Theseus, which forces us to rethink certain aspects of our common sense understanding of the identity of material objects over time (their diachronic identity). Another equally ancient one is the problem of Dion and Theon (Theon being Dion except for, or ‘minus’, one of his feet, so that when Dion loses that foot he coincides with Theon, even though, it seems, Dion and Theon must remain numerically distinct). This problem forces us to rethink our understanding of the identity of material objects at a single time (their synchronic identity).<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> I think we get a good handle on the way you come at metaphysics in your subtle argument against Hawthorne’s views about ‘parity’ and ‘plenitude lovers’ when discussing the in-car/out-car example of <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Dividing-Reality-Eli-Hirsch/9780195111422/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Eli Hirsch</a>. You conclude that we shouldn’t be supplementing common sense ontology on the grounds of parity but instead ‘rather than either embrace and add to that ontology or simply reject it, we do better to reform or refine it.’ You worry that contemporary metaphysicians don’t handle common sense ontology carefully enough don’t you. You are kind of harsh: you say that if you’re a young metaphysician wanting to discover new kinds of objects you should retrain in physics! Could you explain why you disagree with the ‘plenitude lover’ and their notion of ‘parity’ – and just explain the <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Quantifier-Variance-Realism-Eli-Hirsch/9780199732111/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Hirsch</a> example which is a pretty cool and weird scenario?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> The in-car/out-car example can be summarised this way. Consider your drive to work each morning. As we ordinarily think of it, you get into your car and drive it out of the garage. Here, a single object – your car – moves continuously across a borderline, marked by the door of your garage. But it seems that we might think of this situation differently, as follows. Inside your garage there is your ‘in-car’. As you drive out, this in-car shrinks until it eventually disappears, and at the same time another object, your ‘out-car’, grows outside your garage until it eventually reaches the same length that your in-car originally had. Here there are two adjacent objects, neither of which moves, but one grows as the other shrinks. (If you drive further than the door of your garage, the same process is repeated with a subsequent series of non-moving but alternately growing and shrinking objects.) The first way of thinking is the common sense way, but can we really charge the other way with being any less satisfactory as a way of thinking of the situation? Should we say that the two ways are just two of many ‘equivalent’ ways of thinking of the situation, no one of which should be privileged as being the ‘true’ way? My answers to these questions are ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ respectively. I think common sense is correct in supposing there to be objects which retain their identity through processes of movement across space – at least, if this is wrong, then it is only wrong for reasons to do with issues in fundamental physics. I don’t think that there are any such things as in-cars and out-cars. Just thinking about the example in isolation may not reveal any problem with the in-car/out-car way of describing the situation. But we have to remember that what we are looking for, as metaphysicians, is a comprehensive system of ontology, not just a piecemeal treatment of particular cases. To be consistent in the example under consideration, we have, for example, to apply the in-car/out-car mode of description also to you, the driver. We shall have to speak of ‘you’ not in terms of your being a single person who moves from being inside to being outside your garage, but in terms of a shrinking ‘in-you’ and a growing ‘out-you’, which are numerically distinct objects. So, suppose you start having a thought as you go through the door of your garage (as we would ordinarily describe it). On the in-you/out-you model, we’ll have to say that in-you begins the thought and out-you completes it. So one and the same thought must be attributed to two distinct subjects, and this appears to make no sense. </p>
<p>As I’ve just suggested, there might turn out to be reasons based in fundamental physics for thinking that the common sense notion of objects moving through space is problematic – for instance, that we do better to think of ‘movement’ as really consisting in variations of mass/energy density across tracts of spacetime. An analogy would be with the way in which we now understand that sea-waves don’t literally move in from the sea towards the beach, but consist in the regular rising and falling of the seawater’s height above the seabed, giving the illusion of real movement. But there’s no reason to abandon the common sense notion of moving objects, or to regard it as merely ‘conventional’, on purely philosophical grounds. It is deeply entrenched in common sense ontology, which is largely very successful in this regard, and it’s very difficult to see how it could be rejected without rendering other aspects of that ontology – such as its inclusion of ourselves as objects which both move and think – incoherent. So it should only be rejected as a last resort. The in-car/out-car fantasy might sound exotic and intriguing, but this is a cheap way to try to install a radically new ontology. Fundamental physics, with its invocation of such strange entities as superstrings, which have a genuinely explanatory role to play in physical science, is the place to look for interesting new and non-commonsensical types of entity. Such entities can genuinely earn their keep, but not so entities such as in-cars and out-cars. In fact, the latter are really just parasitic upon common-sense ontology, as their very names suggest: the only way to introduce them into philosophical discourse is by way of redescribing a common-sense scenario, such as your morning drive to work, in a bizarre new fashion. Our understanding of the in-car/out-car description of the scenario would be impossible without this reliance upon our prior common sense description of it. That’s not the case with entities like superstrings, where even the ‘string’ metaphor is not essential to understanding their nature.<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> You’ve written a couple of books about <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Locke-on-Human-Understanding-Lowe/9780415100915/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Locke</a>. Do you find <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Locke-Lowe/9780415283489/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Locke’s</a> metaphysics of more than historical interest? And is he a good example of the way you think contemporary metaphysicians should operate?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> It was more by accident than by design that I wrote the first of these books on Locke. A former student of mine – <a href="http:/www.3ammagazine.com/3am/mindful/">Tim Crane</a>, in fact – asked me if I’d write it for the new ‘Guidebook’ series that Routledge was starting, in the mid-1990s. I lectured on modern philosophy for many years, and maybe Tim enjoyed my lectures on Locke – I do hope so! Anyway, I was happy to write on Locke, both because he is, like Aristotle, a philosopher with a healthy regard for common sense, combined with a respect for developments in empirical and theoretical science, and because I felt, and still feel, that Locke is often traduced by his commentators, who are too often willing to attribute indefensible and even downright silly views to him. Moreover, I share Locke’s general opinion about many key matters in metaphysics, epistemology, and the philosophy of mind and action. For instance, like him, I defend volitionism in the philosophy of action. So, in that first book, <em>Locke on Human Understanding</em>, I tried to offer sympathetic but faithful interpretations of Locke’s views and defences of modern versions of some of them. But one deficiency of Locke’s overall approach, I feel, is that it is not sufficiently systematic – it is too piecemeal. In this respect, as well as others, I consider Aristotle to be the vastly superior philosopher, indeed as being unsurpassed.<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> You have defended what you call a ‘<a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Four-category-Ontology-Lowe/9780199229819/?a_aid=3ammagazine">four-category ontology</a>’, something that has an ancestry that traces back to Aristotle. It’s often useful to know what a philosopher sees as rival positions that require seeing off. So before telling us about this ontology, what are the rival positions that you are facing up to and why do you find them inadequate?</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/9780199229819.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-54311" /></p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> I am first and foremost opposed to those metaphysicians who see no need at all to frame a system of ontological categories (categories of being). I describe them as espousing a ‘no category ontology’. Typically, these philosophers think that we can just talk indiscriminately of ‘entities’ or ‘things’, distinguishing between them merely in terms of different descriptive predicates whose application is determined purely empirically. This is the ontology of Lewis Carroll’s walrus and the carpenter, who spoke of many things – of ships and shoes and sealing wax, cabbages and kings. In logico-philosophical terms, an ‘entity’, for such a theorist, is just any possible value of a bound variable, in line with W. V. Quine’s famous dictum, ‘to be is to be the value of a (bound) variable’. Even Quine himself didn’t really espouse a no category ontology, but rather one containing two basic categories: spacetime regions and sets (although at one point he thought that the regions could be reduced to sets). Such an ontology clearly has very little in common with common-sense ontology and that, fundamentally, is why I am not at all sympathetic to it. I don’t believe, for instance, that it can find a satisfactory way to accommodate ourselves, as thinking subjects, amongst the furniture of reality. </p>
<p>Other fashionable modern systems of categorial ontology include D. M. Armstrong’s ontology of states of affairs, with particulars and universals as their ‘constituents’, and the pure ‘trope’ ontology, which is a one-category ontology of property-instances. With regard to states of affairs, I find difficulty in understanding their supposedly ‘non-mereological’ mode of composition (as, notoriously, did David Lewis). With regard to pure trope ontology, I find difficulty in understanding how tropes are supposed to be individuated – that is, what determines their identity conditions. I think much better of the two-category ontology of C. B. Martin and John Heil, which includes not only tropes (or ‘modes’) but also, as an irreducible type of entity, objects or ‘individual substances’, conceived as bearers of such tropes. Where I disagree with this system is with its rejection of universals of any type, which I, like Armstrong, regard as indispensable for a satisfactory account of natural laws.<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> So you defend your ‘ontological square’. How does this work?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> The term ‘ontological square’ is not one that I coined myself, but I am very happy to use it. The square is a diagram depicting the formal ontological relationships between the entities in my four fundamental ontological categories: the categories of object (or individual substance), (substantial) kind, attribute, and mode. The bottom left corner of the square is occupied by objects, the bottom right by modes, the top left by kinds, and the top right by attributes. Kinds and attributes are universals, whereas objects and modes are particulars. Accordingly, objects instantiate (are particular instances of) kinds and modes instantiate (are particular instances of) attributes, so each vertical side of the square consists of an upward-directed arrow denoting the formal ontological relation of instantiation. Next, attributes and modes are properties, whereas objects and kinds are property-bearers, i.e. are entities which are characterized by properties. Accordingly, each horizontal side of the square consists of a right-to-left-directed arrow denoting the formal ontological relation of characterisation. Finally, there is a diagonal arrow leading from the bottom left (object) corner to the top right (attribute) corner, denoting the formal ontological relation of exemplification.                                                                                              </p>
<blockquote><p><strong> Kinds </strong>            characterisation       <strong>Attributes</strong></p>
<p>     <em>instantiation</em>       <em> exemplification </em>      <em>instantiation</em></p>
<p><strong>Objects</strong>             <em>characterisation </em>    <strong>Modes</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>My version of the ontological square is based on a four-fold distinction that Aristotle introduces very early in the <em>Categories</em>, utilising the notions of ‘being in a subject’ and ‘being said of a subject’. According to Aristotle, individual substances (my ‘objects’) are neither in a subject nor said of a subject, substantial kinds (in his terms, species and genera) are said of but not in a subject, attributes (as I call them) are both in a subject and said of a subject, and modes (individual accidents or particularised properties) are in a subject but not said of a subject. Naturally, I prefer my version to Aristotle’s, but the difference between them is not enormous. Both his and my version map rather nicely on to syntactical features of sentences in everyday natural language, and this is part of what makes them align with common-sense thinking. For instance, there is a clear difference between saying something like ‘Rover is a dog’, in which we assign Rover, a particular animal, to a certain natural kind or species, and saying something like ‘Rover is brown’, in which we attribute a certain property or quality to Rover. Modern first-order predicate logic completely obliterates this distinction, representing both sentences as having the logical form ‘Fa’. My view is that our formal logic should perspicuously reflect our fundamental categorial ontology, so that modern first-order predicate logic is, in my view, deficient and in need of revision in this respect. Too many modern metaphysicians uncritically accept the formalism of modern first-order predicate logic and allow it to influence their thoughts about ontology. Ontology should drive formal logic, not the reverse, in my opinion.<br />
 <br />
<strong>3:AM:</strong> This is a system that you think handles laws of nature and the power-categorical distinction better than rivals. Starting with laws of nature, how does your theory conceive of laws of nature and what does it do better than Armstrong’s view, which I guess is the most powerful contemporary rival view?</p>
<p><strong>EJL:</strong> My view about laws of nature can be explained fairly simply in terms of the ontological square. There is an arrow denoting characterisation going from the top right (attribute) corner of the square to the top left (kind) corner. In other words, attributes (which are one type of universal) are said to characterise kinds (which are another type of universal). Sentences expressing such facts have the form ‘Ks are F’ – for example, ‘Dogs are carnivorous’ and ‘Planets move in elliptical orbits’. Linguists call such sentences ‘generics’. ‘Dogs are carnivorous’ doesn’t mean the same as ‘All dogs are carnivorous’, which attributes the property of being carnivorous to each and every individual dog. The truth of ‘Dogs are carnivorous’ is consistent with the truth of ‘Rover is a dog and Rover is not carnivorous’, because Rover might be an abnormal dog. Armstrong, like me, thinks that natural laws involve universals rather than particulars, but he recognises no distinction between substantial universals (kinds) and attributes. Thus, he takes the basic form of a natural law, in the simplest sort of case, to be ‘N(F, G)’, where F and G are first-order attributes (that is, attributes of particulars) and N is a second-order relational universal of ‘necessitation’, holding between first-order attributes. So, for example, he would regard Kepler’s first law of planetary motion, which I earlier expressed in the form ‘Planets move in elliptical orbits’, as having the logical form ‘Being a planet necessitates moving in an elliptical orbit’. My way of expressing the law is clearly much more in tune with everyday natural language and avoids any appeal to a ‘second-order’ relational universal. Armstrong’s account is particularly vulnerable to what is known as ‘the inference problem’, posed by critics such as Bas van Fraassen. According to Armstrong, ‘N(F, G)’ entails ‘For all x, if Fx then Gx’ (where the variable ‘x’ ranges over particulars), but it’s not clear what licenses this inference, which doesn’t appear to be formally valid. My account doesn’t have this problem because, according to it, ‘Planets move in elliptical orbits’ – for instance – doesn’t entail ‘Every planet is moving in an elliptical orbit’ (which is clearly not strictly true, given the gravitational interference between the planets and other disturbing factors) but only ‘Every planet is disposed to move in an elliptical orbit’, in which only a disposition or tendency so to move is ascribed to all individual planets: and my theory of dispositions or powers explains why this is so and why the corresponding inference is formally valid. (The technical details are rather too complex to be described here, but can be found in the last few chapters of my book <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/More-Kinds-Being-Lowe/9781405182560/?a_aid=3ammagazine">More Kinds of Being</a></em>; I also say more about these matters in my newest book, <em><a href="http://www.bookdepository.com/Forms-Thought-Lowe/9781107001251/?a_aid=3ammagazine">Forms of Thought</a></em>.) </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/metaphysical-foundations-for-science/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The players of games</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-players-of-games/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-players-of-games/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 16:13:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Max Dunbar</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Criticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56458</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/doublebindpreview.jpg" alt="" title="doublebindpreview" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56477" /></p>

CagePrisoners is an old tale but it is indicative of wider problems. The Great Game was a term for the swashbuckling imperial rivalry between Britain and Russia for Central Asian rule. It continued well into the Cold War with players like Kissinger and Nixon making alliances and manipulating peoples like Haig with his toy soldiers. Now the left has discovered its own version of the Game - where all that matters is strategic partnerships and the language of resistance, and secularism, liberty and the rule of law are discarded as bourgeois frivolities. The results for people who actually are fighting for freedom, particularly dissidents in Islamic countries, are disastrous. The antiwar left doesn't support the rights of women: indeed, we know that the SWP, the driving force behind the antiwar movement, does not even support the rights of female activists in its own organisation. Forget the anti-imperialist rubric. Feminism is key to everything. It's the only recent radicalism that has worked and has to be supported if the suffering in the Arab world will ever end. To paraphrase Orwell, hope lies with women.

<strong>Max Dunbar</strong> reviews <strong>Meredith Tax</strong>'s <em>Double Bind</em>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Max Dunbar.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/doublebind.jpg" alt="" title="doublebind" width="298" height="425" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56474" /></p>
<p><a href="http://www.lulu.com/shop/meredith-tax/double-bind-the-muslim-right-the-anglo-american-left-and-universal-human-rights/paperback/product-20639503.html"><em>Double Bind: The Muslim Right, The Anglo-American Left, and Universal Human Rights</em></a>, <a href="http://www.meredithtax.org/books/double-bind-muslim-right-anglo-american-left-and-universal-human-rights-0">Meredith Tax</a>, Centre for Secular Space 2013</p>
<p><a href="http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/nick-cohen/2013/02/lone-voice-against-terror/">A lot has been said, a lot has been written</a>, about the treachery of the Western left, its alliance with the religious far right, and its abandonment of solidarity and justice and freedom. You may well be bored of the discussion by now. Isn&#8217;t this just political positioning? We&#8217;re only really talking about a few extremists here, aren&#8217;t we? How do you define &#8216;left&#8217; anyway? But ideas can impact in ways you haven&#8217;t thought about. If a bunch of placard-waving career activists organise a demonstration alongside the Muslim Brotherhood, that doesn&#8217;t matter. <a href="http://www.nybooks.com/blogs/nyrblog/2012/feb/23/women-islam-debate-human-rights-watch/">If the head of Human Rights Watch argues that Western governments should support the Muslim Brotherhood</a> where it is trying to hijack the Arab Spring in Tunisia and Egypt &#8211; that does matter. It changes people&#8217;s lives.</p>
<p>It is a surreal truth to face, but the fact is that to some extent the ideas of UK far left cults have spread into senior levels of international respected human rights organisations. Take, for example, Amnesty International. According to Meredith Tax, the writer and activist, <a href="http://www.dissentmagazine.org/blog/gitagate-two-years-after">Amnesty has a larger budget than some states</a>, so what it does certainly matters. As a human rights organisation it had a duty to fight the American abuses of human rights. In a decision of catastrophic stupidity, the US state of the 1980s backed the Arab-Afghan mujahideen against the Russian invaders. The logic was that this was the Cold War, and the enemy&#8217;s enemy were our friends in the fight against godless communism. (Hey, they&#8217;re completely crazy, but at least they&#8217;re believers!) US money and equipment flowed through Pakistani intelligence services to Muslim Brotherhood organiser Abdullah Azzam, who set up an air bureau to get foreign jihadis into Peshawar training camps. Azzam had another rich friend: a young Saudi called Osama bin Laden.</p>
<p>Post 9/11, the Americans maintained their Saudi alliance, despite its incremental role in promoting jihadist propaganda. US abuses in the terror war included the systemic use of torture, and the legal and moral black hole of Guantanamo Bay. There are other, worse secret US black sites &#8211; Tax mentions Bagram, in Pakistan &#8211; but Gitmo captivated the world like a bloody comet: those kneeling figures in orange jumpsuits linger in the mind and stain the American ideal to this day. It&#8217;s hard to imagine what it would be like to be held in such a facility, but there have been numerous attempted and successful suicides, and allegations of torture, including sleep deprivation, hooding, forced positions and solitary confinement. Detainees can be held for years without a whisper of due process.</p>
<p>Amnesty&#8217;s response to all this was interesting. It partnered with an organisation called CagePrisoners, run by Birmingham-born Muslim Moazzam Begg. Begg became something of a cause celebre after he moved himself and his family to Afghanistan in July 2001. The timing was unfortunate. Six months later, Begg was arrested by the Americans, and ended up in Guantanamo via Bagram. Begg&#8217;s incarceration coincided with a growing liberal outrage about US black sites, the Iraq war and America in general. Artists and journalists mobilised against Gitmo. Michael Winterbottom made a sympathetic and well received documentary about the &#8216;Tipton Three&#8217;, a trio of Midland Muslims picked up by US intelligence on the way to a wedding in Pakistan; and Begg himself was featured in a West End play, <em>Guantanamo: Honour Bound to Defend Freedom,</em> written by the <em>Guardian</em> journalist Victoria Brittain and the novelist Gillian Slovo. Eventually, the then Labour government pressured the US to release Begg and some other detainees. President Bush, against the advice of US intelligence, agreed.</p>
<p>Back in the UK, Moazzam Begg threw himself into journalism and campaigning. He wrote for the <em>Guardian,</em> appeared on antiwar platforms and collaborated with Brittain on his autobiography, <em>Enemy Combatant,</em> in which he portrayed himself as a decent, devout family man who paid the price for being in the wrong place at the wrong time. He moved to Afghanistan partly because of &#8216;the cost of living&#8230; Many people told me that we could live in the best area of Kabul for less than £100 a month&#8217;. He felt that the Taliban &#8216;had made some modest progress &#8211; in social justice and in upholding pure, old-style Islamic values forgotten in many Islamic countries.&#8217; What was he mainly doing in Afghanistan? The general idea was to give &#8216;social value and assistance to those less fortunate than myself&#8217; and, in particular, building a school: &#8216;The plan was to expand both boys and girls schools to incorporate secondary education &#8211; and a link to the Kabul University. We collected books, funds and stationery; together with computers, classroom furniture and playground apparatus&#8230; Though the girls&#8217; school was not authorised by the strict Taliban regime, I still enrolled my own daughter at the school, and my son at the boys &#8211; though he was still too young.&#8217; As Meredith Tax says, Begg presents himself as &#8216;a good-hearted, wide-eyed innocent who bumbles his way through world-historical events without really understanding what&#8217;s going on.&#8217;</p>
<p>Tax has a whole chapter on Moazzam Begg and CagePrisoners. Reading it, you are frequently shaking your head and wondering how even Victoria Brittain could be taken in by such an obvious front story. Tax points out that back in the late nineties, Begg ran a Midlands bookshop called Maktabah al Ansaar, which disseminated salafi-jihadist propaganda, was raided three times by UK authorities, and published a book by al-Qaeda operative Dhiren Barot, now serving thirty years for conspiracy to murder. During this time he met al-Qaeda fixer Mahmoud Abu Rideh, whose war stories inspired Begg&#8217;s relocation to Afghanistan. Begg&#8217;s stated activity there &#8211; building a school for Afghan girls &#8211; is absolutely key to his defence. The girls&#8217; school gives a liberal gloss to both Begg&#8217;s account and the Taliban regime, and puts a dent in feminist criticism. Abu Rideh, interviewed by Begg, says that &#8216;We worked together to build that school&#8230; for girls in a place where the rest of the world was saying that the Taliban did not allow female education, when in fact Muslims were helping to set up schools, like yourself, for girls in Afghanistan.&#8217; All very civilised. Except that the Taliban had already closed down all the girls&#8217; schools. This particular school was set up by al-Qaeda&#8217;s treasurer to teach the children of foreign jihadis. Begg escaped the bombing of Kabul through Osama bin Laden&#8217;s Tora Bora caves, and a money order in his name was found in a Jalalabad training camp raided by the Northern Alliance in November 2001. All this, by the way, Tax gets from Begg&#8217;s memoir, interviews and tribunal statements that Begg does not dispute. She discounts his confession at Bagram which Begg says was extracted under duress.</p>
<p>No surprise then that Begg&#8217;s organisation CagePrisoners campaigned for some of the most vicious jihadi ideologues ever to walk the earth. Tax lists a rogue&#8217;s gallery that includes Abu Hamza, who turned the Finsbury Park mosque into a jihad recruitment centre; Anwar al-Awlaki, the al-Qaeda theoretician who inspired the Fort Hood massacre, the Underwear Bomber and the stabbing of a British MP; and Khalid Sheikh-Mohammed, who helped organise 9/11, the &#8217;93 bombing of the World Trade Centre, the Bali nightclub bombing and the murder of journalist Daniel Pearl.</p>
<p>Obviously, even jihadis are entitled to due process. Guantanamo should be burned to its foundations, and salt sewn into the ground. But it&#8217;s a massive deductive leap from arguing for due process, to arguing that everyone in Gitmo should be released regardless of what they have done or the evidence against them. CagePrisoners made that leap. Gita Sahgal ran Amnesty&#8217;s gender unit and was increasingly concerned about her organisation&#8217;s partnership with Begg&#8217;s crew. After going through CagePrisoner&#8217;s website, she found that &#8216;their goal was to obtain the release of such prisoners, rather than simply affording them fair trial and punishment by a properly constituted court&#8230; Supporting prisoners in this way is not simply an act of charity, but a form of religious support towards their theo-political goals.&#8217;</p>
<p>As Tax explains, human rights is based on the rule of law. Short circuit that and you don&#8217;t have a human rights organisation. Sahgal tried to get Amnesty&#8217;s management to understand this. In an internal memo she argued that:</p>
<blockquote><p>To be appearing on platforms with Britain&#8217;s most famous supporter of the Taliban, whom we treat as a human rights defender, is a gross error of judgment….fatally blurring the distinction between defending the rights of the individual and creating a narrative of innocence to suit our campaigning. This is a very old problem but it has currently reached its apotheosis in the decision to take Begg to Downing Street and to tour with him across Europe.</p></blockquote>
<p>When that memo got no results, Sahgal went public with an interview for the <em>Sunday Times</em>. Three hours after that interview appeared, she was suspended.</p>
<p>CagePrisoners is an old tale but it is indicative of wider problems. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Great_Game">Great Game</a> was a term for the swashbuckling imperial rivalry between Britain and Russia for Central Asian rule. It continued well into the Cold War with players like Kissinger and Nixon making alliances and manipulating peoples like Haig with his toy soldiers. Now the left has discovered its own version of the Game &#8211; where all that matters is strategic partnerships and the language of resistance, and secularism, liberty and the rule of law are discarded as bourgeois frivolities. The results for people who actually are fighting for freedom, particularly dissidents in Islamic countries, are disastrous. The antiwar left doesn&#8217;t support the rights of women: indeed, we know that the SWP, the driving force behind the antiwar movement, <a href="http://maxdunbar.wordpress.com/2013/01/25/nice-guys-of-the-swp/">does not even support the rights of female activists in its own organisation</a>. Forget the anti-imperialist rubric. Feminism is key to everything. It&#8217;s the only recent radicalism that has worked and has to be supported if the suffering in the Arab world will ever end. To paraphrase Orwell, hope lies with women.</p>
<p>With this in mind Sahgal and Tax have set up the <a href="http://www.centreforsecularspace.org/?q=content/about-us">Centre for Secular Space</a> which aims to promote universal rights without concessions to misogyny, fundamentalism and lies. Meredith Tax&#8217;s book, <em>Double Bind</em>, <a href="http://www.centreforsecularspace.org/?q=news/get-our-new-book-double-bind-muslim-right-anglo-american-left-and-universal-human-rights-meredi">can be ordered from there</a>, and it&#8217;s essential if you want to understand the nasty little hole the left has dug itself into. I should also say that the CSS is a new organisation, it doesn&#8217;t have Amnesty&#8217;s huge corporate budget, and it badly needs donations.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/maxdunbar.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="349" /></p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://maxdunbar.wordpress.com/">Max Dunbar</a> was born in London in 1981. He recently finished a full-length novel and his short fiction has appeared in various print and web journals. He is reviews editor of <em>3:AM</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-players-of-games/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Missing Links</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-275/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-275/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 14:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Andrew Gallix</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Buzzwords]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56297</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Picabia&#8216;s legendary 391 magazine. * William Gass, 1977: &#8220;I write because I hate. A lot. Hard&#8221;. * Donald Barthelme&#8216;s syllabus. * The inscrutable brilliance of Anne Carson. * Lacan&#8217;s Joyce. * &#8220;So, no-one really reads this or knows me here, or cares about it if they do know me or not, so what am I [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/missinglinks.jpg" alt="" title="missinglinks" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56443" /></p>
<p><a href= "http://www.ubu.com/historical/391/index.html">Picabia</a>&#8216;s legendary <em><strong>391</strong></em> magazine. * <a href= "http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/3576/the-art-of-fiction-no-65-william-gass">William Gass</a>, 1977: <em>&#8220;I write because I hate. A lot. Hard&#8221;</em>. * <a href= "http://www.openculture.com/2013/03/donald_barthelmes_syllabus_highlights_81_books_essential_for_a_literary_education_.html">Donald Barthelme</a>&#8216;s syllabus. * The inscrutable brilliance of <a href= "http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/17/magazine/the-inscrutable-brilliance-of-anne-carson.html?pagewanted=all&#038;_r=0">Anne Carson</a>. * <a href= "http://www.berfrois.com/2013/03/lacans-joyce-the-real-imaginary/">Lacan&#8217;s Joyce</a>. * <em>&#8220;So, no-one really reads this or knows me here, or cares about it if they do know me or not, so what am I doing <a href= "http://timeimmemorial.tumblr.com/">pushing these pieces of nothing into nowhere</a>, for what, for myself?&#8221;</em> * <a href= "http://www.thewhitereview.org/interviews/interview-with-amit-chaudhuri/">Amit Chaudhuri</a> interviewed. * <a href= "http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bkvqrta5mnw">Gilles Deleuze</a> ABC. * Forty hours of <a href="http://www.ubu.com/sound/barthes.html">Roland Barthes</a> lectures, 1977-78, including his lectures on &#8220;<strong>The Neutral</strong>&#8220;. * <a href= "http://www.daytodaydata.com/georgesperec.html">Georges Perec</a> on the <strong>infra-ordinary</strong>. * <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2013/mar/14/mod-very-british-style-review">We are the Modernists</a>: <em>&#8220;[W]hat could possibly link 1980s suburban oiks in Fred Perry shirts to sharply dressed 1960s existentialists? This book, written by an academic, attempts an answer, contending that Mod was not only &#8216;the first distinctively British youth culture&#8217; but &#8216;a popular form of modernism — that stream of creativity in Europe and America that began in the early 20th century as an avant garde reaction to mainstream aesthetics, morality and politics&#8217;&#8221;</em>. * <a href="http://www.newscientist.com/special/self">The great illusion of the self</a>. * <a href= "http://www.cbc.ca/writersandcompany/episode/2013/02/03/karl-ove-knausgaard-interview/">Knausgaard</a> interview. * <a href= "http://monoskop.org/log/?p=7652">Walter Benjamin</a>&#8216;s juvenilia. * <a href= "http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1483">A history of neon</a>: <em>&#8220;What, in the end, makes advertisements so superior to criticism? Not what the moving red neon sign says — but the fiery pool reflecting it in the asphalt&#8221;</em> (<strong>Walter Benjamin</strong>). * <a href= "http://www.openculture.com/2012/06/andrei_tarkovskys_very_first_films_three_student_films_1956-1960.html">Andrei Tarkovsky</a>&#8216;s juvenilia. * <a href= "http://www.nypost.com/p/entertainment/richard_hell_my_new_york_Q4aIRRnjrkpGTeBx4n4FKI">Richard Hell</a>&#8216;s New York. His autobiography is reviewed <a href="http://www.vol1brooklyn.com/2013/03/14/poetry-and-punks-on-the-bowery-richard-hells-i-dreamed-i-was-a-very-clean-tramp-reviewed/">here</a>. * <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KFgyezfS6ik"><em>NY 77: The Coolest Year in Hell</a></em>. * An interview with <a href="http://louderthanwar.com/glen-matlock-interview-legendary-ex-pistol-speaks-to-ltw/">Glen Matlock</a>. * <a href="http://www.paulgormanis.com/?p=7953">Nick Kent</a>: best-dressed man in town? * <a href="http://www.berfrois.com/2013/03/a-litter-from-vladimir-dixon/">&#8216;A litter from Vladimir Dixon to Gem&#8217;s Choice&#8217;</a>. * <a href="http://www.unthankbooks.com/node/52">David Rose</a>&#8216;s introduction to <em>The Syllabus of Errors</em>. * <a href= "http://www.irishtimes.com/culture/art-and-design/visual-art/writers-blocks-the-book-i-am-working-on-has-much-of-the-punctuation-rinsed-out-of-it-1.1320232">Writers&#8217; blocks</a>. * Has the world finally caught up with <a href="http://www.vulture.com/2013/03/sam-lipsyte-fun-parts.html">Sam Lipsyte</a>? * How a mordant jokester with a madman’s imagination became a <a href= "http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/12/books/the-fun-parts-stories-by-sam-lipsyte.html?_r=0">literary rock star</a>. * <a href= "http://therumpus.net/2013/03/the-rumpus-interview-with-david-shields-2/">David Shields</a> interviewed in <em>The Rumpus</em>. * On <a href="http://www.culture.pl/web/english/literature-full-page/-/eo_event_asset_publisher/iCU6/content/kronos-gombrowicz-s-unknown-journal#.UTWrQCnH2Ss.twitter">Gombrowicz</a>&#8216;s <em>Kronos</em>. * <a href= "http://www.theparisreview.org/interviews/79/the-art-of-fiction-no-180-andrea-barrett">Andrea Barrett</a>: <em>&#8220;We all feel unhoused in some sense. That’s part of why we write&#8221;</em>. * <a href= "http://www.openculture.com/2013/03/the_confessions_of_robert_crumb.html">The confessions of Robert Crumb</a>. * A review of <strong>Ray Brassier</strong>&#8216;s <a href= "http://metapsychology.mentalhelp.net/poc/view_doc.php?type=book&#038;id=6817&#038;cn=394"><em>Nihil Unbound</em></a>. * <a href= "http://observatory.designobserver.com/rickpoynor/feature/on-my-shelf-fin-de-copenhague/37720/">Guy Debord and Asger Jorn</a>&#8216;s <em>Fin de Copenhague</em>. * <a href= "http://ubumexico.centro.org.mx/sound/celine_l-f/Celine-LF_03-Regelment-Chanson-par--L.-F.-Celine.mp3">Louis-Ferdinand Céline</a> sings! * <a href="http://spitalfieldslife.com/2013/03/10/tony-bock-on-the-railway/?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=email&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+SpitalfieldsLife+%28Spitalfields+Life%293<1070s">1970s railway stations</a>. * <strong>Peter Cook</strong>&#8216;s <a href= "http://darkestlondon.com/2013/03/11/peter-cooks-the-establishment-club/">The Establishment Club</a>. * <a href= "http://williamgaddis.org/recognitions/inconnue/index.shtml">Influence and authenticity of l&#8217;Inconnue de la Seine</a>. * <a href= "http://www.slate.com/articles/arts/books/2013/03/len_deighton_s_bomber_the_first_book_ever_written_on_a_word_processor.single.html">The first novel ever written on a word processor</a>. * <a href= "http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/books/2013/02/in-praise-of-concision.html">In praise of concision</a>. * <a href= "http://thequietus.com/articles/11650-rudimentary-peni-reissues">Rudimentary Peni</a> album reissues. * <a href= "http://www.thewhitereview.org/interviews/interview-with-ivan-vladislavic/">Ivan Vladislavic</a> interviewed in <em>The White Review</em>. * <a href= "http://www.openbookontario.com/news/%E2%80%9Cwhat_reading_has_become%E2%80%9D_derek_beaulieu%E2%80%99s_upcoming_exhibition_how_read_st_catharines">Derek Beaulieu</a> on his upcoming <em><strong>How to Read</strong></em> exhibition. * <a href= "http://thenewinquiry.com/essays/turtles-from-the-shells/">Douglas Rushkoff</a> on &#8220;present shock&#8221;. * <strong>Jake Burns</strong> of <a href= "http://www.unthankbooks.com/node/52">Stiff Little Fingers</a> interviewed. * Two poems by <a href= "http://www.berfrois.com/2013/03/two-poems-nicholas-rombes/">Nicholas Rombes</a>. * <a href="http://htmlgiant.com/reviews/the-revolution-is-never-televised-robbe-grillets-project-for-a-revolution-in-new-york/">Alain Robbe-Grillet</a>&#8216;s <em><strong>Project for a Revolution in New York</strong></em>. * <a href= "http://www.standpointmag.co.uk/node/4893/full">Hitler&#8217;s Superman</a>. * <a href= "http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/lsereviewofbooks/2013/03/04/book-review-hitlers-philosophers-sherrat/">Hitler&#8217;s philosophers</a>. * Great picture of <a href= "https://twitter.com/viv_albertine/status/311408398950338560/photo/1">Viv Albertine</a>, New York, 1981. * <a href="http://cross-my-tea.tumblr.com/post/45334665295">Orange Juice</a>, 1981. * <a href= "http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1482">Nabokov</a> and the theatre of history. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-275/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
<enclosure url="http://ubumexico.centro.org.mx/sound/celine_l-f/Celine-LF_03-Regelment-Chanson-par--L.-F.-Celine.mp3" length="5378161" type="audio/mpeg" />
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Last of London</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-last-of-london/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-last-of-london/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>3AM</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Criticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56401</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/lpb-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="lpb" width="420" height="179" class="aligncenter size-thumbnail wp-image-56408" />

<em>London: From Punk to Blair</em> isn’t a love letter to London, in the way that some collections of essays develop an authorial group-think as the writers fall in love with their shared subject.  Both the tone and the content are brilliantly heterodox. There are some well-known names amid the collection – Rushdie, Hanif Kureshi, the always brilliant Patrick Keiller – as well as newer writers and experts on particular subjects.  Instead of trying to capture London in a book, Kerr and Gibson have gathered a group of people with interesting perspective and stories to tell. They reflect London’s glories, and its gross inequalities, its gleaming shards and its seedy underbelly.<p>
<b>John P. Houghton</b> reviews the revised edition of <em>London: From Punk to Blair</em>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By John P. Houghton.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/lpb-191x300.jpg" alt="" title="lpb" width="191" height="300" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-56408" /></p>
<p><em><a href="http://www.bookdepository.co.uk/London-Joe-Kerr/9781780230498/?a_aid=3ammagazine">London: From Punk to Blair</a></em>, 2nd edition, eds. Joe Kerr and Andrew Gibson, Reaktion, 2013</p>
<p>The ratio of pigeons to people in London is 1:1. London pigeons, like their human counterparts, are often accused by pigeons from elsewhere in the country of thinking the world begins and ends in the capital. The London pigeons don’t care. They know the other pigeons are really just jealous.</p>
<p>There are no chapters written by an actual pigeon in the collection of 34 essays that make up <em>London: From Punk to Blair</em>, but there is a chapter on &#8216;Rats with wings: London’s battles with animals&#8217;. This reminds us of how many different creatures also share London with us, most of which we have simply stopped noticing.</p>
<p>This connects with a theme running through the book: how London as a physical and psychological place is conceived and contested. How its actual and mental space is taken away from some people, by the forces of the market or social trends, and taken by others.</p>
<p>Joe Kerr’s introduction warns that “as the relentless cleansing of the capital continues apace, it is becoming increasingly difficult to imagine where… its poorer populations will settle”. And that was the introduction to the first edition, published in 2003, when the bedroom tax was just a dumb and cruel idea and instead of a dumb and cruel policy.</p>
<p>Salman Rushdie writes with fury about the death of families, often immigrant and from ethnic minorities, living in modern slum housing. The piece was written in 1991; until I saw that note at the end, I assumed he was discussing a very recent case.</p>
<p>These issues are still with us today because London often seems incapable of dealing with fundamental challenges. Several of the contributions highlight the ways in which London has failed to get a grip on its creaking infrastructure. Joe Kerr’s chapter &#8216;Blowdown&#8217; describes the rise and fall of <a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/municipal-chic-an-interview-with-lynsey-hanley/">London’s tower blocks</a>; once seen as the solution to the infinite housing crisis, now seen as monuments to municipal folly. </p>
<p>Space in London is divided up in other ways. Jenny Bavidge and Andrew Gibson describe how the capital’s children are “more and more restricted as their place to play gets smaller”. Niran Abbas reminds us that our space is invaded, without us knowing most of the time, about 300 times per day by the city’s 150,000 CCTV cameras. London’s gay community has more space open to it, as old prejudices die out, but as Mark W. Turner points out, much of that space is intensely commercialised and reflect some narrow and “very specific virtues: youth, maleness and whiteness”.</p>
<p><em>London: From Punk to Blair</em> isn’t a love letter to London, in the way that some collections of essays develop an authorial group-think as the writers fall in love with their shared subject.  Both the tone and the content are brilliantly heterodox. There are some well-known names amid the collection – Rushdie, Hanif Kureshi, the always brilliant <a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-future-of-landscape-patrick-keiller/">Patrick Keiller</a> (and <a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-future-of-landscape-patrick-wright/">Patrick Wright</a>) &#8212; as well as newer writers and experts on particular subjects (<a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/dark-entries/">Nicholas Royle</a>, <a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/interpretation-as-a-fine-art/">Tom McCarthy</a>). </p>
<p>Instead of trying to capture London in a book, Kerr and Gibson have gathered a group of people with interesting perspective and stories to tell. They reflect London’s glories, and its gross inequalities, its gleaming shards and its <a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/punterland/">seedy underbelly</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve read some rotten books about London so I was a bit nervous approaching <em>London: From Punk to Blair</em>. I couldn’t have been more wrong. It’s a great collection of writing. </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/jh.jpg" alt="jh" title="jh" width="101" height="162" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-10865" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://www.metropolitanlines.co.uk/">John P. Houghton</a> is a writer and adviser on neighbourhoods, cities and social exclusion and is the author with Prof. Anne Power of <em><a href="http://www.bookdepository.co.uk/book/9781861346582/Jigsaw-Cities/?aid_3ammagazine">Jigsaw Cities</a></em>. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-last-of-london/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The North African Unit</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-north-african-unit/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-north-african-unit/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 16:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>David Winters</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Fiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56415</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NorthAfricaLandscape.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="179" />

Schneid is the theorist of our movement. He is interested in typology and time. When new thought blossoms he exterminates the thinkers. He sends us all across north Africa to do this. There are other units, in other continents. He speaks of Black Easter and cosmic dread and speculative annihilation. He sends us white papers on the psychological archaeology of repulsion. His favorite weapon is a flare gun, used up close and in the face. There is no other way to say this.

By <b>Nicholas Rombes</b>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Nicholas Rombes.</p>
<p><img class="size-full wp-image-56416 alignnone" src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NorthAfricaLandscape.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="421" /></p>
<p>My temporary apartment. The sand. The blue water. Agadir.</p>
<p>Bugged and over-bugged so many times that I can practically hear myself through Schneid’s ears. Best not to talk. Best not to think. Retrieve the loaded handgun stashed between the mattresses. Go to the cafe on the corner where the Marxist students used to congregate, before I wrote poems that identified them by name, that gave them over to their tortured futures. Their dialectical futures. Their electroshock futures. In the hot sun at Aitswal Beach there are three men waiting for me, each one dedicated to murder in his own way.</p>
<p>A warpath of words, my poems. Poems giving shape and substance to ideas that out-revolutionize the revolution itself. The bartender’s face is scarred. Africa is no longer the same. The signals are weaker. The patient is dying. I remove the folder and place it in front of me. The bar door is propped open with a broken cinder block and there is a warm breeze coming in and I use my glass of illegal beer to hold the papers still. A young woman with pink palms appears and takes a place at the bar next to me. The African sandflies described in the <em>Bulletin of Entomological Research</em> in 1938 have returned.</p>
<p>The enjambment of just one line could make the difference between a prolonged death and a short one. The television above the bar seems to switch channels on its own. The bartender is cutting lemons right before our eyes. The code Schneid gave me implicates him. I don’t know if Schneid knows this. That he has asked me to break a code that, once broken and revealed, condemns him to death. The bartender removes the quartered lemons and wipes the counter. There is a phone ringing from the black depths of the back of the bar. I have never shaken fully the soft sand from this part of the Sahara. It falls from my hair like thunder. The West hears it now, too late.</p>
<p>The insurgents or whatever they are called at any given time have developed a code that the weaker among us believe unbreakable. It travels across the lines in the old analog way and to decipher it means re-harvesting equipment discarded long ago as useless. According to Schneid I am the poet of the counter-revolution. I have been sent to Chad, to Garoua. My memory sloshes from one side of my head to the other. From Garoua I am driven through impossible sand north to Mokolo. Then further north, for weeks, deeper into shallow blinding light. There is dissent in the caravan. There is a fight over the safest route. A sparkplug is stolen during the night and we languish for days.</p>
<p>Schneid is the theorist of our movement. He is interested in typology and time. When new thought blossoms he exterminates the thinkers. He sends us all across north Africa to do this. There are other units, in other continents. He speaks of Black Easter and cosmic dread and speculative annihilation. He sends us white papers on the psychological archaeology of repulsion. His favorite weapon is a flare gun, used up close and in the face. There is no other way to say this.</p>
<p>I arrive, at last, back at the café. I can hear the ocean waves in the distance. There is an American show from the 1990s on the television, <em>Wild Palms.</em> For the usual reasons we pretend not to watch it. The three men from Aitswal are there, too, sitting in the back in plastic chairs. They are wearing loose white shirts. One of them is smoking. These are likely the new men that Schneid has sent. They are semioticians, and I am just a poet. I can see their axes beneath the table. Now the one who exterminated the Marxists must be exterminated himself. I understand this.</p>
<p>Somewhere in Europe Schneid practices with his flare gun on one of the students I’ve named in my poems. Right before my eyes, the bartender makes an alien symbol with his hands and one of the men from back comes over and sits beside me. There is sand blowing in through the open door and collecting in the corners of the café. <em>Wild Palms </em>still plays on the television. Two men walk across the screen in the bright sun beside a blue pool. One of them wears a white track suit. A voice off screen—a woman’s voice—says, “Love among consenting holograms?” What will become of the North African Unit without me, without my words?</p>
<p>And then the other two men from the back approach me, one of them holding an axe. And what happens next, there is no poetry to convey the tenderness by which they seize me, laying their hands upon me, the animal they have been given to destroy.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Rombes3AMpic.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="231" /></p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<strong><a href="http://twitter.com/Requiem102">Nicholas Rombes</a></strong> writes for <em>The Rumpus</em>, <em>The Oxford American</em>, and <em>Filmmaker Magazine</em>, where he serves as a contributing editor and writes the <a href="http://www.filmmakermagazine.com/news/tag/blue-velvet-project/" target="_blank">Blue Velvet Project</a>. His work has appeared in <em>The Believer</em>, <em>Wigleaf</em>, <em>Exquisite Corpse</em>, and other places. He teaches in Detroit, Michigan, and can be found <a href="http://thehappinessengine.net/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-north-african-unit/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Forms of Divination</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/forms-of-divination/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/forms-of-divination/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 22:04:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>steven fowler</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Poetry]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=53597</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/Author-Photo-389x179.jpg" alt="" width="389" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-53598" />

Don’t pick me up I’ll be okay leave me down here 
with your broken keyboard 
never tell them what we did in the attic and throw 
my impossible gadgets away from the playground 
long story short I don’t believe 
this is breakfast

By <b>Bobby Parker</b>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Bobby Parker.</p>
<p><strong>Fake Blood</strong></p>
<p>My crush can walk through walls and finger<br />
books on my shelf leaving slime that smells<br />
like galloping perfume rollercoasters<br />
I sleep with her face </p>
<p> <strong>Doppelganger</strong></p>
<p>We couldn’t sing it was so loud up<br />
there everybody has a brass instrument<br />
&amp; my see-through grandfather couldn’t open the door<br />
he was shouting other stuff</p>
<p><strong>The Picture I See But Never Saw</strong> </p>
<p>If you hold it up<br />
this way you will see God smoking blue and yellow<br />
if you turn it the other way you will see<br />
Satan bending red and black<br />
my mother can’t find it at the moment<br />
but I swear my family can’t eat a thing<br />
they take turns sitting down</p>
<p><strong>Saturday Morning Cartoons</strong> </p>
<p>He knocks my parents’ door<br />
I make him wait until The End before I let him in<br />
I don’t tell him what happened he likes the ones<br />
that arrange themselves around us like council estates<br />
laughing eye holes on the floor </p>
<p><strong>Clocks that Fall Off</strong></p>
<p>Don’t pick me up I’ll be okay leave me down here<br />
with your broken keyboard<br />
never tell them what we did in the attic and throw<br />
my impossible gadgets away from the playground<br />
long story short I don’t believe<br />
this is breakfast</p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong></p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/Author-Photo.jpg" alt="" width="389" height="336" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-53598" /></p>
<p><strong>Bobby Parker</strong> was born in 1982 and lives in Kidderminster, England. Publications include the critically acclaimed experimental books <em>Ghost Town Music</em> and <em>Comberton</em>, both published by The Knives Forks &amp; Spoons Press, with a pamphlet of selected poems due to be published by Holdfire Press later in the year or early 2013. He is currently working on his first novel and a book for children. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/forms-of-divination/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Making the Bed</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/making-the-bed/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/making-the-bed/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 09:05:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Flash Fiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56373</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NathanLoceff-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="NathanLoceff" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56374" /></p>

“For some reason I’ve started making the bed.” Luc said stroking the little, grey bristles poking out from his cheeks.
“I don’t know what it is. I’ve never made the bed before. I always thought it was a waste of time, and then suddenly, I can’t stand to see my bed unmade.”
“What are you talking about?” asked Marcel before taking the final sip of his coffee.
“Making the bed in morning. I never used to do it. Now I can’t help myself.”
“So what?” said Marcel rubbing his hands on his cream coloured corduroys.
“So nothing, I just thought it was interesting. When Marigelle was alive she couldn’t stand to see the bed unmade and I never did it. Not once in all the years we lived together.”
They both chuckled.

By <strong>Nathan Loceff</strong>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Nathan Loceff.</p>
<p>“For some reason I’ve started making the bed.” Luc said stroking the little, grey bristles poking out from his cheeks.  </p>
<p>“I don’t know what it is. I’ve never made the bed before. I always thought it was a waste of time, and then suddenly, I can’t stand to see my bed unmade.”</p>
<p>“What are you talking about?” asked Marcel before taking the final sip of his coffee.</p>
<p>“Making the bed in morning. I never used to do it. Now I can’t help myself.” </p>
<p>“So what?” said Marcel rubbing his hands on his cream coloured corduroys.</p>
<p>“So nothing, I just thought it was interesting. When Marigelle was alive she couldn’t stand to see the bed unmade and I never did it. Not once in all the years we lived together.”  </p>
<p>They both chuckled. </p>
<p>“Two more coffees,” Luc called across the counter to the woman who was standing in front of them. </p>
<p>“Thanks,” he said when she put two cups of coffee down in front of them.</p>
<p>“You never made the bed even though you knew your wife hated it?” was her response.</p>
<p>“Bahhh,” he started to say but she cut him short, “Not even on her birthday?”</p>
<p>Marcel pulled a little at the pockets of his corduroys and looked down.</p>
<p>Luc blushed ever so slightly, but said, “Why would I do it on her birthday? If I did that she would have realised that I knew how much she cared about it.” </p>
<p>The woman gave him a look that said more than she could have written in a hundred page treatise. </p>
<p>“Boy, you’re really a jerk,” said Marcel as the woman walked away to serve someone else. </p>
<p>“Bahhh, the uhhhh,” he started to say and then thought better of it and picked up his coffee and took a sip. </p>
<p>“Hey guys,” said Jean, coming up between the two friends. He shook hands with both men and wished them both a Merry Christmas. </p>
<p>“A coffee, please.” he said in the direction of the woman behind the counter.</p>
<p>When she put it down in front of him he said, “Merry Christmas.”</p>
<p>“Is it Christmas?” she said looking blankly at him. </p>
<p>“Of course it’s Christmas.” </p>
<p>“Christmas is just for the kids,” said someone standing near them at the bar.</p>
<p>“If it’s Christmas, how come I’m working and all you guys are standing around drinking coffee?” the woman behind the bar asked. </p>
<p>Looking down, the three men all took sips in silence. </p>
<p>Then, after a few moments passed Luc inclined his head toward the window and said, “Look at that.”</p>
<p>Outside snow had begun to fall. The three men watched, drinking their coffee. When they had finished they paid and walked out into the cold. All three wore caps and had scarves wrapped around their necks. As they walked the snow collected on their shoulders and caps and on the streets around them. </p>
<p>As soon as Marcel had said goodbye and turned a corner Luc put his hand on Jean’s arm and said, “I started making the bed,” with a light in his eyes. </p>
<p>“So what?” Jean laughed.</p>
<p>“So nothing.” </p>
<p>“I never make the bed. What’s the point?” </p>
<p>“That’s what you think.” Luc responded.</p>
<p>They walked on in silence for a moment.</p>
<p>“God, I love the snow, I’ve always loved the snow. Marigelle and I used to take long walks on snowy nights. Watching the snow fall past the street lamps was one of her favourite things.” </p>
<p>“Colette liked that too.” said Jean with a sigh.</p>
<p>Luc walked up the little staircase to his apartment. He turned the key in the lock and went in. He took off his big coat, knocked the snow off and hung it by the door. He took off his cap and hung it over his coat. He took off his shoes, put on his slippers and walked into his bedroom. He looked at the bed. It was perfect. Not a thread was out of place.  </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NathanLoceff.jpg" alt="" title="NathanLoceff" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56374" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
Born in Santa Rosa, California, <a href="mailto:nathan.loceff@fulbrightmail.org">Nathan Loceff</a> is a writer who has, as of late, been waking up in Paris, France.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/making-the-bed/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The language of disaster</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-language-of-disaster/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-language-of-disaster/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 07:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Criticism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56309</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/iraqichristpreview.jpg" alt="" title="iraqichristpreview" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56357" /></p>

The language of disaster is fragmentation. Violence fractures everything. The living legacy of dictatorship and war is present in every word of every line. A senseless, sprawling chaos of religious terror, Ba’ath repression and collateral damage forms an unnerving background to the collection, like a sports commentary delivered by a jabbering maniac. Blasim’s Iraq is a place where you can go out for milk and cigarettes and get blown up by a car bomb. The title story, narrated from the afterlife, is about an Iraqi conscript forced into becoming a suicide bomber. Another story, ‘The Song of the Goats,’ explores an inter-family conflict between two brothers, one an embittered and emasculated Iran/Iraq war veteran, the other working for Saddam’s secret police. Blasim says that ‘I have nine siblings, and all my family in Iraq went off to do different things. I left to be a writer, one of my brothers went to study religion, and one joined the police. And all of us, we have different opinions about families and about life.’ The truth is <em>never</em> simple. It’s as Rumi says, so often we believe we see the whole world, when in fact we are holding just a fragment of a shattered mirror.

<strong>Max Dunbar</strong> reviews <strong>Hassan Blasim</strong >'s <em>The Iraqi Christ</em>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Max Dunbar.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/iraqichrist.jpg" alt="" title="iraqichrist" width="277" height="425" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56356" /></p>
<p><em><a href="http://www.bookdepository.co.uk/Iraqi-Christ-Hassan-Blasim/9781905583522/?a_aid=3ammagazine">The Iraqi Christ</a></em>, Hassan Blasim, <a href="http://www.commapress.co.uk/?section=books&#038;page=TheIraqiChrist">Comma Press</a> 2013</p>
<p>At one point in Hassan Blasim’s startling new collection, the author is asked a question that writers of the short form hear over and over again: ‘Why don’t you write a novel, instead of talking about all these characters – Arabs, Kurds, Pakistanis, Sudanese, Bangladeshis and Africans? They would make for mysterious, traditional stories. Why do you cram all these names into one short story? Let the truth come to light in all its simplicity.’</p>
<p>In the interviews I subsequently read, the Iraqi writer tries again and again to face down the conundrum. <a href="http://blogs.chi.ac.uk/shortstoryforum/an-interview-with-hassan-blasim/">To <em>Thresholds</em> magazine he said</a>: ‘In a novel, you have to talk about everything, you have to know about everything. But a short story is like me – I don’t know anything about life.’ <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/2013/02/iraqi-author-hassan-blasim-we-need-express-disaster-our-lives">He told the <em>New Statesman</em> that</a> ‘we need to express the disaster of our lives in the Arab world in a language that is bold, up to date and not afraid’. Blasim also regrets ‘the tedious and nauseating refrain about the beauty and sanctity of the Arabic language because it is the language of the Quran and of the great tradition of Arabic poetry.’ Instead he writes in a terse, unsettling but nevertheless lyrical style. There is the same queer mixture of clarity and disalignment you feel while reading Kafka’s short stories. It is the terrible clarity that comes with fear, where every particle of the street seems fresh and crisp, and it seems like these are your last impressions of the world.</p>
<p>The language of disaster is fragmentation. Violence fractures everything. The living legacy of dictatorship and war is present in every word of every line. A senseless, sprawling chaos of religious terror, Ba’ath repression and collateral damage forms an unnerving background to the collection, like a sports commentary delivered by a jabbering maniac. Blasim’s Iraq is a place where you can go out for milk and cigarettes and get blown up by a car bomb. The title story, narrated from the afterlife, is about an Iraqi conscript forced into becoming a suicide bomber. Another story, ‘The Song of the Goats,’ explores an inter-family conflict between two brothers, one an embittered and emasculated Iran/Iraq war veteran, the other working for Saddam’s secret police. Blasim says that ‘I have nine siblings, and all my family in Iraq went off to do different things. I left to be a writer, one of my brothers went to study religion, and one joined the police. And all of us, we have different opinions about families and about life.’ The truth is <em>never</em> simple. It’s as Rumi says, so often we believe we see the whole world, when in fact we are holding just a fragment of a shattered mirror.</p>
<p>Blasim offers a new take on an oral culture. ‘The Song of the Goats’ features a competition where Iraqis clamour to give the most harrowing take on the war, and ‘Sarsara’s Tree,’ is about a corrupt NGO official who spins emotive stories of starving Africans to finance unnecessary projects, only to find himself caught up in genuine and frightening village lore. But Blasim is at his best when he’s surreal. On the occasions a terrorist attack hits the UK, bystanders say, ‘It’s like something out of a film,’ and I used to think that was a reflection of Western ignorance, our protected postmodern consumerist lives, but maybe it’s the same for people who actually have to live in war zones, and the unreality just gets deeper and more intense, until it seems to cover everything. The author tells us: ‘Violence in the city is like a nightmare. It’s real and not real&#8230; And it’s like dreaming too.’ In ‘The Hole,’ Blasim’s most affecting piece, a shoplifter is chased out of a supermarket by random gunmen, and falls into a twisting warren. Already down the hole are an old man and a dead Russian soldier. They chat and banter, and the narrator quickly makes peace with his new home. Then, a woman falls into the hole. ‘A blood analysis robot was chasing me,’ she says.</p>
<p>This spring is the Iraq war’s tenth anniversary. In British newspapers and blogs <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/what-a-tragedy-that-we-couldnt-stop-the-war-in-iraq-despite-marching-in-our-thousands-8488812.html">we have had a barrage of sanctimonious commemorations</a>, and <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/sam-parker/iraq-robbed-a-generation-of-their-faith-in-politics_b_2628416.html">Adrian Mole style demo nostalgia pieces</a> for the <a href="http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/alex-massie/2013/02/the-iraq-wars-real-victims-laurie-penny-and-the-narcissistic-left/">Grand March of 2003</a>. I was on that protest too, and it’s striking that so many people’s politics, at least on Iraq, haven’t moved an inch in ten years. Young writers including Owen Jones and Laurie Penny write about the march as if it were the defining event of a generation, but say little or nothing about the experiences of other young people of that generation – the average age on Telic operations was twenty-one – who actually went out there and fought to get a fascist dictatorship out of power. Still more disturbing is the absence of Iraqi voices from the debate. If free thinking Arab writers are rarely seen on leftwing platforms, the least we can do is read their fiction. And Blasim’s short stories are a great contribution to the literature of this troubled, bloodsoaked country.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/maxdunbar.jpg" alt="" title="maxdunbar" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-49468" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://maxdunbar.wordpress.com/">Max Dunbar</a> was born in London in 1981. He recently finished a full-length novel and his short fiction has appeared in various print and web journals. He is reviews editor of <em>3:AM</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-language-of-disaster/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>No New York: A Jade Anniversary</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/no-new-york-a-jade-anniversary/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/no-new-york-a-jade-anniversary/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 21:13:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Andrew Gallix</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56220</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NoNewYork35LKYGB-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="NoNewYork35LKYGB" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56333" /></p>

The ones that claim total recall, well, suffice it to say they’re lying. They have to be. For No Wave was the one, true Blank Generation. Yes. It took Aristotle’s <em>tabula rasa</em>, and with one flailing swipe per Attali, all the rest was noise. Noise being code for negation — a deliberate dithering of all things affirmative — No Wave is then best described not by what it was, but instead by what it wasn’t: no shirt, no shoes, no problem. No fucking future. None at all.

<strong>Logan K. Young</strong> on <em>No New York</em>.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NoNewYork35LKYGB.jpg" alt="" title="NoNewYork35LKYGB" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56333" /></p>
<p>By Logan K. Young.</p>
<p><em>&#8220;(You mean you don’t own a copy? What are you, sick or something?)&#8221;</em><br />
- Lester Bangs, &#8220;<a href= "http://music.iupui.edu/faculty/albright/BangsReview1.html">A Reasonable Guide to Horrible Noise</a>&#8221;</p>
<p>May 5-6, 1978. For once, it really did happen so fast. All of it. Rather literally, too. Blink, bat an eye or go take a piss, and you probably missed it. (Those things worth remembering, anyways.) What a bummer. Indeed. If you weren’t there, then you just don’t know. Alas, such is life; you have to seize it while ye may. But even if you were around (and you truly were doing it right) you still don’t remember. (Or at least you shouldn’t.) The ones that claim total recall, well, suffice it to say they’re lying. They have to be. For No Wave was the one, true Blank Generation. Yes. It took Aristotle’s <em>tabula rasa</em>, and with one flailing swipe per Attali, all the rest was noise. Noise being code for negation — a deliberate dithering of all things affirmative — No Wave is then best described not by what it was, but instead by what it wasn’t: no shirt, no shoes, no problem. No fucking future. None at all.</p>
<p>But what’s really in a name? No, seriously? It’s a simple enough inquisition. The line is straight, ‘tis the answer what’s crooked. Ensconced in the void plied by these otherwise nameless, at-risk kids, that inquiry becomes a near tautology. Is the thing now the name? Dunno. Is its name just a thing now? Ibid. So, like Beckett’s <em>L&#8217;innommable</em>, perhaps anything longform on <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_New_York"><em>No New York</em></a> is primordially flawed. We shan’t go on; we shall go on. On y va! After all, there’s music, movies and mores left to kill. Still. Janie, get your gun.</p>
<p>To be fair, such existential quandaries didn’t matter to a group like <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_(band)">Mars</a>. Meanwhile, a band such as <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_(band)">D.N.A.</a> couldn’t be bothered. Likewise, not a single epistemological shit was given by <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teenage_Jesus_and_the_Jerks">Teenage Jesus &#038; the Jerks</a>. And <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Chance_and_the_Contortions">The Contortions</a>, umm, they were just too cool. Sorry. Basically, they were all looking only for a light. But what we’ve come to call ‘No Wave’ wasn’t anyone’s beacon. That’s for damn sure. A raging burnout in a left-for-dead New York City, nah, it was not built to last the night. Everything about it (the look, the feel, the lifestyle&#8230;the savagery) was ephemeral. On purpose, no less. </p>
<p>In fact, No Wave wasn’t made to last at all. It was but a flash in the mire, a non-movement of mass transience — Dada gone nihilistic. (Nada?) With certifiable crazies like Sumner Crane, Arto Lindsay, Lydia Lunch and James Chance at the helm, how could it be anything else? It couldn’t. Their time was borrowed at such an unhealthy interest rate, it made the most sense to fold. Pli selon pli, quoth Mallarmé. And during that time, affirmation of any kind — any creed that need be screed — was akin to bullshit. Not in their backyard, naw.  </p>
<p>Listening now, 35 years later, one of the most striking things about <em>No New York</em> is how none of the four bands contained herein sound anything alike. At all. The bop-seared caterwaul of The Contortions squeals worlds apart from Teenage Jesus’ draconian coronach. The dual-action, proto-pigfuckings of Mars aren’t even in the same ballpark (much less the same vinyl side) as D.N.A.’s out-of-pocket riddims. And of course, this quartet of East Village-cum-Lower East Side n’er-do-wells sounded nothing like their supposed brethren down in SoHo (Glenn Branca’s Theoretical Girls, Rhys Chatham’s Gynecologists), much less back east in Brooklyn (Red Transistor’s Von LMO). Insofar as a prevailing, immediately recognizable sound at least, there’s no such thing as ‘No Wave.’ There never was. It simply did not exist.  </p>
<p>You see, it harkens back to how No Wave was named. Standard convention notwithstanding, the thing soon became sentient. One better, it’s been told that its name means something hence. What started as a self-effacing simulacrum has since become a bona fide title of self-aggrandizement. Case in point: Nowadays, “no wave” gets bandied about as an adjective as often as it does in nominative form. There’s no stopping it. Period. (N.B. Peek at any publication, be it in print, online or via app, from the last six months. You’ll see.) Lowercase, “no wave” is a cheap and easy shorthand tied to the toe of any band that sounds like a deathwish. Hell, they needn’t even hail from the Big Apple. But guess what? That’s totally fine. Honestly, it is. ‘No Wave’ never meant anything in its own lifetime; it should stand for nothing but the same today. Proudly.        </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/NoNewYork35LKYLL.jpg" alt="" title="NoNewYork35LKYLL" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56334" /></p>
<p>As if the name alone weren’t troubling enough, the fact that <em>No New York</em> is, was and forever shall be a compilation proves equally as troublous. More so than anyone else, it was <a href= "http://brian-eno.net/lux/">Brian Eno</a> who committed these four bands to wax. So, yet again, an essay explicitly devoted to what’s essentially his mix tape might be a goof from the get-go. At best, a compilation will always be a subjective singles club — a rounding up solitary songs. At worst, it’s just another solipsistic memento mori. It’s a congenital issue. The compilation, itself, can’t help it. No matter how curated the selections, how thoughtful the sequencing, it will forever be less than the sum of its parts. And as anyone who’s ever given a mix tape (or was gifted a Muxtape) knows, an aggregate does not an album make. No, <em>No New York</em>, you are definitely not an album.</p>
<p>But that’s not a denigration. Per se. What’s so great about an album, anyways? What makes it so freakin’ special? That, too, is a question certainly worth begging. An LP is forever. Sure. Spinning 33.333 times right ‘round the unit circle, its Euclidean uniformity is borderline pathological — a record of the utmost compliance. But as an idée affixed to the Cartesian plane, the long-player’s a folly wont of Molière (especially so for <em>No New York</em>’s cruel theatre of sound.) For the foursome Eno picked to grace its grooves, their collective skronk was the epitome of careening; at any moment, things could not only fall apart, they would be decimated. Obliterated, rent asunder. Scorched from the earth. Entirely. In short, there could be no definitive No Wave album. If <em>No New York</em> was to be at all, it had to exist as a compilation. There was just no other way.  </p>
<p>Past tense is perfect tense here because none of the bands actually on <em>No New York</em> survived into adulthood. Furthermore, every single No Wave group, circa 1976 to 1980, was more or less stillborn. It’s a sobering fact. Parts of them had to die to keep on living, and, thankfully, the great ones were long gone before they got old. Of course, the immortality rate for sonic immorality always has been high. To wit, four of <em>No New York</em>’s <em>enfants terribles</em> — bass Contortion George Scott, Jerk drummer Bradley Field, Mars drummer Nancy Arlen and even lead Martian himself, Sumner Crane — are dead. Gone. They tell their no tales no longer. Scott, Field, Arlen, Crane, et al. gave us enough nope, and then they hung themselves with it: out to lunch, out to dry. Out, out dark, depraved spot. </p>
<p>Given the clinical sheen of present-day lower Manhattan, yup, said stain is tempting to fetishize. The heart lusts after what the loins hath had. That’s how hindsight works, after all. Remember, though, that nostalgia was initially catalogued as a disease. It was a malady. First. But foremost, if No Wave’s got a tint at all, it ain’t exactly colored up roses. Its vision is far too jaundiced. Any would-be patina would have to consist one-part gut, two-parts grime. Again, that’s for damn sure. And just as No Wave never liked its name while alive, we shouldn’t come to praise the <em>No New York</em> compilation now. No, that wouldn’t be prudent. If anything, No Wave should be razed. Wholesale. Truthfully, that’s probably what <em>No New York</em> would’ve wanted — four vacant bands, 16 condemned tracks. </p>
<p>Obviously, this cannot be done. Why’s that, you ask? For starters, it seems <em>No New York</em>’s been spared the zoning board. Somehow, an edifice that never was concrete got designated as a landmark, an official preserve. And in a city at constant war with real estate marquises and guerilla gentrifiers of every stripe, that’s no small feat of ghost engineering. But really, it’s mostly because it’s been too long. Three-and-a-half decades into the future, No Wave — as an aesthetic proper — can’t be undone. Nay, not even if you sued. The statute remains upheld. What’s wrought is wrought. </p>
<p>It’s the grossest kind of irony, à la O. Henry’s “Magi.” Despite No Wave’s best efforts, its innate intent even, this damned anti-movement ultimately proved too lasting, its Magna Non-Carta of 1978 too important. Not thinking twice, then, would be tantamount to treason. Or, better yet, boho heresy. Apropos of Lot&#8217;s wife fleeing Sodom, in acknowledging the carnage that was No Wave, yes, we run the pomo risk of not hearing <em>No New York</em> at all. Ideologically. If ever there were a tribe that didn’t want redemption, then this 40-minute record of their demagogy at its most base would most assuredly be it. But as far as saving No Wave’s best surviving relic goes, looking back is a chance we’re going to have to take. Losing but a pinch of <em>No New York</em> now would be a fate worse than the briniest pillar of salt. </p>
<p>Yes. Bromides, like the taxonomical vampires that catalyze them, suck. But we have to dispense them, if for nothing more than posterity might not have our same apothecary. Stunted in real-time, No Wave’s idiomatic idea of progress nevertheless proved a giant leap forward. Wagons west, destiny manifest. Ho! But in a hundred years time, the apparent glasnost of the World Wide Web’s open-table administration will have surrendered to a thousand more despots — each one less enlightened, more stentorian than the last. Moreover, since takeovers are inherently hostile coups, we can’t exactly arm a militia to stand up to a medium we can’t even fathom coming. So, in light of the menschen-machines that will eventually stop us in our tracks, we have to make sure that future generations will have access to <em>No New York</em>. If we teach them well, maybe one will serve as our children’s protest song. Antichrist, meet your archivist&#8230;</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/LKY3AM.jpg" alt="" title="LKY3AM" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56303" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<strong>Logan K. Young</strong> is the author of <a href= "http://www.amazon.co.uk/Mauricio-Kagel-A-Semic-Life/dp/1257375636"><em>Mauricio Kagel: A Semic Life</em></a>. He has written for NPR, taken pictures for <em>Maximum Rock&#8217;n'roll</em>, drawn for <em>Double Scribble</em>, and recorded for Mabson Enterprises. Last summer, he was a student in <a href= "http://www.berfrois.com/2012/11/logan-young-can-rock-stars-teach-poets/">Thurston Moore&#8217;s seminar</a> at the Jack Kerouac School for Disembodied Poetics. Come winter, Young had won a fellowship to the USC Annenberg/Getty Arts Journalism Program. His favorite track off <em>No New York</em> is &#8220;I Can&#8217;t Stand Myself&#8221;. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/no-new-york-a-jade-anniversary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Burrito &amp; Kate</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/burrito-kate/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/burrito-kate/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 08:04:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Susan Tomaselli</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Fiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56318</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/gerardmckeown-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="gerardmckeown" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56337" /></p>

Burrito tried to instigate philosophical debate the whole way back into town, but we weren’t interested. Kate was telling funny stories about people she’d gone to college with. One guy used to be a catalogue model and when he met his girlfriend’s mum for the first time the mum said he looked ‘really handsome, like someone you would see in Kays catalogue’, then he got paranoid that her mum might have seen him in a pair of y-fronts and dumped her.

By <strong>Gerard McKeown</strong >.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Gerard McKeown.</p>
<p>The park was empty from the rain and the evening. It would stay empty, except for the people I was meeting. The dope felt light in my pocket. I kept shaking it and asking myself if I’d believe it was an ounce, more a Milky Way than a Mars Bar. Waiting in a kids play park, ready to sell drugs, made me feel like a wanker, like I was in one of those awareness videos we used to make fun of at school.</p>
<p>I was meeting was a stoner called Burrito who was one of the many students returning home to the town during the summer. When he arrived Burrito had a girl with him called Kate. I didn’t know her. Kate was pretty, in that hippy sort of way. Her hair was braided with purple string, I’m not sure what it was supposed to do but it was hard to focus on anything else about her.</p>
<p>I had seventy pounds worth of dope on me but I was selling it to them for a hundred: it was amazing the expansion a block of dope underwent in half an hour in a hot oven. Burrito took the dope and shook it lightly in his hand, feeling the weight. He showed it to Kate who shrugged then nodded eagerly as if she didn’t care as long as she got a smoke soon. Burrito took five twenties out of his pocket and handed them to me. His dope shaking ritual revealed as the show it was.</p>
<p>“Split or choose?” he said turning to Kate.</p>
<p>“Choose,” she said.</p>
<p>Burrito split the dope into two equal sized blocks and Kate pocketed one, that she tucked into a gap in her twenty deck of Marlborogh Lights. Burrito slipped his half into his pocket.</p>
<p>“Do you fancy a smoke?” Kate asked me.</p>
<p>​“We buy it from him and smoke it with him too?” Burrito muttered.</p>
<p>​“Naw, you’re alright,” I said to Kate.</p>
<p>​“Naw, go on, stay,” she insisted, pulling me by the arm.</p>
<p>We walked along a path that took us out into the country, stopping at a little wood that blocked out the wind and rain. It was only half seven but already starting to get dark. Fallen leaves provided a nice cushion for us to sit on.</p>
<p>Burrito let rip with an egg and mustard special, and looked around him like a dog that had pissed on the floor and didn’t understand why he was being put outside. This was the reason for his nickname; someone said he smelt like he’d been eating beany burritos. Burrito thought it was because he looked like Gram Parsons from The Flying Burrito Brothers; their only similarity was Burrito’s hair, which he had cut purposely, after getting the nickname, to copy Parsons’ shaggy longish look.</p>
<p>Kate sparked up the first spliff and Burrito the second. Burrito attempted to start a philosophical conversation that he’d no doubt pre-rehearsed in his head. He’d done this before, another time he’d a girl with him, and he knew that I didn’t know the names for any of the philosophers or their arguments or the movements they belonged to or how they tied together.</p>
<p>“What do you think death is like?” he asked looking directly at me.</p>
<p>I didn’t reply. Though part of me felt I should; it might stop him telling one of his stories. Burrito’s stories went like this: ‘I was at the park. It was a sunny day. I had a bag of weed.’ And there it would end. All Burrito’s stories ended with him having a bag of weed. There would be occasional variances on this theme: sometimes Burrito would roll a big joint but usually he just had a bag of weed. Maybe it was the same bag of weed every time, maybe that was why it was worth talking about, or so I’d thought, but now I dealt to him I realised this wasn’t the case, though the amount he smoked suggested why he thought these stories were worth telling.</p>
<p>“Do you know what happens when you die?” he asked.</p>
<p>I ignored him. I’d stopped looking at him, there was no reason to think his question was specifically for me. One of Burrito’s signature farts drifted up into my nostrils. Kate passed me the spliff.</p>
<p>“Do you think death is like going to sleep?” Burrito asked. There was something in his tone, like he was daring me to say yes. Kate stared at the ground, like she didn’t want to meet anyone’s eye, like she was embarrassed for him. She took out her dope and began rolling another spliff.</p>
<p>“I dunno,” I shrugged.</p>
<p>“I think Death is when there are an infinite number of yourself repeating the same action at the same time.”</p>
<p>Burrito was looking round, mainly at Kate, waiting for some sort of praise for his intelligence. She was trying hard not to look up, and stared at the spliff she was making with such intensity that if we’d just got up and left she wouldn’t have noticed. When she refused to acknowledge him Burrito gave me a look like I wasn’t intelligent enough to understand what he was saying. Kate must have felt his eyes leave her because she glanced up and shook her head at him when his back was turned.</p>
<p>Listening to Burrito make an arse out of himself was one thing but I had a home with munchies and music and big cups of sugary tea that were more appealing than competing against this prick for a girl who was looking more uncomfortable by the minute.</p>
<p>“Do you study philosophy?” I asked him.</p>
<p>“No I study Law,” he said and then paused for our awed silences. I seized the opportunity to turn the conversation to Kate.</p>
<p>“Are you a student too?” I asked her.</p>
<p>“Just finished my degree,” she said. “2:1.”</p>
<p>“What are you going to do now?”</p>
<p>“Pay off some debts,” she laughed, holding up her hands like claws “eighty words a minute.”</p>
<p>“You see most people think death is like a big sleep…” Burrito began, interrupting us.</p>
<p>My flat became more appealing with every rambling phrase that poured out of Burrito’s mouth. Every joint we smoked made listening to him more of a chore. The sky was growing that dark evening colour that gives everything a bluish look. The birds were twittering away in the trees and beside me Burrito was twittering away about philosophy, spoiling it all.</p>
<p>“I’m going to head,” I said standing up, passing the joint to Kate. “Have a good night.”</p>
<p>“If you’re going into the city centre we’ll come too,” she said.</p>
<p>“Yeah, let’s go,” Burrito offered, a little late.</p>
<p>Burrito tried to instigate philosophical debate the whole way back into town, but we weren’t interested. Kate was telling funny stories about people she’d gone to college with. One guy used to be a catalogue model and when he met his girlfriend’s mum for the first time the mum said he looked ‘really handsome, like someone you would see in Kays catalogue’, then he got paranoid that her mum might have seen him in a pair of y-fronts and dumped her.</p>
<p>It was interesting that Burrito wasn’t in any of her stories, or didn’t seem to have any stories of his own. He slowed down, dragging behind us most of the way.</p>
<p>​Kate ignored him. She seemed really indifferent to him; I started to wonder how long he’d known her, or if he knew her that well at all.</p>
<p>“This is me here,” I said when we reached the edge of the pedestrian zone in the city centre; I wasn’t letting them see where I lived.</p>
<p>“See you,” Burrito said sulkily as he tried to lead Kate on.</p>
<p>Kate asked me for my number. Hopefully she would be without Burrito the next time we met.</p>
<p>She looked really pleased when I gave it to her and gave me one of those lingering looks before turning off and walking down the road with Burrito. He said something to her that I couldn’t hear; they burst out laughing and she pushed him. Then he looked back at me, laughing still. It struck me how friendly they looked together, and I wondered that he never spotted all the head shaking she did when he couldn’t see.</p>
<p>And as I stood there stoned, in the empty city centre, watching the two of them walk away with little more than fifty pounds worth of dope left between them: the fact that I had double that amount of their money in my pocket was little consolation.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/gerardmckeown.jpg" alt="" title="gerardmckeown" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56337" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
<a href="http://www.gerardmckeown.co.uk/">Gerard McKeown</a> is a writer living in London, originally from Ireland. He studied English at Queens University Belfast and Cumbria Institute of the Arts. In 2007 he was a runner up in the BBC Radio 4 UK Poetry Slam and in 2010 was featured as part of <em >The Irish Pages: Up and Coming Writers</em> showcase.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/burrito-kate/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brief encounter with the mysterian</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/brief-encounter-with-the-mysterian/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/brief-encounter-with-the-mysterian/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 14:55:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Richard Marshall</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The End Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=55639</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/colinmcginn-420x179.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56300" /></p>

My book on disgust is about the nature of that emotion, as it now exists, not about its evolutionary origins. Similarly one might write a book about knowledge and not bother too much with how knowledge evolved millions of years ago. As it happens, I have recently completed a book about human evolution and the hand. Both types of investigation are worthwhile.

Continuing the <em>End Times</em> series, <strong>Richard Marshall</strong> interviews <strong>Colin McGinn</strong>. 
]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/colinmcginn.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56300" /></p>
<p><a href="http:/mcginn.philospot.com/">Colin McGinn</a> interviewed by Richard Marshall.</p>
<p>Colin McGinn has no time for interviews because he&#8217;s too busy writing his <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/search/advanced?searchAuthor=Colin+McGinn&amp;searchSortBy=popularity&amp;searchTerm=&amp;page=1#content">books</a>, practicing his backhand and doing the philosophical stuff &#8211; but even so he took time out for a swift fly-past for the benefit of <em>3:AM Magazine</em>. He&#8217;s funny, caustic and a guy who reckons he has the measure of what needs to be said and done. His blog is an evergreen provocation and he&#8217;s not out to make friends but to keep the controversies hot. Best thing to do is to read the damn books I guess. His is the kick-ass obloquy done in the high-handed Swiftian style. Raw!    </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You have lectured on the inner philosopher in us all. Were you even as a child someone listening to those philosophical questions?</p>
<p><strong>Colin McGinn:</strong> I am still a child, and was an old man then. And yes, I was studying philosophy in the womb (see Descartes on the innateness of metaphysical ideas).</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You are a famous exponent of mysterianism, ‘a philosophy proposing that certain problems will never be explained or at the least cannot be explained by the human mind at its current evolutionary stage. The problem most often referred to is the hard problem of consciousness.’ I remember reading your book <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Mysterious-Flame-Colin-McGinn/9780465014231/?a_aid=3ammagazine">The Mysterious Flame</a></em> when it was published in 1999 and being impressed by a really smart philosopher &#8216;fessing up to the futilitarian idea that something was just too hard to solve. But I wonder whether you still think that we’ll never understand the nature of consciousness. Do you think there’ll never be a time when we get machines smarter than us? So I gues my general question is about philosophers changing their minds. Is there anything that could make you change your mind?</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I think we know the nature of consciousness better than anything else. What we don’t know is how it springs bright-eyed from the heaving of matter. Many machines are already smarter than us—at dumb things. My mind could easily be changed: by seeing consciousness leaking from the atomic nucleus, say. I also think physics is a hotbed of mystery (see my book <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Basic-Structures-Reality-Colin-McGinn/9780199841103/?a_aid=3ammaagazine">Basic Structures of Reality</a></em>).</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> One of the cool things in your <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Making-Philosopher-Colin-McGinn/9780060957605/?a_aid=3ammagazine">autobiography</a> was the detail about you playing endless games of pushball. Your approach to philosophy seems very enamored with an American, hip sense of style. Philosophy in the UK seemed drab by contrast. Is that right? </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/9780060957605.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-55642" /></p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I don’t know what pushball is and have never knowingly played it. I have played quite a good deal of pinball, as well as old video games like Galaga and Defender. My sense of style is not American-inspired: it is a combination of Steve Marriott and Vladimir Nabokov. I never found philosophy in the UK drab, just underpaid. </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You’re an iconoclast. You write things that cause a stir and shake up establishment figures. You seem to kick up. This seemed to me to be the heart of your <a href="http:/leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2007/10/colin-mcginn-di.html">attack on Honderich</a> in a book review a few years ago  that got everyone very worked up. Honderich seemed to be a snob and elitist who was happy to be super critical of others but didn’t approve of someone like you. Am I right to read this into your attitude to some of your peers. I recall in your autobiography that you had a kind of unhappy crossing with Michael Dummett which again seemd like a story of a grand big ‘un being impossibly rude to a young turk.</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I am a moral and intellectual elitist of the most extreme and repellent kind. I simply thought Honderich’s book was terrible. Dummett was just being Dummett. I think young people should be encouraged.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Recent work in philosophy by, say, <a href="http:/experimentalphilosophy.typepad.com/">experimemtal philosophers</a> like <a href="http:/www.3ammagazine.com/3am/indie-rock-virtues/">Josh Knobe</a>, seem to be much less inclined to elitism and far more constructively engaged in dialogic philosophical conversation. Do you think that philosophy is less the preserve of dull elitism than it was when you began? </p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Philosophy now is horribly democratic. I used to be a psychologist, so I know about experiments; people who do “ex-phi” don’t seem to. I don’t mind surveying people’s conceptual opinions, but I find the hostility to traditional philosophy ludicrous and pernicious (I’ve written about this in <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Truth-by-Analysis-Colin-McGinn/9780199856145">Truth By Analysis</a></em>).</p>
<p> <strong>3:AM:</strong> You wrote about philosophy and sport in your book ‘<em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Sport-Colin-McGinn/9781844651481">Sport: Art of Living</a></em>’. You once compared Obama and Bush in terms of both sporting and linguistic prowess. Can you say more about your philosophical interest in sport, an unusual topic for philosophical reflection, and how such reflection helps us think about the world? </p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I am an athlete by nature—it is in my blood. I spent a lot of yesterday in the howling wind practicing my backhand slice with a ball machine. I would rather throw a couch than sit on it. Philosophically, games and sport are the meaning of life (see Bernard Suits, <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Grasshopper-Bernard-Suits/9781551117720">The Grasshopper</a></em>).</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You are a serious writer about <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Ethics-Evil-Fiction-Colin-McGinn/9780198238775">literature</a>. You have written about <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Shakespeares-Philosophy-Colin-McGinn/9780060856168">Shakespeare as a philosopher</a>. Can you say something about him, about the problem of evil in his plays, his epistemology, ethics, happiness and the meaning of life? </p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/9780060856168.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-55645" /></p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong>  Shakespeare stands above and below human life. As to evil and what not, I suggest reading my book <em>Shakespeare’s Philosophy</em> (I write books so as not to have to answer questions).</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Can you say something about how studying Shakespeare has impacted on your <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Power-Movies-Colin-McGinn/9781400077205">philosophical outlook</a>? Are there positions you argue now that you doubt you would have argued had you not read Shakespeare? </p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Shakespeare has had no impact on my philosophical life, except to make it seem less worthwhile.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> You argue that philosophy is generally an atheistic discipline these days. Yet you argue that ‘tolerating somebody else’s beliefs is not failing to critisise them. It’s not persecuting them for having those beliefs. That is absolutely important. You should not prosecute people for their beliefs. It doesn’t mean that you can’t criticize their beliefs.’ Given that most people now live in hugely diverse and pluralistic social groups, this is a subtle and civilized position that many people find hard to understand and accept. It’s something that I think <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Why-Tolerate-Religion-Brian-Leiter/9780691153612">Brian Leiter</a> has discussed in terms of religious belief. Can you say more about why you think this tolerance is of such fundamental <a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Moral-Literacy-Colin-McGinn/9780872201965">importance</a>?</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Tolerance is about freedom of thought and speech. Such freedom is the most precious thing in the world. </p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> One thing you say about philosophy is that to be philosophically smart you need to get to grips with some foundational stuff first before moving on to more esoteric subjects like whether God exists. So you argue that before considering Theism we need to know what knowledge is, what logical reasoning is and what truth is and so on. To some this might seem the wrong way round. They will say that we start with the esoteric question and we work out answers to what you’re calling the basic questions through thinking about those? So how do you answer that sort of thought?</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I have nothing to say about this question. I would be boring even myself. (All right: a bit of both.)</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Last year you published your book on disgust, ‘ <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Meaning-Disgust-Colin-McGinn/9780199829538">The Meaning Of Disgust</a></em>.’ The problem of disgust as you address it arises because of its nature as a sui generis aversive emotion ‘importantly different from its aversive cousins’. It is the uniqueness that makes it philosophically interesting to you. It raises the question: ‘ Why should we be so averse to what is not intrinsically harmful to us?’ So can you tell us how you go about answering this question.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/9780199829538.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="430" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-55647" /></p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> My book on disgust is about the nature of that emotion, as it now exists, not about its evolutionary origins. Similarly one might write a book about knowledge and not bother too much with how knowledge evolved millions of years ago. As it happens, I have recently completed a book about human evolution and <a href="http:/mcginn.philospot.com/index.php?story=story120728-183642">the hand</a>. Both types of investigation are worthwhile.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Josh Knobe and those in the experimental philosophy movement may argue that analysis without experimental data is blind. They might object that your approach is too rooted in armchair investigation. What would you say to this criticism?</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Conceptual analysis is not about concepts—it is about the world. We can analyze the world conceptually from both a first-person and a third-person viewpoint. I bang on about this in <em>Truth By Analysis</em>.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong>  You wrote about imagination in your 2004 book ‘<em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Mindsight-Colin-McGinn/9780674022478">Mindsight: Image, Dream, Meaning</a></em>’ that you had decided to write on imagination because ‘contemporary philosophy of mind contains little directly on the imagination.’ You make the distinction between images and percepts. Can you say what this distinction is and why it is crucial for your overall understanding of imagination.</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Imagination is a big subject. It is becoming hip. It is fairly elitist. Images differ from perceptions in many ways; I seem to recall that my book relentlessly lists these ways. I was rehashing Sartre and Wittgenstein.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> Finally, you have written  in your book ‘<em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Ethics-Evil-Fiction-Colin-McGinn/9780198238775">Ethics, Evil and Fiction</a></em>’ that fiction can enrich the study of ethics. Can you say something about this and tell us which books you have found enlightening and which authors you’d recommend for readers here at 3:AM? </p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> Fiction makes evil bearable (herein lies its danger). I recommend my self-published novel <em><a href="http:/www.amazon.com/Bad-Patches-Colin-McGinn/dp/1477688382">Bad Patches</a></em> to readers of 3:AM (available from Amazon for $3.99!). It is about the evil of banality.</p>
<p><strong>3:AM:</strong> And finally finally, could you give us a top five list of philosophy books you’d recommend to the smart readers of 3:AM (other than yours of course, which they’ll already be reading!)?</p>
<p><strong>CM:</strong> I never read philosophy books anymore unless at the point of a gun. I recently read <strong>Richard Dawkins’s</strong> <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Ancestors-Tale-Richard-Dawkins/9780753819968">The Ancestor’s Tale</a></em>, which I found very informative. I also read <strong>Tivadar Soros’</strong> powerfully understated <em><a href="http:/www.bookdepository.co.uk/Masquerade-Tivadar-Soros/9781611450248">Masquerade</a> </em>about a very real evil (one of his sons gave it to me). I think <em>The Cleveland Show</em> is the funniest thing on television, closely followed by <em>Downton Abbey</em>.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/richardmarshallnewnew.jpg" alt="" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-55265" /><br />
<strong>ABOUT THE INTERVIEWER</strong><br />
<a href="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?s=%22richard+marshall%22"><strong>Richard Marshall</strong></a> is still biding his time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/brief-encounter-with-the-mysterian/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Incomparables</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/incomparables/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/incomparables/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 13:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Andrew Gallix</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonfiction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56172</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/ManRayphotoofMarcelDuchamp1920LaTonsure-420x179.jpg" alt="" title="ManRayphotoofMarcelDuchamp1920LaTonsure" width="420" height="179" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-56276" /></p>

The web also regenerates deep connections to the past; so cyberspace, this territory which stretches out from hypertext to the world-wide computer network, from virtual reality to video games, might also be theorized as the domain of Roussel’s idea of reduplicating without duplication, reiterating without repeating: his game-of-mirrors cosmos. His is a strident activity lost in an infinite navigation from one sort of encounter to another in which the affirmation of the other keeps appearing and disappearing in the play of mechanical manoeuvres (or mechanisms) destined to avert gratification. This is where the bachelor apparatus of Duchamp repeats itself ad infinitum by transmitting the machine via an alter-ego.

<strong>Joseph Nechvatal</strong> reviews the <strong><em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em></strong> exhibition in Paris.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Joseph Nechvatal.</p>
<p><strong><em>Nouvelles impressions de Raymond Roussel</em><br />
(New Impressions of Raymond Roussel)<br />
Palais de Tokyo, Paris</strong></p>
<p><em>&#8220;My soul is a strange factory&#8221; &#8211; Raymond Roussel</em></p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/ManRayphotoofMarcelDuchamp1920LaTonsure.jpg" alt="" title="ManRayphotoofMarcelDuchamp1920LaTonsure" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56276" /></p>
<p><em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em> points us towards an intellectual history that maps out art’s role in creating a social allegory for the poetic psychoanalysis [1] of mechanized pleasure — in circular struggle with the mechanized mass killings of World War I and II, the holocaust, and Hiroshima. And the rewards of such exhausting circularity are considerable, given both the historical significance of Raymond Roussel’s influence and its unapologetic relevance to today’s cyber culture — with its intransigent obliqueness and mechanical dizziness.</p>
<p>But if I were going to generate an art exhibition as homage to a particularly flamboyant artist [2], even if <em>un peu obscur</em>, I would think that it would be advantageous to try to match the aesthetic qualities of that person (absurdly intricate mechanical interlacings) with the show’s general aesthetic. Unfortunately, that was not the least bit achieved with the homage to the wildly creative dandy writer <a href= "http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond_Roussel">Raymond Roussel</a> (1877-1933) [3] that is at the Palais de Tokyo&#8217;s Centre d&#8217;art contemporain in Paris. </p>
<p>While access to much of the remarkable work here (including five of Roussel’s otherworldy handwritten manuscript pages for his last book <em>Comment j&#8217;ai écrit certains de mes livres</em> (How I Wrote Some of my Books) and a wonderful cookie-encasing sculpture memento called <em>Etoile cosmique</em> (Cosmic Star) — a glass and silver case that Roussel had made for a star-shaped biscuit he brought back from lunch in Juvisy-sur-Orge with the astronomer Camille Flammarion (1842-1925) on July 29, 1923 — is to be appreciated and relished, the cavernous half-finished Level 1 Galerie Seine devoured and neutralized any stylistic moods of gamesmanship that are associated with Roussel: such as the famously extravagant, yet intricately hermetic, elaborate mechanamorphic constructions that verged on the exuberantly preposterousness of a machine running infinitely wild. Perhaps if I had seen the other two manifestations of this show — <em>Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em> held at the Museo Reina Sofia (Madrid) in 2011 and the Museu Serralves (Porto) in 2012 — I may not have felt so disappointed in the general lack of neurotic deliriousness experienced in this one. </p>
<p>Granted that Raymond Roussel’s disregard for financial restraint [4] cannot be matched by the Palais de Tokyo, but still the gutted construction materials hanging overhead in this ugly cavernous space take the eye and mind out of the magnificently intricate labyrinthine quality typical of his extravagant writings: as established in the prose work <em>Impressions d’Afrique</em> (1910) (a work that features a painting machine that duplicates the colour spectrum of the sky at dawn) [5], <em>Locus Solus</em> (1914) (like <em>Impressions d’Afrique</em>, written according to formal constraints based on homonymic puns) and the obsessive but convulsingly poetic <em>Nouvelle Impressions d’Afrique</em> (1932) [6]. Thus the larger the art (even as it was needed to fill this mammoth half-raw space) the worse it connected to Roussel’s sense of virtual impenetrability through mechanical precision.</p>
<p>Mike Kelly’s lumbering black cave <em>Kandors 10B (Exploded Fortress of Solitude)</em> (2011) and Rodney Graham’s <em>Camera Obscura Mobile</em> (1995-1996) installation were particularly unmatched to Roussel’s obsessive minute attention; a concentration that is capable of whirling together copious narratives from a veiled network of murky puns and obscured double entendres in a way that anticipates the Oulipo. Mark Manders’s steamy black connectivist sculpture <em>Mind Study</em> (2011), Giuseppe Gabellone’s beautiful silver sculpture <em>L’Assetalo</em> (Thirsty Man) (2008) and Jacques Carelman’s droll motion sculpture <em>Le Diamont</em> (The Diamond) (1975) worked only a bit better in reinforcing a spirit of intricate mechanicalness as they each ate up almost an entire room. A relatively fascinating installation by André Maranha, Pedro Morais, Jorge Queiroz and Francisco Tropa called <em>Tres Moscas</em> (Three Flies) (2012) did eat an entire room and only delivered limited thematic power in terms of absurd interlacing.<br />
Much more capable of such finicky and arcane mesmerizing rhythms was the more intimate yet preposterous work of Thomas Bayrle (his deadpan pulsating romantic machine <em>Spatz von Paris</em>, 2011, is one of the highlights of the show).</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/MarkMandersMindStudy.jpg" alt="" title="MarkMandersMindStudy" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56279" /><br />
[<strong>Mark Mander, <em>Mind Study</em></strong>] </p>
<p>Rodney Graham’s series of books called <em>The System</em> worked well in the context and it was captivating to see displays of the literary journal <em>Revue Locus Solus</em>, established by American writers John Ashbery, Harry Mathews, Kenneth Koch and James Shuyler. Published in Paris between 1961 and 1962, the journal formed a bridge between French authors, both historical and contemporary, and writers from the New York School and the Beat Generation. The Collège de Pataphysique was represented by the writer Jean Ferry who published several studies devoted to Roussel, including <em>L’Afrique des Impressions</em>, a detailed analysis which consists of considering the text as instructions for users and reconstructing, in the form of maps, diagrams and schedules, the journeys and events that took place at Ponukélé, an imaginary place in Roussel’s Africa. Two comical cosmic Joseph Cornell boxes, <em>Blue Sand Box</em> and <em>Sand Fountain</em> from the early 1950s pleased me, as they bracketed a stream of photographed drawings of fantastic imaginary architecture from 1857 by Victorien Sardou — as did an early Pataphysical video by Jean-Christophe Averty. </p>
<p>The irascible Salvador Dalí is represented with his short motion picture <em>Impressions de la Haute Mongolie</em> (1975), made with the filmmaker José Montes-Baquer. Dalí read Roussel’s books as early as the 1920s and Roussel had a great influence on Dalí’s &#8220;critical paranoia&#8221; method. Dalí, who died with a copy of <em>Impressions d&#8217;Afrique</em> on his bedside table, believed him to be one of France&#8217;s greatest writers ever. Jean Tinguely is inserted, rightly, into this mix with a brain-teasing manic lithograph from 1966-67 called <em>Requiem pour une feuille morte</em> (Requiem for a Dead Leaf), rather than an expected endless drawing machine contraption, that would have more directly interlocked with Roussel’s imagined painting machine.<br />
And Roussel’s major inspiration (along with novelist and naval officer Pierre Loti), the author Jules Verne, has a wacky lithograph of a flat globe studded with images entitled <em>Around the World in Eighty Days</em> from 1880. Roussel greatly admired the works of Verne — which he read over and over again, fascinated with their extraodinary voyages and machines, full of bachelor scientists completely absorbed in positivist exploratory dreams taken to delirious extremes. At that scale of interlacing, some of the hypnotic effect of Roussel’s capacious playful circularity can be felt.</p>
<p>However, Gabriele Di Matteo’s contribution to the show’s circularity is essential. His hand-painted over digital-painting <em>Marcel Duchamp, a life in pictures by André Raffray</em> illustrates the time when Duchamp attended a showing of <em>Impressions d’Afrique</em> in 1912, an experience Duchamp would describe as revelatory. As Gabriele Di Matteo depicts, Duchamp, along with Guillaume Appollinaire, Picabia and Picabia’s wife Gabrielle Buffet, attended a performance of <em>Impressions of Africa</em> — the play by Roussel, based on his book. Duchamp later credited Roussel with the inspiration for his <em>The Bride Stripped Bare by Her Bachelors, Even (The Large Glass)</em>. There are several original notes by Duchamp and a drawing that he made for <em>The Large Glass</em> in 1912-1915 in the show, as well as quite a few photos of Duchamp with <em>The Large Glass</em>. Among them is the striking photo of Duchamp that was taken by Man Ray in 1920 that shows a star carved out in Duchamp’s hair. This work connects ludicrously well with Roussel’s star-shaped cookie piece, <em>Etoile cosmique</em>, from just three years later.</p>
<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/RaymondRousselEtoilecosmique1923.jpg" alt="" title="RaymondRousselEtoilecosmique1923" width="450" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56278" /><br />
[<strong>Raymond Roussel’s <em>Etoile cosmique</em> (<em>Cosmic Star</em>), 1923</strong>]</p>
<p>Historically, the mechanamorphic impulse behind Marcel Duchamp&#8217;s works from 1912 (that derived a good deal from Roussel) is of great significance. That is when Duchamp started producing paintings and drawings depicting mechanized sex acts such as <em>Mechanics of Modesty</em> and <em>The Passage from the Virgin to the Bride</em> — and the fantastic machine-body work <em>The Bride Stripped Bare by Her Bachelors, Even</em> that follow his exposure to the play <em>Impressions d’Afrique</em> — is an inescapable point of reference for the avant-garde of the 20th century. The same may be said for Francis Picabia (who has a room of paintings all to himself at the show <em>La Collection Michael Werner</em> just a stone&#8217;s throw away at the Musée d&#8217;Art Moderne Ville de Paris).</p>
<p>The elaborateness of the machine, for Duchamp and Picabia, became the symbol of sexual bliss [7] attainable through concept connected to auto-sexual autonomy in contradiction to the horror that mechanized war had brought. By hypnotizing attention, the machine freed them from troubling obsessions and personal hang-ups through the alternative model of android life; intimating both our rush of desperation and our ecstatic release, refracted through a web of glazed impersonality. If the machine, as a representative of order, was a fascination Duchamp and Picabia used to balance out the age’s clumsiness, whether of the mind or flesh, Roussel’s mechanamorphic production and machine forms refigured the human body into an almost mechanized substance.</p>
<p>In <em>The Bride Stripped Bare by the Bachelors, Even</em>, which positions a central bride machine over a bachelor apparatus, Duchamp, with the strictness of machinery, applies fantasy to seduction and masturbation. In a way, Duchamp suggests that we (as viewers) can use his art as a vehicle for self-transcendence into a kind of dream world of nonsense sex. This rabbit-hole logic he took from Roussel.</p>
<p>So <em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em> succeeds when it outlines an eccentric expanding circular history of 20th-century art, linking the points between artists and writers who have talked of the influence of this author and his writings on their work: starting with Dada (Duchamp, Man Ray, Picabia), then André Breton and the Surrealists (like Michel Leiris, Salvador Dalí, Jean Cocteau) to Neo-Dada Nouveau réalisme (Jean Tinguely) through Oulipo (Georges Perec) Pataphysicians (Jean Ferry, Jean-Christophe Averty and the Collège de Pataphysique) and the authors of the nouveau roman (like Alain Robbe-Grillet). As noted above, his most direct influence in the English-speaking world was on the New York School of poets John Ashbery, Harry Mathews, James Schuyler, and Kenneth Koch.</p>
<p>Writing as art — or art as writing: this is the theoretical ripe fruit plucked from <em>Nouvelles impressions de Raymond Roussel</em> — art theory as art — made conceivable by Roussel’s inventions of language machines that produced texts through the use of repetitions and combination/permutations. This machine-like logic provides art with a seemingly pure spectacle of endless variety of textual games and combinations flowing in circular form. (We see and feel this most fully, however, in the sprawling and dazzling Julio Le Parc kinetic op art retrospective on the first floor of the Palais de Tokyo, rather than in this show.) </p>
<p>And there are lessons here for painting, also. Within this writing process Roussel described a number of fantastic machines, including a painting machine in his novel <em>Impressions of Africa</em>. This painting machine wonderfully describes and foresees the arrival of computer-robotic technology and it&#8217;s application to visual art which we have available to us today, a century after he envisioned it.</p>
<p>The web also regenerates deep connections to the past; so cyberspace, this territory which stretches out from hypertext to the world-wide computer network, from virtual reality to video games, might also be theorized as the domain of Roussel’s idea of reduplicating without duplication, reiterating without repeating: his game-of-mirrors cosmos. His is a strident activity lost in an infinite navigation from one sort of encounter to another in which the affirmation of the other keeps appearing and disappearing in the play of mechanical manoeuvres (or mechanisms) destined to avert gratification. This is where the bachelor apparatus of Duchamp repeats itself ad infinitum by transmitting the machine via an alter-ego.</p>
<p>But <em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em> reminds us that Raymond Roussel&#8217;s themes and procedures also involved imprisonment and liberation, exoticism, cryptograms and torture by language — all formally reflected in his working technique with its inextricable play of double images, repetitions, and impediments, all giving the impression of the pen running on by itself through the dreamy usage and baroque play of mirrored form.  </p>
<p>Roussel&#8217;s running on repetition technique, as used in the Thomas Bayrle sculpture, for example, lends itself well to the creation of unforeseen, automatic, spontaneous art which gives me the feeling of prolonging action into eternity through the ceaseless, fantastic constructions of the work itself, transmitting an altered, exalted and orgasmic state of mind which after the initial dazzle creates one predominant overall effect: that of creating doubt through mechanical discourse.</p>
<p>The image of enclosure is common with Roussel where a secret to a secret is held back, systematically imposing a formless anxiety in the reader through the labyrinthine extensions and doublings, disguises and duplications of his texts, which make all speech and vision undergo a moment of annihilation.</p>
<p><em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em> succeeds when it presents to us through intimacy the model of quiet perfection of the eternally repetitive mechanical machine which functions independently of time and space, pulling us into a logic of the infinite. We can learn this from Roussel&#8217;s final rebus-like book, <em>Comment j&#8217;ai écrit certains de mes livres</em> (How I Wrote Some of my Books); the last of his conceptual machines, the machine which contains and repeats within its mechanism all those mental machines he had formerly described and put into motion, making evident the machine which produced all of his machines — the master machine [8]. All of these machines map out an eccentric spiral space that is circular in nature and thus an abstract attempt at eliminating time. They reproduce the old myths of departure, of loss and of return. They construct a crisscrossed mechanical map of the two great mythic spaces so often explored by western imagination: space that is rigid and forbidden, containing the quest, the return and the treasure (for example the geography of the Argonauts and the labyrinth), and the other space of polymorphosic noise: the visible transformation of instantly crossed frontiers and borders, of strange affiliations, of spells, and of symbolic replacements (the space of the Minotaur). </p>
<p><em>Nouvelles impressions de Raymond Roussel</em> potentially removes us out of our quiet and glib indolence and points us in the potent direction of expanding intensity. I believe that shows like this are critical to us now because the counter-mannerist excess found there can problematize the popular simulacrum that art has become — and make the underground, intricately strange privateness of the human animal livelier.</p>
<p><center>****</center></p>
<p>[<strong>1</strong>] At age 17, Roussel wrote <em>Mon Âme</em>, a long poem published three years later in <em>Le Gaulois</em>. By 1896, he had commenced editing his long poem <em>La Doublure</em> when he suffered a mental crisis. After the poem was published on June 10, 1897 and was completely unsuccessful, Roussel began to see the psychiatrist Pierre Janet.</p>
<p>[<strong>2</strong>] Poet, novelist, playwright, musician, and chess enthusiast.</p>
<p>[<strong>3</strong>] Raymond Roussel was born in Paris in 1877. His writings, including the novels <em>Impressions of Africa</em> and <em>Locus Solus</em> and volumes of poetry and drama, were largely ignored in his lifetime, but have since been championed by the likes of Michel Leiris (whose father was Roussel’s accountant), Raymond Queneau, Alain Robbe-Grillet (his first novel, <em>Le Voyeur</em>, was originally titled <em>La Vue</em> in homage to Roussel’s long 1904 poem of the same name), Georges Perec, Harry Mathews, John Ashbery and Michel Foucault (Foucault wrote a critical study, <em>Death and the Labyrinth</em>, after the chance discovery of one of Roussel’s volumes in an antiquarian shop across from the Luxembourg Gardens). Roussel died under mysterious circumstances (apparently by suicide) in 1933 in Palermo in Sicily after he went broke chasing literary fame before his death — decades before his work began receiving the acceptance he craved. He is buried in Père-Lachaise cemetery in Paris.</p>
<p>[<strong>4</strong>] In 1894, at age 16, he inherited a substantial fortune from his deceased father and began to write poetry to accompany his musical compositions. Tremendously wealthy, he took two world tours during which he hardly left his hotel rooms.</p>
<p>[<strong>5</strong>] The story told in <em>Impressions of Africa</em> is a nominally bare-bones fantasy. The shipwrecked inhabitants of the Lyseus, en route from Marseille to Argentina, are captured by an African potentate, Talou, who holds them hostage while awaiting their ransom. The ship’s manifest includes actors, singers, musicians, fearless naturalists, a slew of carpenters, and, fortuitously, a trove of instruments, lumber, scientific equipment, and trained animals. Partly to keep themselves busy, the motley Europeans, dubbing themselves the Incomparables, decide to stage a set of performances. Converging with their gala is Talou’s military triumph over a rival clan (and the execution of a handful of unloyal subjects). This is the back-story of <em>Impressions of Africa</em>, literally.</p>
<p>[<strong>6</strong>] <em>New Impressions of Africa</em> is a 1,274-line poem, consisting of four long cantos in rhymed alexandrines, each a single sentence with parenthetical asides that run up to five levels deep. From time to time, a footnote refers to a further poem containing its own depths of brackets. Roussel worked and reworked the 1,274 lines of <em>New Impressions of Africa</em> over a seventeen-year period, rewriting each one as many as twenty times to accomplish a mordant succinctness.</p>
<p>[<strong>7</strong>] Around the same point in time, Dr. Freud was explaining in his lectures that complex machines that repeat in dreams signified the genital organs. Roussel&#8217;s descriptions of eggs on plates and the multiple allusions to the odor of urine after the eating of asparagus are typical of a poetic-mechanical apparatus helping to take us further into the area of the unconscious and the sexual.</p>
<p>[<strong>8</strong>] Roussel had kept this compositional method a secret until the publication of his posthumous text, <em>How I Wrote Some of My Books</em>, where he describes it as follows: &#8220;I chose two similar words. For example, billard (billiard) and pillard (looter). Then I added to it words similar but taken in two different directions, and I obtained two almost identical sentences thus. The two sentences found, it was a question of writing a tale which can start with the first and finish by the second. Amplifying the process then, I sought new words related to the word billiard, always to take them in a different direction than that which was presented at first, and that provided me each time with a new creation. The process evolved and I was led to take an unspecified sentence, from which I drew some images by dislocating it. &#8230;&#8221;</p>
<p><center>****</center></p>
<p><a href= "http://palaisdetokyo.com/fr/exposition/nouvelles-impressions-de-raymond-roussel"><em>Nouvelles impressions de Raymond Roussel</em></a> (<em>New Impressions of Raymond Roussel</em>) includes work by: Mathieu K. Abonnenc, Jean-Michel Alberola, Jean-Christophe Averty, Zbynek Baladrán, Thomas Bayrle, Jacques Carelman, Guy de Cointet, Collège de Pataphysique, Joseph Cornell, Salvador Dalí, Gabriele Di Matteo, Thea Djordjadze, Marcel Duchamp, Giuseppe Gabellone, Rodney Graham, João Maria Gusmão &#038; Pedro Paiva, Mike Kelley, Revue Locus Solus, Pierre Loti, Sabine Macher, Man Ray, Mark Manders, André Maranha, Pedro Morais, Jorge Queiroz et Francisco Tropa, Jean-Michel Othoniel, Victorien Sardou, Joe Scanlan, Jean Tinguely, Jules Verne.</p>
<p><strong>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</strong><br />
Since 1986 <a href= "http://www.nechvatal.net/">Joseph Nechvatal</a> has worked with ubiquitous electronic visual information, computers and computer-robotics. His computer-robotic assisted paintings and computer software animations are shown regularly in galleries and museums throughout the world. From 1991-1993 he worked as artist-in-residence at the Louis Pasteur Atelier and the Saline Royale / Ledoux Foundation&#8217;s computer lab in Arbois, France, on <em>The Computer Virus Project</em>: an experiment with computer viruses as a creative stratagem. In 2002 he extended that artistic research into the field of viral artificial life through his collaboration with the programmer Stéphane Sikora. Nechvatal earned his Ph.D. in the philosophy of art and new technology at The Centre for Advanced Inquiry in the Interactive Arts (CAiiA) University of Wales College, Newport, UK. His book of essays <em>Towards an Immersive Intelligence: Essays on the Work of Art in the Age of Computer Technology and Virtual Reality (1993-2006)</em> was published by Edgewise Press in 2009. In 2011 his book <em>Immersion Into Noise</em> was published by the University of Michigan Library&#8217;s Scholarly Publishing Office in conjunction with the Open Humanities Press.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/incomparables/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Missing Links</title>
		<link>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-274/</link>
		<comments>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-274/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 20:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Andrew Gallix</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Buzzwords]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/?p=56125</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kit Caless reviews Lee Rourke&#8216;s excellent Varroa Destructor, forthcoming from 3:AM Press: &#8220;There is a twinkling humour that runs through the book: a kind of funny nihilism through which Rourke brings a dark beauty to the mundane&#8221;. * On Félix Guattari&#8216;s unpublished SF film script. * An excerpt from Iain Sinclair&#8216;s forthcoming American Smoke. * [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/missatomicbomb.jpg" alt="" title="missatomicbomb" width="590" height="349" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-56274" /></p>
<p><strong>Kit Caless</strong> reviews <a href="http://thequietus.com/articles/11603-lee-rourke-varroa-destructor">Lee Rourke</a>&#8216;s excellent <strong><em>Varroa Destructor</em></strong>, forthcoming from <a href= "http://3ampress.tumblr.com/">3:AM Press</a>: <em>&#8220;There is a twinkling humour that runs through the book: a kind of funny nihilism through which Rourke brings a dark beauty to the mundane&#8221;</em>. * On <a href= "http://www.eastofborneo.org/articles/castaways-of-a-new-cosmic-catastrophe">Félix Guattari</a>&#8216;s unpublished SF film script. * An excerpt from <a href= "http://www.iainsinclair.org.uk/2013/03/09/dream-science-a-taster-from-american-smoke-iains-new-book-with-w-burroughs-photos/">Iain Sinclair</a>&#8216;s forthcoming <em><strong>American Smoke</strong></em>. * <a href= "http://julietjacques.tumblr.com/">Juliet Jacques</a> goes in search of the miraculous. * <a href= "http://inexhaustible-instant.tumblr.com/">Inexhaustible instants</a>. * <a href= "http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rmLGq6Odu7g&#038;feature=youtu.be">Will Self</a> pays a visit to <strong>occupied Sussex</strong> and asks students never to ignore the <em>&#8220;Chicken of Depression&#8221;</em>. * <a href= "http://jacketmagazine.com/23/lazer-waldr.html">Edmond Jabès</a>. * <a href= "http://www.bookslut.com/blog/archives/2013_03.php#019961">Clarice Lispector</a> (from <em>The Apple in the Dark</em>). * <a href= "http://www.galleybeggar.co.uk/book-store/product-category/wedlock-by-george-egerton/">George Egerton</a>&#8216;s <em>Wedlock</em>. * <a href= "http://www.continentcontinent.cc/index.php/continent/article/viewArticle/84">Cosmic pessimism</a>. * <a href= "http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/books/2013/03/interview-with-a-writer-lars-iyer/">Lars Iyer</a> interviewed in <em><strong>The Spectator</strong></em>. * <a href= "http://puntar.wordpress.com/2013/03/05/brod-insults-brod/">Brod insults Brod</a>. * <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2013/mar/07/will-self-flag-waving-heartlands">Will Self</a> on Britain&#8217;s far right. * <a href= "http://www.waggish.org/">David Auerbach</a>&#8216;s great review of <strong>Perec</strong>&#8216;s <a href= "http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1466"><em>La boutique obscure</em></a>. * <strong>Nicholas Lezard</strong> reviews <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2013/mar/05/mandy-charlie-stewart-home-review">Stewart Home</a>&#8216;s new novel: <em>&#8220;It is almost as if the book is an enactment of the very sloppiness of the society it seeks to indict, or describe. It is very cheeky of Home to have his cake and eat it like this: yet you have to admire cheek at this level&#8221;</em>. * New <a href= "http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dZsAr4FHghw">Anne Pigalle</a> video. * The only known recording of <a href= "http://www.openculture.com/2012/05/sigmund_freud_speaks_the_only_known_recording_of_his_voice_1938.html">Freud</a>, 1938. * <a href= "http://hermouth.blogspot.co.uk/">Popping a lozenge into her mouth</a>. * <a href= "http://www.thewhitereview.org/features/celan-reads-japanese/?utm_source=The+White+Review+Mailing+List&#038;utm_campaign=f869338edb-The_White_Review_SSP&#038;utm_medium=email">Paul Celan reads Japanese</a>. * Congratulations to <a href= "http://www.latimes.com/features/books/jacketcopy/la-jc-tom-mccarthy-james-salter-windham-campbell-prizes-20130304,0,3398500.story">Tom McCarthy</a>, who is among the winners of the inaugural <strong>Donald Windham-Sandy M. Campbell Literature Prizes</strong>. * <a href= "http://www.bookslut.com/features/2013_03_019938.php">Dylan Nice</a> interviewed at <em><strong>Bookslut</strong></em>: <em>&#8220;<strong>Gary [Lutz]</strong> was the first writing teacher I had who showed me that the sentence was capable of art. He would underline good sentences and interrogate bad ones. Verbs would be circled and Gary would ask &#8216;inevitable?&#8217; And no, the verb was not inevitable, and I&#8217;d never considered that concept before, inevitability. It smacks of the eternal, a text beyond the writer to which the writer submits&#8221;</em>. * On <a href= "http://lareviewofbooks.org/article.php?id=1465">Sam Lipsyte</a>. * The ever wonderful <a href= "http://www.paulgormanis.com/?p=3965">Judy Nylon</a>. * <a href= "http://ubumexico.centro.org.mx/sound/burroughs_william/RET/Burroughs-William_RET_3-04-We-Are-The-Night-Family.mp3">William Burroughs</a>&#8216;s &#8220;<strong>We Are the Night Family</strong>&#8221; tape cut-up, 1964. * <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/mar/09/david-bowie-william-burroughs">When Bowie met Burroughs</a>. * <strong>Brian Dillon</strong> on <a href= "http://briangdillon.wordpress.com/2013/03/01/all-that-is-solid/">Helen Marten</a>. * <a href= "http://www.thestoolpigeon.co.uk/features/video-richard-hell-blank-generation-film-with-carole-bouquet-andy-warhol.html"><em>Blank Generation</em></a>, 1980. * <a href= "http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/03/fashion/safekeeping-a-punk-creation-possessed.html?_r=1&#038;">Richard Hell</a> in the <em><strong>New York Times</strong></em>. * Information about <a href= "http://www.richardhell.com/">Hell</a>&#8216;s long-awaited <a href= "http://pinterest.com/eccobooks/richard-hell/">autobiography</a> is beginning to <a href= "http://www.austinchronicle.com/blogs/music/2011-09-28/tramp-on-your-street/">filter through</a>. Here&#8217;s a bit about <a href= "http://tmagazine.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/27/close-read-kiss-and-yell/">the Pistols</a>: <em>&#8220;&#8216;I felt almost as if they were my dream, my mental production.&#8217; But he also acknowledges that the Pistols had something he didn’t. Johnny Rotten, he writes, &#8216;was all energy and extroversion. He galvanized the kids. I was the opposite, a sullen forlorn junkie outcast who just wanted to be left alone, except by admiring girls.&#8217;&#8221;</em> There&#8217;s a short review of the memoir <a href= "http://www.publishersweekly.com/978-0-06-219083-3">here</a>, and another one <a href= "http://www.kirkusreviews.com/book-reviews/richard-hell/i-dreamed-i-was-a-very-clean-tramp/">there</a>. And also <a href= "http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/03/richard-hell-21-questions.html?mid=twitter_vulture">this</a>.  * <a href= "http://dangerousminds.net/comments/lipstick_killers_the_new_york_dolls_live_halloween_1973">The New York Dolls</a> live, 1973. * <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2013/mar/08/robert-thomson-life-in-writing">Rupert Thomson</a>: <em>&#8220;By day, he worked on accounts for &#8216;helicopters, face cream or window cleaner&#8217;, while by night he was a clubber on London&#8217;s punk scene — &#8216;I was once set on fire at the Marquee when a girl called Tampax put a match to my bin-liner T-shirt&#8221;</em>. * An interview with <a href= "http://www.thewhitereview.org/interviews/interview-with-billy-childish-2/?utm_source=The+White+Review+Mailing+List&#038;utm_campaign=f869338edb-The_White_Review_SSP&#038;utm_medium=email">Billy Childish</a>: <em>&#8220;They ask for distinguishing marks on your passport and I wanted to have &#8216;tattoo on left-buttock&#8217;. So I thought I’d go for a Kurt Schwitters poem&#8221;</em>; <em>&#8220;The art galleries of today are set up for art tourism&#8221;</em>. * <a href= "http://www.youtube.com/user/SCARCITYOFTANKSBAND/videos?flow=grid&#038;view=1">Scarcity of Tanks</a>. * <a href= "http://www.anti-utopias.com/dynamic-tensions-a-discussion-between-taney-roniger-and-joseph-nechvatal/">Joseph Nechvatal</a> interviewed. * London&#8217;s <a href= "http://www.paulgormanis.com/?p=1942">Kings Road</a> in the summer of 1976. * An interview with <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/mar/01/steve-reich-schoenberg-coltrane-radiohead">Steve Reich</a>. * <a href= "http://julietjacques.tumblr.com/post/44730945219/gloriously-terrifyingly-surreal-video-for-b">The missing link between Wire and <em>Multi-Coloured Swap Shop</em></a>. * <a href= "http://www.adambiles.com/adam/Home.html">Adam Biles</a> and <a href= "http://www.badaude.typepad.com/">Joanna Walsh</a> talk about <strong>Paris</strong> on <a href= "http://3ampress.tumblr.com/post/44935194259/adam-biles-and-joanna-walsh-on-resonance-fm">Resonance FM</a>. * <a href= "https://www.archetypeme.com/article/my-dinner-auden-and-others">David Shields 1</a>. * <a href= "http://www.dazeddigital.com/artsandculture/article/15735/1/david-shields">David Shields 2</a>. * <a href= "http://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2013/03/06/shakedown-cossery-in-egypt/">Albert Cossery</a> in Egypt. * In praise of <a href= "http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2013/mar/08/my-hero-william-cobbett-richard-ingrams">William Cobbett</a>.</p>
<p>[Pic: <a href= "http://www.retronaut.com/2013/03/miss-atomic-bomb/">Miss Atomic Bomb, 1957</a>.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/the-missing-links-274/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
<enclosure url="http://ubumexico.centro.org.mx/sound/burroughs_william/RET/Burroughs-William_RET_3-04-We-Are-The-Night-Family.mp3" length="14278508" type="audio/mpeg" />
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
